See discussions, stats, and author profiles for this publication at: https://www.researchgate.net/publication/333246959 Chemical Constituents of Moss <Synonym>Macromitrium orthostichum</Synonym> Nees ex Schwgr.

ArticleinAsian Journal of Chemistry June 2019 DOI: 10.14233/ajchem..

CITATION <Compound>zeorin</Compound>, READS 32 <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, authors, including: Some of the authors of this publication are also working on these related projects: Hoyas of the <Location>Philippines View</Location> project Natural Products Derived from <Location>Philippine Plants View</Location> project Consolacion Ragasa De La Salle University 346 PUBLICATIONS,935 CITATIONS SEE PROFILE Virgilio Linis De La Salle University 16 PUBLICATIONS CITATIONS SEE PROFILE chien-chang Shen Eurofins, <Location>Belgium</Location> 126 PUBLICATIONS3 CITATIONS SEE PROFILE All content following this page was uploaded by Virgilio Linis on 22 May 2019.

The user has requested enhancement of the downloaded file.

A J CSIAN OURNAL OF HEMISTRY https://doi.org/10.14233/ajchem. .21992.

Macromitrium Brid is a large genus of pantropical mosses consisting of xerophytic epiphytes.

One member of this genus, <Synonym>Macromitrium orthostichum</Synonym> Nees ex Schwgr is restricted in <Location>Southeast Asia</Location> up to <Location>Papua New Guinea</Location> was recorded in <Location>Luzon</Location>, <Location>Mindoro</Location> and <Location>Mindanao</Location> islands in the <Location>Philippines</Location>.

Like other members of Macromitrium, this species is distinguished from other mosses by having creeping prostrate <PlantPart>stems</PlantPart> that give rise to rigid branches that terminate into sporophytes.

The plant of <Synonym>Macromitrium orthostichum</Synonym>, as in most members of Macromitrium, have some shades of reddish brown with <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> variously twisted and contorted around the branches.

<Synonym>Macromitrium orthostichum</Synonym> differs from other Macromitrium species by having papillose rhizoids arising along the basal <PlantPart>leaf</PlantPart> margins.

There is no report on the chemical constituents and biological activities of <Synonym>Macromitrium orthostichum</Synonym>.

Herein, the isolation of <Compound>zeorin</Compound> , <Compound>atranorin</Compound> and a mixture of <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> (Fig. ) from the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of <Synonym>Macromitrium orthostichum</Synonym> is reported.

To the best of our knowledge, this is the first report on the isolation of compounds <Compound>zeorin</Compound>, <Compound>atranorin</Compound>, <Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, from <Synonym>Macromitrium orthostichum</Synonym>.

Chemical Constituents of Moss <Synonym>Macromitrium orthostichum</Synonym> Nees ex Schwgr.

CONSOLACION Y. RAGASA <Compound>atranorin</Compound>, *, MARIA CARMEN S. TAN1, VIRGILIO C. LINIS and CHIEN-CHANG SHEN 1Department of Chemistry, De La Salle University, 2401 <Location>Taft Avenue</Location>, <Location>Manila</Location> 1004, <Location>Philippines</Location> 2Department of Chemistry, De La Salle University Science & Technology Complex, Leandro V. Locsin Campus, <Location>Binan City</Location>, <Location>Laguna</Location> 4024, <Location>Philippines</Location> 3Department of Biology, De La Salle University, 2401 <Location>Taft Avenue</Location>, <Location>Manila</Location> 1004, <Location>Philippines</Location> <Compound>4National</Compound> Research Institute of Chinese Medicine, Ministry of Health and Welfare, 155-1, Li-Nong St., <Location>Sec</Location>. , <Location>Taipei</Location>, <Location>Taiwan</Location> *Corresponding author: Tel./Fax: +63 <Compound>atranorin</Compound>, 5360230; E-mail: consolacion.ragasa@dlsu.edu.ph Received: 10 February 2019; Accepted: 29 April 2019; Published online: 21 May 2019; AJC-19426 Chemical investigation of <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of moss <Synonym>Macromitrium orthostichum</Synonym> Nees ex Schwgr has led to the isolation of <Compound>zeorin</Compound> , <Compound>atranorin</Compound> and a mixture of <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> in about 1:1 ratio.

The structure of compound <Compound>zeorin</Compound>, was elucidated by extensive 1D and 2D NMR spectroscopy, while compounds <Compound>atranorin</Compound>, <Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, were identified by comparison of their NMR data with literature data.

Keywords: <Synonym>Macromitrium orthostichum</Synonym>, <Family>Orthotrichaceae</Family>, <Compound>Zeorin</Compound>, <Compound>Atranorin</Compound>, <Compound>beta-Sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>Stigmasterol</Compound>.

Asian Journal of Chemistry; Vol. , No. (2019), 1626-1628 This is an open access journal, and articles are distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, 0 (CC BY-NC-SA <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, 0) International License which allows readers to freely read, download, copy, distribute, print, search, or link to the full texts of its articles and to use them for any other lawful non-commercial purpose as long as the original source is duly acknowledged.

EXPERIMENTAL NMR spectra were recorded on a Varian VNMRS spectrometer in CDCl at 600 MHz for 1H NMR and 150 MHz for 13C NMR spectra.

Column chromatography was performed with silica gel 60 (70-230 mesh).

Thin layer chromatography was performed with plastic backed plates coated with silica gel F254 and the plates were visualized by spraying with <Compound>vanillin</Compound>/H2SO4 solution followed by warming.

Sample collection: The Philippine specimen chosen for present investigation was gathered from a tree branch on a mossy forest at <Location>Mount Natib</Location>'s Peak, <Location>Morong</Location>, <Location>Bataan</Location>, <Location>Philippines</Location> on 19th December 2017.

The specimen was collected and authenticated as <Synonym>Macromitrium orthostichum</Synonym> Nees ex Schwgr by one of the authors (VCL).

General isolation procedure: A glass column 12 inches in height with 0.5 inches in internal diameter was used for the fractionation of the crude <Preparation>extract</Preparation>.

Fractions of 10 mL volumes were collected and monitored by thin layer chromatography.

Fractions containing spots with similar Rf values were combined and rechromatographed using the appropriate solvent.

Final purification was carried out using Pasteur pipette as the column, collecting <Compound>zeorin</Compound>, mL fractions.

TLC-pure isolates were combined, and after evaporation of the solvent were subjected to NMR analysis.

Isolation of chemical constituents of <Synonym>Macromitrium orthostichum</Synonym>: The freeze-dried <Synonym>Macromitrium orthostichum</Synonym> (17.81 g) was <Preparation>ground</Preparation> in a blender, soaked in CH2Cl2 for three days and then <Preparation>filtered</Preparation>.

The filtrate was concentrated under vacuum to afford a crude <Preparation>extract</Preparation> (0.1723 g) which was chromatographed by gradient elution using increasing proportions of <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 at 10 % increment.

The fraction eluted with 40 % <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 was rechromatographed using 10 % EtOAc in petroleum ether to afford a mixture of compounds <Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound>, and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, <Compound>atranorin</Compound>, mg) after washing with petroleum ether.

The 50 % <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed using 15 % EtOAc in petroleum ether, followed by CH3CN:Et2O:CH2Cl2 (0.5:0.5:9, v/v).

The fractions eluted with 15 % <Compound>ethyl acetate</Compound> in petroleum ether were combined and rechromatographed using the same solvent to afford compound <Compound>zeorin</Compound>, (0.7 mg) after washing with petroleum ether.

The fractions eluted with CH3CN:Et2O: CH2Cl2 (0.5:0.5:9, v/v) was rechromatographed using the same solvent to yield compound <Compound>atranorin</Compound>, (0 <Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound>, mg) after washing with petroleum ether.

<Compound>Zeorin</Compound> : 1H NMR (600 MHz, CDCl): 0.74 (3H, s, H-28), 0.85 (3H, s, H-25), 0.96 (3H, s, H-27), <Compound>zeorin</Compound>, 00 (3H, s, H-26), <Compound>zeorin</Compound>, 02 (3H, s, H-23), <Compound>zeorin</Compound>, 13 (3H, s, H-24), <Compound>zeorin</Compound>, 16 (3H, s, H-29), <Compound>zeorin</Compound>, 19 (3H, s, H-30), <Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound>, 94 (1H, dt, J = <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, <Compound>atranorin</Compound>, 10.

Hz, H-6).

C NMR (150 MHz, CDCl): 40.33 (C-1), 18.50 (C-2), 43.79 (C-3), 33.60 (C-4), 61.07 (C-5), 69.30 (C-6), 45.48 (C-7), 42.85 (C-8), 49.41 (C-9), 39.33 (C-10), 21.03 (C-11), 23.98 (C-12), 49.77 (C-13), 41.86 (C-14), 34.32 (C-15), 21.90 (C-16), 53.94 (C17), 43.99 (C-18), 41.21 (C-19), 26.58 (C-20), 51.05 (C-21), 73.90 (C-22), 36.73 (C-23), 22.10 (C-24), 17.11 (C-25), 18.25 (C-26), 17.05 (C-27), 16.07 (C-28), 28.75 (C-29), 30.87 (C-30).

<Compound>Atranorin</Compound> : 1H NMR (600 MHz, CDCl): 6.38 (1H, s, H-5), 10.34 (1H, s, H-8), <Compound>atranorin</Compound>, 67 (3H, s, H-9), 6.50 (1H, s, H-6'), <Compound>atranorin</Compound>, 07 (3H, s, H-8'), <Compound>atranorin</Compound>, 53 (3H, s, H-9'), <Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound>, 97 (3H, s, OCH3) 12.48 (1H, s, 2-OH), 12.53 (1H, s, 4-OH), 11.92 (1H, s, 3'-OH).

<Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound> : 1H NMR (600 MHz, CDCl): <Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound>, 50 (1H, m, H-3), 5.35 (1H, d, J = <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, Hz, H-5), 0.66 (3H, s, H-18), 0.99 (3H, s, H-19), 0.93 (3H, d, J = 6. Hz, H-21), 0.84 (3H, d, J = 6. Hz, H-26), 0.83 (3H, d, J = 6. Hz, H-27), 0.86 (3H, t, J = 6. Hz, H-29).

<Compound>Stigmasterol</Compound> : 1H NMR (600 MHz, CDCl): <Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound>, 50 (1H, m, H-3), 5.33 (1H, d, J = <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, Hz, H-5), 0.68 (3H, s, H-18), 0.99 (3H, s, H-19), <Compound>zeorin</Compound>, 01 (3H, d, J = 6. Hz, H-21), 5.13 (1H, dd, J = 8 <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, 15.

Hz, H-22), 5.00 (1H, dd, J = 8 <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, 15.0, H-23), 0.84 (3H, d, J = 6. Hz, H-26), 0.83 (3H, d, J = 6. Hz, H-27), 0.80 (3H, t, J = 6. Hz, H-29)..

Silica gel chromatography of the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of <Synonym>Macromitrium orthostichum</Synonym> afforded <Compound>zeorin</Compound> , <Compound>atranorin</Compound> and a mixture of <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> in about 1:1 ratio.

The structure of compound <Compound>zeorin</Compound>, was elucidated by extensive 1D and 2D NMR spectroscopy and confirmed by comparison of its NMR data with those reported in the literature.

The NMR data of compound <Compound>atranorin</Compound>, were in accordance with those reported in the literature for <Compound>atranorin</Compound> ; compound <Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound>, for <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> and compound <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, for <Compound>strigmasterol</Compound>.

The 1:1 ratio of compounds <Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound>, and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, was deduced from the intensities and integrations of the 1H NMR resonances for olefinic protons at 5.35 (d, J = <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, Hz, H-5) and methyl protons at 0.66 (s) for compound <Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound>, and olefinic protons at 5.35 (d, J = <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, Hz, H-5), 5.13 (dd, J = 8 <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, 15.

Hz) and 5.00 (dd, J = 8 <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, 15.

Hz) and the methyl protons at 0.68 (s) for compound <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>,

Although there is no reported biological activity for <Synonym>Macromitrium orthostichum</Synonym>, the compounds isolated from the plant were reported to possess diverse activities.

<Compound>Zeorin</Compound> and <Compound>atranorin</Compound> exhibited antidiabetic and <BioAct>antioxidant</BioAct> activities.

Compound <Compound>zeorin</Compound>, exhibited strong <BioAct>antibacterial</BioAct> and <BioAct>antifungal</BioAct> activities.

On the other <BodyPart>hand</BodyPart>, compound <Compound>atranorin</Compound>, showed antiproliferative action against malignant cell lines , possessed <BioAct>antinociceptive</BioAct> OH H H H OH H OHO HO CH3 O O H3C OH CH3 O O CH3 H <Compound>atranorin</Compound>, <Compound>zeorin</Compound>, 1 <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, 6 10 11 13 18 21 22 23 25 26 27 28 29 24 30 HO <Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound>, HO <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, Fig..

Chemical structures of <Compound>zeorin</Compound> , <Compound>atranorin</Compound> , <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> from the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of <Synonym>Macromitrium orthostichum</Synonym> Vol. , No. (2019) Chemical Constituents of Moss <Synonym>Macromitrium orthostichum</Synonym> Nees ex Schwgr. effects , exhibited antibiotic action against <Synonym>Macromitrium aurum</Synonym> , inhibited <Compound>leukotriene</Compound> B4 synthesis in leukocytes , and modulated the <Illness>wound</Illness> healing process.

<Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound> inhibited the growth of human <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> <CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine> and MDAMB adenocarcinoma cells ; was effective for the treatment of benign prostatic hyperplasia ; showed potential as an <BioAct>anticancer</BioAct> drug for colon carcinogenesis ; reduced intestinal cholesterol uptake ; and induced apoptosis mediated by the activation of ERK and the downregulation of Akt in MCA-102 <Compound>murine</Compound> fibrosarcoma cells.

On the other <BodyPart>hand</BodyPart>, <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> showed therapeutic efficacy against Ehrlich ascites carcinoma in mice ; lowered plasma cholesterol levels, inhibited cholesterol absorption, and suppressed hepatic cholesterol and classic <Compound>bile acid</Compound> synthesis in rats ; showed cytostatic activity against Hep2 and <CellLine>McCoy</CellLine> cells ; markedly inhibited tumour promotion ; exhibited <BioAct>antimutagenic</BioAct> , topical <BioAct>anti-inflammatory</BioAct> , antiosteoarthritic and <BioAct>antioxidant</BioAct> activities. .S A research grant from the De La Salle University Science Foundation through the URCO is gratefully acknowledged.

CONFLICT OF INTEREST The authors declare that there is no conflict of interests regarding the publication of this article.