Available online www.jocpr.com Journal of Chemical and Pharmaceutical Research, 2014, 6:1318-1320 Research Article ISSN : 0975-7384 <Location>CODEN</Location>(<Location>USA</Location>) : JCPRC 1318 Chemical constituents of the <PlantPart>bark</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Aleurites moluccana</Synonym> L. Willd.

Agnes B. Alimboyoguen, Kathlia A. De Castro-Cruz, Chien-Chang Shen, Wen-Tai Li2 and Consolacion Y. Ragasa,4* <Compound>1School</Compound> of Chemical Engineering and Chemistry, Mapa Institute of Technology, Muralla St., Intramuros, <Location>Manila</Location> 1002 <Location>Philippines</Location> <Compound>2National</Compound> Research Institute of Chinese Medicine, 155-1, Li-Nong St., <Location>Sec</Location>. , <Location>Taipei</Location> 112, <Location>Taiwan</Location> 3Chemistry Department, De La Salle University Science & Technology Complex Leandro V. Locsin Campus, <Location>Binan City</Location>, <Location>Laguna</Location> 4024, <Location>Philippines</Location> 4Chemistry Department, De La Salle University, 2401 <Location>Taft Avenue</Location>, <Location>Manila</Location>, 1004 <Location>Philippines</Location>.

. The <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of the <PlantPart>bark</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Aleurites moluccana</Synonym> L. Willd afforded <Compound>12-hydroxy-13-methoxy-8,11,13podocarpatrien-3-one</Compound> , <Compound>spruceanol</Compound> , <Compound>3-acetylaleuritolic acid</Compound> , <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound> and a mixture of <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> in a 4:1 ratio.

The structures of <Compound>Hydroxy-13-methoxy-8,11,13-podocarpatrien-3-one</Compound>, <Compound>spruceanol</Compound>, <Compound>3-acetyl aleuritolic acid</Compound>, were elucidated by extensive 1D and 2D NMR spectroscopy.

Keywords <Synonym>Aleurites moluccana</Synonym> L. Willd., <Family>Euphorbiaceae</Family>, <MedicinalPlant>lumbang</MedicinalPlant> <PlantPart>bark</PlantPart>, <Compound>12-hydroxy-13-methoxy-8,11,13podocarpatrien-3-one</Compound>, <Compound>spruceanol</Compound>, <Compound>3-acetylaleuritolic acid</Compound>.

. <Synonym>Aleurites moluccana</Synonym> [L] Willd of the family <Family>Euphorbiaceae</Family>, commonly known as <MedicinalPlant>lumbang</MedicinalPlant> is an indigenous tree in <Location>Southeast Asia</Location> which grows naturally in forest areas and abandoned lands at low and medium altitudes.

Many parts of the tree including the <PlantPart>seeds</PlantPart>, <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart>, <PlantPart>flowers</PlantPart>, and <PlantPart>bark</PlantPart> are frequently used in traditional medicine.

<Preparation>Decoction</Preparation> of the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> and <PlantPart>bark</PlantPart> are usually administered to treat headaches, <Illness>fever</Illness>, hypocholesterolemia, tumors, <Illness>diarrhea</Illness> and <Illness>dysentery</Illness>.

The <PlantPart>flowers</PlantPart> and sap of <Synonym>Aleurites moluccana</Synonym> are commonly used in maintaining dental hygiene , while the <PlantPart>seed</PlantPart> oil is a laxative stimulant and sometimes used like castor oil.

An earlier study reported the isolation of swertisin from the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart>, and <Compound>acetyl aleuritolic acid</Compound> from the <PlantPart>bark</PlantPart> which were found to exhibit <BioAct>antimicrobial</BioAct> properties.

<Compound>Moluccanin</Compound>, a coumarinolignoid from <Synonym>Aleurites moluccana</Synonym> exhibited anti-bacterial and <BioAct>antiviral</BioAct> activities.

Another study reported the isolation of three novel <Compound>3-acetyl aleuritolic acid</Compound>, 4-seco-podocarpane-type trinorditerpenoids: <Compound>moluccanic acid</Compound>, moluccanic <Compound>acid methyl ester</Compound> and <Compound>6,7-dehydromoluccanic acid</Compound> from the <PlantPart>twigs</PlantPart> and <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of the tree which were found to possess cytotoxicity effects.

Furthermore, four new podocarpane-type trinorditerpenes were isolated from the <PlantPart>twigs</PlantPart> and <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Aleurites moluccana</Synonym>.

Recently, five megastigmanes namely, (<Compound>6S,9R)roseoside</Compound>, <Compound>vomifoliol-9-O-beta-apiofuranosyl-beta-glucopyranoside</Compound>, <Compound>3-oxo-alpha-ionol-O-beta-apiofuranosyl-beta-glucopyranoside</Compound>, <Compound>3-oxo-alpha-ionol-O-beta-glucopyranoside</Compound>, and <Compound>debiloside</Compound> were isolated from the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Aleurites moluccana</Synonym>.

In this study, the isolation and structure elucidation of <Compound>12-hydroxy-13-methoxy-8,11,13-podocarpatrien-3-one</Compound> , <Compound>spruceanol</Compound> , and <Compound>3-acetylaleuritolic acid</Compound> (Fig. ), along with <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> from the CH2Cl2 <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of the air-dried <PlantPart>bark</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Aleurites moluccana</Synonym> [L] Willd are reported.

Consolacion Y. Ragasa et al J. <Location>Chem</Location>.

Pharm. Res., 2014, 6:1318-1320.

1319 CH3 OH <Compound>spruceanol</Compound>, AcO <Compound>3-acetyl aleuritolic acid</Compound>, 3 810 18 20 11 13 <Compound>Hydroxy-13-methoxy-8,11,13-podocarpatrien-3-one</Compound>, HO CH3 <Compound>Hydroxy-13-methoxy-8,11,13-podocarpatrien-3-one</Compound>, 6 11 14 18 20 24 27 30 <Compound>Hydroxy-13-methoxy-8,11,13-podocarpatrien-3-one</Compound>, 4 8 11 14 18 20 15 17 H O OCH3 OH <Compound>Hydroxy-13-methoxy-8,11,13-podocarpatrien-3-one</Compound>, Fig..

Chemical constituents of <Synonym>Aleurites moluccana</Synonym> <PlantPart>bark</PlantPart>: <Compound>12-hydroxy-13-methoxy-8,11,13-podocarpatrien-3-one</Compound> , <Compound>spruceanol</Compound> , and <Compound>3-acetylaleuritolic acid</Compound> EXPERIMENTAL SECTION General Experimental Procedures NMR spectra were recorded on a Varian VNMRS spectometer in CDCl at 600 MHz for 1H NMR and 150 MHz for 13C NMR spectra.

Column chromatography was performed with silica gel 60 (70-230 mesh).

Thin layer chromtography was performed wih plastic backed plates coated with silica gel F254 and the plates were visualized by spraying with <Compound>vanillin</Compound>/H2SO4 followed by warming.

Sample Collection The <PlantPart>bark</PlantPart> sample was collected at the <Location>Cavite</Location> State University, <Location>Indang</Location>, <Location>Cavite</Location> in September, 2011.

The <PlantPart>bark</PlantPart> was identified as <Synonym>Aleurites moluccana</Synonym> [L] Willd at the Philippine National Museum and stored at the <Location>Cavite</Location> State University Research Center Laboratory.

Isolation The air-dried <PlantPart>bark</PlantPart> <Compound>Hydroxy-13-methoxy-8,11,13-podocarpatrien-3-one</Compound>, 1 kg) of <Synonym>Aleurites moluccana</Synonym> was <Preparation>ground</Preparation> in a blender, soaked in CH2Cl2 for three days and then <Preparation>filtered</Preparation>.

The filtrate was concentrated under vacuum to afford a crude <Preparation>extract</Preparation> (78.7 g) which was chromatograped using increasing proportions of <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 at 10% increment.

The 30% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed using 10% EtOAc in petroleum ether, followed by 12.5% EtOAc in petroleum ether, and finally 15% EtOAc in petroleum ether as eluents.

The fractions eluted with 10% EtOAc in petroleum ether were combined and rechromatographed (4 ) in the same solvent to afford <Compound>triglycerides</Compound> (4 mg).

The fractions eluted with 12.5% EtOAc in petroleum ether were combined and rechromatographed (5 ) in the same solvent to afford <Compound>polyprenols</Compound> (7 mg) after washing with petroleum ether.

The fractions eluted with 15% EtOAc in petroleum ether were combined and rechromatographed <Compound>3-acetyl aleuritolic acid</Compound>, ) in the same solvent to afford a mixture of <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> (5 mg) after washing with petroleum ether.

The 40% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed (10 ) using 10% EtOAc in petroleum ether to afford <Compound>Hydroxy-13-methoxy-8,11,13-podocarpatrien-3-one</Compound>, (6 mg).

The air-dried <PlantPart>bark</PlantPart> (0.90 kg) of <Synonym>Aleurites moluccana</Synonym> was <Preparation>ground</Preparation> in a blender, soaked in CH2Cl2 for three days and then <Preparation>filtered</Preparation>.

The filtrate was concentrated under vacuum to afford a crude <Preparation>extract</Preparation> (52.9 g) which was chromatograped using increasing proportions of <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 at 10% increment.

The 10% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed (9 ) using 10% EtOAc in petroleum ether to afford <Compound>3-acetyl aleuritolic acid</Compound>, (7 mg).

The 40% and 50% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fractions were combined and rechromatographed (11 ) using Et2O:CH3CN:CH2Cl2 (0.5:0.5:9) to afford <Compound>spruceanol</Compound>, (5 mg). -<Compound>hydroxy-13-methoxy-8,11,13-podocarpatrien-3-one</Compound> : colorless solid.

C NMR (150 MHz, CDCl): 37.62 (C-1), 34.65 (C-2), 217.37 (C-3), 47.28 (C-4), 50.64 (C-5), 20.38 (C-6), 30.60 (C-7), 127.35 (C-8), 140.16 (C-9), 36.94 (C-10), 110.51 (C-11), 143.78 (C-12), 144.71 (C-13), 111.22 (C-14), 26.89 (C-18), 21.04 (C-19), 24.48 (C20), 55.81 (OCH3).

<Compound>Spruceanol</Compound> : colorless solid.

C NMR (150 MHz, CDCl): 37.33 (C-1), 27.98 (C-2), 78.74 (C-3), 38.96 (C4), 49.32 (C-5), 18.93 (C-6), 29.27 (C-7), 125.20 (C-8), 147.79 (C-9), 37.57 (C-10), 109.68 (C-11), 151.98 (C-12), 119.07 (C-13), 139.20 (C-14), 135.42 (C-15), 119.55 (C-16), 12.83 (C-17), 28.04 (C-18), 15.34 (C-19), 24.81 (C20). -Acetylaleuritolic acid : colorless solid.

C NMR (150 MHz, CDCl): 37.37 (C-1), 23.45 (C-2), 80.87 (C-3), 37.67 (C-4), 55.58 (C-5), 18.72 (C-6), 40.75 (C-7), 39.02 (C-8), 49.05 (C-9), 37.92 (C-10), 17.30 (C-11), 33.65 (C12), 37.31 (C-13), 160.57 (C-14), 116.78 (C-15), 31.33 (C-16), 51.42 (C-17), 41.43 (C-18), 35.32 (C-19), 29.29 (CConsolacion Y. Ragasa et al J. <Location>Chem</Location>.

Pharm. Res., 2014, 6:1318-1320.

1320 20), 33.31 (C-21), 30.70 (C-22), 27.94 (C-23), 16.58 (C-24), 15.62 (C-25), 26.17 (C-26), 22.43 (C-27), 183.56 (C28), 31.86 (C-29), 28.66 (C-30), 170.99, 21.30 (OAc)..

Silica gel chromatography of the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of the <PlantPart>bark</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Aleurites moluccana</Synonym> afforded <Compound>12-hydroxy-13methoxy-8,11,13-podocarpatrien-3-one</Compound> , <Compound>spruceanol</Compound> , and <Compound>3-acetylaleuritolic acid</Compound> .

The structures of <Compound>Hydroxy-13-methoxy-8,11,13-podocarpatrien-3-one</Compound>, <Compound>spruceanol</Compound>, <Compound>3-acetyl aleuritolic acid</Compound>, were elucidated by extensive 1D and 2D NMR spectroscopy. -<Compound>Hydroxy-13-methoxy-8,11,13-podocarpatrien-3-one</Compound> , <Compound>spruceanol</Compound> and <Compound>3-acetyl aleuritolic acid</Compound> were earlier reported as constituents of <Synonym>Aleurites moluccana</Synonym>.

<ChemicalClass>Diterpene</ChemicalClass> <Compound>spruceanol</Compound>, was first reported as a constituent of the <PlantPart>root</PlantPart> and <PlantPart>bark</PlantPart> of Cunuria spruceana which exhibited <BioAct>cytotoxic</BioAct> and antitumor activity.

The structure of <Compound>3-acetyl aleuritolic acid</Compound>, was confirmed by comparison of its 13C NMR data with those reported in the literature for <Compound>3-acetylaleuritolic acid</Compound>.

<ChemicalClass>Triterpene</ChemicalClass> <Compound>3-acetyl aleuritolic acid</Compound>, exhibited <BioAct>antimicrobial</BioAct> activity against <Synonym>S. aureus</Synonym> and <Synonym>S. typhimurium</Synonym> ; significant inhibitory activity on vitality of adult male worms of <Synonym>O. gutturosa</Synonym> ; strong inhibition of DNA topoisomerase II and high cytotoxicity against human lung carcinoma A549 cells.

The structures of <Compound>polyprenols</Compound> , <Compound>triglycerides</Compound> , <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> , were confirmed by comparison of their 13C NMR data with those reported in the literature.

REFFERENCES JA Duke, Handbook of Medicinal Herbs, CRC Press, <Location>USA</Location>, 1991, 29.

VC Filho; TMB <Compound>Bresolin</Compound>; CMS Bittencourt; MM Souza; RM Lucinda; NLM Quinto; TC Mora; R Spricigo; C Picolli; M Nita; M Pesreira, 2008, Patente PI 0804525-9 A2 (22).

C Meyre-Silva; TC Mora; MW Biavatti; AR Santos; J Dal-Magro; RA Yunes; V <Location>Cechinel-Filho</Location>, <Location>Phytomed.</Location>, 1998, 5, 109-113.

C Meyre-Silva; TC Mora; AR Soares Santos; J Dal Magro; RA Yunes; F Delle Monache; V <Location>Cechinel-Filho</Location>, Acta Farm.

Bonaerense, 1997, 16 , 169-72.

T Shamsuddin; W Rahman; SA Khan; KM Shamsuddin; JB Kintzinger, <Location>Phytochem.</Location>, 1988, 27, 1908-1909.

CP Locher; MT Burch; HE Mower; J Berestecky; H Davis; B Van-Poel; A Lasure; DA Vanden-Berghe; AJ Vlietinck, J. <Compound>Ethnopharmacol</Compound>., 1995, 49, 23-32.

CP Locher; M Witvrouw; MP Bethune; MT Burch; HE Mower; H Davis; A Lasure; R Pauwels; E Clercq; AJ Vlietinck, <Location>Phytomed.</Location>, 1996, <Compound>spruceanol</Compound>, 259-264.

H Liu; Y Di; J Yang; F Teng; Y Lu; W Ni; X Hao, Tetrahedron Lett., 2008, 49, 5150-5151.

H-Y Liu, S-J Li, Y Zhao, W Ni, X-J Hao, J-Z Li, Y Hu, B-B Xie, C Qing, C-X Chen.

Helv. Chim.

Acta, 2007, 90, 2017-223.

D Silva; B Fernandes; E Felipe, L Ferreira; DR Callejon; TGuaratini, Biochem.

Syst. <Compound>Ecol</Compound>., 2012, 40, 34-37.

DB Da Silva; EFA, Fernandes; LS Ferreira; DR Callejon; T Guaratini; JNC Lopes; C Meyre-Silva; VC Filho; NP Lopes, Biochem.

Syst. <Compound>Ecol</Compound>. , 40, 34-37.

SP Gunasekera; GA Cordel; NR Farnsworth, J. Nat.

Prod., 1979, 42, 658-662.

S Prachayasittikul; S Suphapong; A Worachartcheewan; R Lawung; S Ruchirawat; V Prachayasittikul, Molecules,, 2009, 14, 850-867.

MY Peres; F Delle Monache; AB Cruz; MG Pizzolatti; RAJ Yunes J. <Compound>Ethnopharmacol</Compound>. , 56, 223-226.

B Nyasse; I Ngantchou; JJ Nono; B Schneider, Nat.

Prod. Res., 2006, 20, 39<Compound>Hydroxy-13-methoxy-8,11,13-podocarpatrien-3-one</Compound>, <Compound>spruceanol</Compound>, <Compound>3-acetyl aleuritolic acid</Compound>, 97.

S Wada; R Tanaka, <Location>Chem</Location>.

Biodivers., 2006, <Compound>3-acetyl aleuritolic acid</Compound>, 473-479.

JA Rideout ; CY Ragasa; H-T Ngo, ACGC <Location>Chem</Location> Res Commun., 2003, 16, 40-47.

CY Ragasa; GS Lorena; EH Mandia; DD Raga; C-C Shen, Amer.

J. Essent.

Oils Nat.

Prod., 2013, <Compound>Hydroxy-13-methoxy-8,11,13-podocarpatrien-3-one</Compound>, 7-10.

J-MC Cayme; CY Ragasa, <Location>Kimika</Location>, 2004, 20 <Compound>Hydroxy-13-methoxy-8,11,13-podocarpatrien-3-one</Compound>, <Compound>spruceanol</Compound>, , 5-12.