Available online on www.ijppr.com International Journal of Pharmacognosy and Phytochemical Research 2016; 8; 668-674 ISSN: 0975-4873 Research Article *Author for Correspondence <BioAct>Cytotoxic</BioAct> Compounds from <Synonym>Dysoxylum gaudichaudianum</Synonym> (A. Juss.) Miq.

<Location>Mariquit</Location> M. De Los Reyes <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, , Glenn G. Oyong, Vincent Antonio S. Ng4, Chien-Chang Shen and Consolacion Y. Ragasa,6 1Biology Department, De La Salle University Science & Technology Complex, Leandro V. Locsin Campus, <Location>Binan City</Location>, <Location>Laguna</Location> 4024, <Location>Philippines</Location> 2Biology Department, De La Salle University, 2401 <Location>Taft Avenue</Location>, <Location>Manila</Location> 0922, <Location>Philippines</Location> 3Center for Natural Science and Environmental Research, De La Salle University, 2401 <Location>Taft Avenue</Location>, <Location>Manila</Location> 0922, <Location>Philippines</Location> 4Chemistry Department, De La Salle University, 2401 <Location>Taft Avenue</Location>, <Location>Manila</Location> 0922, <Location>Philippines</Location> <Compound>5National</Compound> Research Institute of Chinese Medicine, Ministry of Health and Welfare, 155-1, Li-Nong St., <Location>Sec</Location>. , <Location>Taipei</Location> 112, <Location>Taiwan</Location> 6Chemistry Department, De La Salle University Science & Technology Complex, Leandro V. Locsin Campus, <Location>Binan City</Location>, <Location>Laguna</Location> 4024, <Location>Philippines</Location> Available Online: 31st March, 2016.

<Compound>Squalene</Compound> , <Compound>polyprenol</Compound> , <Compound>triglycerides</Compound> , and <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> , isolated from the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Dysoxylum gaudichaudianum</Synonym>, were evaluated for their <BioAct>anti-proliferative</BioAct> activities against three human cancer cell lines, <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> (<CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine>) and colon (<CellLine>HT-29</CellLine> and <CellLine>HCT-116</CellLine>), and a normal cell line, human dermal fibroblast neonatal (<CellLine>HDFn</CellLine>) using the in vitro PrestoBlue cell viability assay.

The <CellLine>HT-29</CellLine> cell line was most susceptible to the compounds tested.

<Compound>Squalene</Compound> and <Compound>polyprenol</Compound> were most <BioAct>cytotoxic</BioAct> against <CellLine>HT-29</CellLine> (IC50 of 0.84 and <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, 059 g/mL, respectively), followed by <CellLine>MCF7</CellLine> (IC50 of <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, 404 and <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, 786 g/mL, respectively), and <CellLine>HCT-116</CellLine> (IC50 of 7.859 and 9.258 g/mL, respectively).

<Compound>Triglycerides</Compound> was highly <BioAct>anti-proliferative</BioAct> against <CellLine>HT-29</CellLine> cells (IC50 of <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, 738 g/mL) and moderately inhibitory against <CellLine>HCT-116</CellLine> and <CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine> cells (IC50 of 13.05 and 16.12 g/mL, respectively).

<Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound> was most <BioAct>cytotoxic</BioAct> against <CellLine>HT29</CellLine> and <CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine> (IC50 of <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, 41 and <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, 277 g/mL, respectively) and moderately <BioAct>cytotoxic</BioAct> against <CellLine>HCT-116</CellLine> (IC50 of 11.63 g/mL).

Comparing the <BioAct>cytotoxic</BioAct> effects of these compounds against the three cancer cell lines, <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, were most <BioAct>cytotoxic</BioAct> against <CellLine>HT-29</CellLine>.

Compounds <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, and <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, were less inhibitory to <CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine> and least inhibitory to <CellLine>HCT-116</CellLine>.

Comparing the effects of <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, on the two colon cancer cell lines, their IC50 values against <CellLine>HT-29</CellLine> were lower than those of <CellLine>HCT-116</CellLine>.

Compounds <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, showed moderate cytotoxicity against <CellLine>HDFn</CellLine> cells (11.18 to 17.72 g/mL) and were less <BioAct>cytotoxic</BioAct> to the normal cells than the cancer cells.

Keywords: <Synonym>Dysoxylum gaudichaudianum</Synonym> (A. Juss.) Miq., <Compound>squalene</Compound>, <Compound>polyprenol</Compound>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, cytotoxicity, <CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine>, <CellLine>HCT-116</CellLine>, <CellLine>HT-29</CellLine>, <CellLine>HDFn</CellLine>.

<Synonym>Dysoxylum gaudichaudianum</Synonym> (A. Juss.) Miq of the family <Family>Meliaceae</Family> may be found in thickets and primary and secondary lowland forests up to <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, 800 m asl in many parts of the <Location>Philippines</Location> where it is locally known as <MedicinalPlant>igyo</MedicinalPlant>, and in other Malesian regions down to <Location>Samoa</Location>.

Commonly known as <MedicinalPlant>ivory mahogany</MedicinalPlant>, the mature plant may be used as a general purpose timber.

In traditional folk medicine, <Preparation>decoction</Preparation> of chopped <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> and <PlantPart>bark</PlantPart> are used to treat <Illness>coughs</Illness>, <Illness>skin irritations</Illness>, <Illness>body aches</Illness>, <Illness>lung hemorrhage</Illness>, and sexually transmitted diseases and are also used to induce vomiting after <Illness>food poisoning</Illness>,. In addition, it was reported that the <Preparation>juice</Preparation> <Preparation>extracted</Preparation> from the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> may be used as an early abortifacient.

In another study, the plant's <PlantPart>bark</PlantPart> yielded four new compounds, <Compound>dysoxylins A</Compound>, <Compound>dysoxylins B</Compound>, <Compound>dysoxylins C</Compound>, and <Compound>dysoxylins D</Compound>, belonging to the <ChemicalClass>tetranortriterpenoid</ChemicalClass> family, which demonstrated strong bioactivity against anti-respiratory syncytial virus (RSV)6,7. Structure elucidation of isolates from hexane and choloroform extracts of the plant's <PlantPart>stem bark</PlantPart> yielded <Compound>p-hydroxyacetophenone</Compound>, <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>.

A new limonoid, <Compound>gaudichaudysolin A</Compound>solated from the plant's <PlantPart>bark</PlantPart>, was evaluated in vitro for its <BioAct>cytotoxic</BioAct> effects against five human cancer cell lines: <CellLine>HL60</CellLine> (human blood premyelocytic leukemia), <CellLine>RPMI</CellLine> (multiple myeloma), <CellLine>NCI-H226</CellLine> (non-small cell lung carcinoma), <CellLine>HCT116</CellLine> (human colon cancer), and <CellLine>MCF7</CellLine> (human <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> adenocarcinoma) cells.

This study was conducted as part of our research on the chemical constituents of the genus Dysoxylum found in the <Location>Philippines</Location>.

We earlier reported the isolation of new glabretal-type <ChemicalClass>triterpenoids</ChemicalClass> along with the known <Location>Mariquit</Location> et al. /<BioAct>Cytotoxic</BioAct> Compounds from <Location>IJPPR</Location>, Volume 8, Issue 4: April 2016 Page 669 compounds, <Compound>24,25-epoxy-3Beta,23-dihydroxy-7-tirucallene</Compound>, <Compound>squalene</Compound>, <Compound>polyprenol</Compound>, <Compound>linoleic acid</Compound> and <Compound>lutein</Compound> from the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Dysoxylum mollissimum</Synonym> Blume.

Recently, we reported that the crude <Compound>dicloromethane</Compound> <PlantPart>leaf</PlantPart> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of <Synonym>Dysoxylum gaudichaudianum</Synonym> (A. Juss.) Miq exhibited IC50 values of 7.35 and 13.19 g/mL against <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> cancer (<CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine>) and colon cancer (<CellLine>HT-29</CellLine>) cells, respectively.

Chemical investigation of the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> <PlantPart>leaf</PlantPart> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> led to the isolation of <Compound>squalene</Compound> , <Compound>polyprenols</Compound> , <Compound>triglycerides</Compound> , and <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> 11.

We report herein Figure 1: Chemical structures of <Compound>squalene</Compound> , <Compound>polyprenols</Compound> , <Compound>triglycerides</Compound> , and <Compound>beta-Sitosterol</Compound> from the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Dysoxylum gaudichaudianum</Synonym>.

Figure 2: Dose-response curves showing the <BioAct>cytotoxic</BioAct> activities of <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, and <Location>Zeocin</Location> on the cell viability of <CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine>, <CellLine>HCT-116</CellLine>, <CellLine>HT-29</CellLine> and <CellLine>HDFn</CellLine>.

Each plot shows the effect of <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, and <Location>Zeocin</Location> against each cell line.

Data shown are means of triplicates.

GraphPad Prism 6.07 was used to perform extra sum-of-squares F test to (A) evaluate if the best-fit parameter (half maximal inhibitory concentration) differs among data sets (treatments), and (B) determine the differences among the dose-response curve fits.

The results are: <CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine> (A) F (DFn, DFd) = F (5, 124) = <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, 864, p = 0.0027 and (B) F (10, 124) = 5.384, p < 0.0001; <CellLine>HCT-116</CellLine> (A) F (5, 116) = 9.586, p < 0.0001 and (B) F (10, 116) = 5.080, p < 0.0001; <CellLine>HT-29</CellLine> (A) F (5, 124) = 5.644, p = 0.0001 and (B) F (10, 124) = 6.194, p < 0.0001; <CellLine>HDFn</CellLine> (A) F (5, 124) = 11.35, p < 0.0001 and (B) F (10, 124) = 6.025, p < 0.

0001.

<Location>Mariquit</Location> et al. /<BioAct>Cytotoxic</BioAct> Compounds from <Location>IJPPR</Location>, Volume 8, Issue 4: April 2016 Page 670 the cytotoxicity studies on <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, (Figure <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, isolated from the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Dysoxylum gaudichaudianum</Synonym>.

To the best of our knowledge this is the first report on the IC50 values of <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, and <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, against <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> and colon cancers.

MATERIALS AND METHODS Sample Collection Samples of <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> and <PlantPart>twigs</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Dysoxylum gaudichaudianum</Synonym> (A. Juss.) Miq were collected from the De La Salle University - Science and Technology Complex (DLSU-STC) riparian forest in February 2014.

The samples were authenticated and deposited at the De La Salle University Herbarium with voucher specimen #920.

Isolation and Structure Elucidation The isolation and structure elucidation of <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, from the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Dysoxylum gaudichaudianum</Synonym> were reported previously.

Preparation of Compounds for Cytotoxicity Tests The compounds (<Compound>Squalene</Compound>, <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, ) from <Synonym>Dysoxylum gaudichaudianum</Synonym> were dissolved in <Compound>dimethyl sulfoxide</Compound> (DMSO) to make a <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, mg/mL stock solution.

Working solutions were prepared in complete growth medium to a final non-toxic DMSO concentration of 0.

1%.

Maintenance and Preparation of Cell Lines for Cytotoxicity Tests The cytotoxicity of <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, from the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> (CH2Cl2) extracts from <Synonym>Dysoxylum gaudichaudianum</Synonym> was tested on the following human cell lines: <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> cancer (<CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine>), colon cancer (<CellLine>HCT-116</CellLine> and <CellLine>HT-29</CellLine>; ATCC, <Location>Manassas</Location>, <Location>Virginia</Location>, <Location>U.S.A.</Location>), and human dermal fibroblast, neonatal (<CellLine>HDFn</CellLine>; Invitrogen Life Technologies, <Location>U.S.A.</Location>), which are routinely maintained at the Cell and Tissue Culture Laboratory, Molecular Science Unit, Center for Natural Science and Environmental Research, De La Salle University, <Location>Manila</Location>, <Location>Philippines</Location>.

Following standard procedures,13, cells were grown in Dulbecco's Modified Eagle Medium (DMEM, <Location>Gibco</Location>, <Location>USA</Location>) containing 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS, <Location>Gibco</Location>, <Location>USA</Location>) and 1x antibioticantimycotic (<Location>Gibco</Location>, <Location>USA</Location>) and kept in an incubator (37C, 5% CO2, 98% humidity).

At 80% confluence, the monolayers were washed with phosphate-buffered saline (PBS, pH 7 <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, <Location>Gibco</Location>, <Location>USA</Location>), trypsinized with 0.05% Figure 3: Dose-response curves showing the <BioAct>cytotoxic</BioAct> activities of <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, and <Location>Zeocin</Location> on the cell viability of <CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine>, <CellLine>HCT-116</CellLine>, <CellLine>HT-29</CellLine> and <CellLine>HDFn</CellLine>.

Each plot shows the effect of a compound against all cell lines tested.

Data shown are means of triplicates.

GraphPad Prism 6.07 was used to perform extra sum-of-squares F test to (A) evaluate if the bestfit parameter (half maximal inhibitory concentration) differs among data sets (treatments), and (B) determine the differences among the dose-response curve fits.

The results are: compound <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, (A) F (DFn, DFd) = F <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, 88) = 39.06, p < 0.0001 and (B) F (6, 88) = 19.64, p < 0.0001; compound <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, (A) F <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, 80) = 30.83, p < 0.0001 and (B) F (6, 80) = 15.61, p < 0.0001; compound <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, (A) F <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, 88) = <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, 711, p = 0.0145 and (B) F (6, 88) = <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, 797, p = 0.0021; compound <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, (A) F <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, 88) = 10.27, p < 0.0001 and (B) F (6, 88) = 5.419, p < 0.

0001.

<Location>Mariquit</Location> et al. /<BioAct>Cytotoxic</BioAct> Compounds from <Location>IJPPR</Location>, Volume 8, Issue 4: April 2016 Page 671 Trypsin-EDTA (<Location>Gibco</Location>, <Location>USA</Location>) and resuspended with fresh complete media.

Cells were counted following standard trypan blue exclusion method using 0.4% Trypan Blue Solution (<Location>Gibco</Location>, <Location>USA</Location>).

Cells were seeded in 100-L aliquots into 96-well microtiter plates (FalconTM, <Location>USA</Location>) using a final inoculation density of <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, x 104 cells/well.

The plates were further incubated overnight (37C, 5% CO2, 98% humidity) until complete cell attachment was reached.

These cells were used for the cytotoxicity studies as described below.

Cell Viability Assay The cytotoxicity of the <Synonym>Dysoxylum gaudichaudianum</Synonym> compounds was determined in a cell viability assay using PrestoBlue (Molecular Probes, Invitrogen, <Location>USA</Location>).

This test is based on the presence of mitochondrial reductase in viable cells which then reduces the <Compound>resazurin</Compound> dye (blue and nonfluorescent) in the reagent to resorufin (red and highly fluorescent).

The conversion is proportional to the number of metabolically active cells and is determined quantitatively using absorbance measurements.

To the monolayers in the microtiter plate, 100 L of filtersterilized <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, were added to corresponding wells at twofold serial dilutions to make final screening concentrations of 50, 25, 12.5, 6.25, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, 12, <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, 56, 0.78, and 0.39 g/mL.

The treated cells were further incubated (37C, 5% CO2, 98% humidity) for <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, days.

Ten microliters of PrestoBlue was added to each well.

The cells were incubated (37C, 5% CO2, 98% humidity) for <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, hr.

Wells with no compound added served as negative controls while wells with ZeocinTM (<Location>Gibco</Location>, <Location>USA</Location>) served as positive controls.

Wells containing cell culture media only were used to correct for background absorbance.

Absorbance measurements were carried out using BioTek ELx800 Absorbance <Compound>Microplate</Compound> Reader (BioTek Instruments, Inc., <Location>U.S.A.</Location>) at 570 nm and normalized to 600 nm values (reference wavelength).

Absorbance readings were used to calculate for the cell viability for each sample concentration following the equation below. (%) = ( - ) ( - ) 100 Nonlinear regression and statistical analyses were done using GraphPad Prism 6.07 (GraphPad Software, Inc.) to <Compound>extrapolate</Compound> the half maximal inhibitory concentration, IC50 (the concentration of the compound which resulted in a 50% reduction in cell viability).

The cytotoxicity of <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, was <Preparation>expressed</Preparation> as IC50 values.

All tests were performed in triplicates and data were shown as means.

The extra sumof-squares F test was used to evaluate the differences in the best-fit parameter (half maximal inhibitory concentration) among data sets (treatments) and to determine the differences among dose-response curve fits according to the software's recommended approach.

One-way ANOVA (p < 0.05) was also used to determine significant differences among treatments, followed by Tukey's multiple comparison post hoc test (p < 0.05), to compare different pairs of data sets.

Results were considered significant at p < 0.

05.

RESULTS AND DISCUSION This work presents studies on the <BioAct>cytotoxic</BioAct> activities of <Compound>squalene</Compound> , <Compound>polyprenol</Compound> , <Compound>triglycerides</Compound> , and <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound> , previously isolated from the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> extracts of <Synonym>Dysoxylum gaudichaudianum</Synonym> <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart>, against three human cancer cell lines, <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> (<CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine>) and colon (<CellLine>HT-29</CellLine> and <CellLine>HCT-116</CellLine>), and a human normal cell line, human dermal fibroblast, neonatal (<CellLine>HDFn</CellLine>).

A known <BioAct>anti-cancer</BioAct> drug, <Location>Zeocin</Location>, was used as positive control.

The % cell viability as a function of the logarithmic values of compound concentration is shown in Figures <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, and <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, Most plots nearly follow the typical sigmoidal curve which is characteristic of an inhibitory dose-response relationship between treatments and cell viability.

Figure <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, compares the <BioAct>anti-proliferative</BioAct> effects per cell line, while Figure <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, compares the effects per compound.

The corresponding IC50 values are summarized in Table <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, The <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> cancer cell line (<CellLine>MCF7</CellLine>) is most susceptible to <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, and <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, with IC50 values of <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, 277, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, 786, and <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, 404 g/mL, respectively, and least susceptible to <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, with an IC50 value of 16.12 g/mL.

Oneway ANOVA showed that all treatments are statistically different (p < 0.0001), but Tukey's multiple comparison post hoc test revealed that there are no pairwise differences between <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, and <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, and <Location>Zeocin</Location>, <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, and <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, and <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, and <Location>Zeocin</Location> (p > 0.

05).

The colon cancer cell line (<CellLine>HCT-116</CellLine>) is most susceptible to <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, and <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, with IC50 values of 7.859 and 9.258 g/mL, respectively, followed by <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, and <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, with IC50 values of 11.63, and 13.05 g/mL, respectively.

One-way ANOVA showed that all treatments are statistically different (p < 0.0001), but Tukey's multiple comparison post hoc test showed pairwise differences only between <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, and <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, (p < 0.0001), and <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, and <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, (p < 0.

01).

The growth of Table 1: <BioAct>Cytotoxic</BioAct> activities (IC50) of <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, and <Location>Zeocin</Location> against <CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine>, <CellLine>HCT-116</CellLine>, <CellLine>HT-29</CellLine> and <CellLine>HDFn</CellLine>.

Compound IC50*(g/mL) <CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine> <CellLine>HCT-116</CellLine> <CellLine>HT-29</CellLine> <CellLine>HDFn</CellLine> <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, 404 7.859 0.84 12 <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, 786 9.258 <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, 059 17.01 <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, 16.12 13.05 <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, 738 17.72 <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, 277 11.63 <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, 41 11.

<Location>Zeocin</Location> <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, 168 <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, 856 <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, 318 <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, 713 *IC50 values were extrapolated from dose-response curves generated from nonlinear regression analysis done using GraphPad Prism 6.

05.

For each cell line, one-way ANOVA was conducted to determine differences among data sets (treatments).

The results are: <CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine>, F (5, 118) = 35.74, p < 0.0001; <CellLine>HCT-116</CellLine>, F (5, 110) = 182 <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, p < 0.0001; <CellLine>HT29</CellLine>, F (5, 118) = 107 <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, p < 0.0001; <CellLine>HDFn</CellLine>, F (5, 118) = 275 <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, p < 0.

0001.

Results of the Tukey's multiple comparison post hoc test are discussed in this section.

<Location>Mariquit</Location> et al. /<BioAct>Cytotoxic</BioAct> Compounds from <Location>IJPPR</Location>, Volume 8, Issue 4: April 2016 Page 672 the other colon cancer cell line (<CellLine>HT-29</CellLine>) exhibited the strongest inhibition at the lowest concentrations of the compounds, with IC50 values of 0.84, <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, 059, <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, 41, <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, 738 g/mL for <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, and <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, respectively.

Tukey's multiple comparison post hoc test showed statistical differences between all treatments except for <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, and <Location>Zeocin</Location> (p > 0.

05).

The normal cell line, <CellLine>HDFn</CellLine>, responded moderately to all the compounds, with IC50 values of 11.18, 12 <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, 17.01, and 17.72 g/mL for <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, and <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, respectively.

The pairs of compounds, <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, and <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, and <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, and <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, are not statistically different (p > 0.

05).

Data analysis showed statistical differences in the best-fit parameter (half maximal inhibitory concentration) among treatments and among the dose-response curve fits (Figures <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, and <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, .

Overall, comparing the three human cancer cell lines, <CellLine>HT-29</CellLine> showed the most <BioAct>cytotoxic</BioAct> response to the compounds tested (IC50 value of 0.84 g/mL for <Compound>squalene</Compound> ).

This was followed by <CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine> cells (IC50 values of <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, 77 and <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, 786 g/mL for <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> and <Compound>polyprenol</Compound> , respectively).

In a preliminary study on the <BioAct>cytotoxic</BioAct> activity of the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of <Synonym>Dysoxylum gaudichaudianum</Synonym> <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart>, the crude <Preparation>extract</Preparation> exhibited <BioAct>cytotoxic</BioAct> activities with IC50 values of 13.19 and 7.35 g/mL for <CellLine>HT-29</CellLine> and <CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine> cancer cells, respectively.

In the current study, the isolated compounds from the <Preparation>extract</Preparation> exhibited high <BioAct>anti-proliferative</BioAct> activities against the cell lines used, indicating that these compounds may be responsible for the cytotoxicity of the <Preparation>extract</Preparation>.

Among the cancer cell lines tested, <CellLine>HCT-116</CellLine> showed the least response to the compounds.

On the other <BodyPart>hand</BodyPart>, the normal cell line, <CellLine>HDFn</CellLine>, exhibited moderate susceptibility only.

The most <BioAct>cytotoxic</BioAct> effect was seen in <CellLine>HT-29</CellLine> cells using <Compound>squalene</Compound> , while the least <BioAct>anti-proliferative</BioAct> effect was observed in <CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine> cells treated with <Compound>triglycerides</Compound> .

Overall, <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, showed varying, but promising <BioAct>cytotoxic</BioAct> properties.

The US National Cancer Institute has defined the active <BioAct>cytotoxic</BioAct> limits of natural products as 20 g/mL or less for crude extracts and <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, g/mL or less for pure compounds.

Pure compounds that exhibit active cytotoxicity may have some potential for drug development.

The results showed that <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, from the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> extracts of <Synonym>Dysoxylum gaudichaudianum</Synonym> <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> can be further developed for the treatment of human colorectal type and human <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> cancers.

The study also showed that the <BioAct>cytotoxic</BioAct> activity of <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, was a function of the specific type of cancer cells targeted.

When the two colon cancer cell lines are compared, the IC50 values of 14 for <CellLine>HT-29</CellLine> were lower than <CellLine>HCT-116</CellLine>, implying that the former could be more responsive to <BioAct>anti-cancer</BioAct> treatments using the compounds tested.

<Compound>Squalene</Compound> was reported that variances in the expression profiles of several genes associated with drug sensitivity between <CellLine>HCT-116</CellLine> and <CellLine>HT-29</CellLine> could influence the cells' response to different inhibitory compounds.

A related study using four human colon cancer cell lines (<CellLine>HCT-116</CellLine>, <CellLine>HT-29</CellLine>, <CellLine>HCT-15</CellLine>, and <CellLine>KM-12</CellLine>) revealed that gene expression profiling after inhibition of signal transduction by 17-allylamino-17demethoxygeldanamycin, a known inhibitor of the hsp90 molecular <Compound>chaperone</Compound>, could explain how cells respond under different treatment conditions.

Previous studies revealed that <Compound>squalene</Compound>, <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, and <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound> exhibited <BioAct>cytotoxic</BioAct> and <BioAct>anticancer</BioAct> properties.

<Compound>Squalene</Compound> was reported to exhibit antitumor activities against colon cancer in rodents.

<Compound>Squalene</Compound> was also found to remarkably control colonic aberrant crypt foci (ACF) formation and crypt multiplicity in laboratory rats which supported the hypothesis that <Compound>Squalene</Compound> possesses chemopreventive activity against colon carcinogenesis.

In a study evaluating the <BioAct>anti-proliferative</BioAct> effects of <ChemicalClass>tocotrienols</ChemicalClass>, <ChemicalClass>carotenoids</ChemicalClass>, <Compound>squalene</Compound>, and coenzyme Q10 from palm oil against two human <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> cancer cell lines, <CellLine>MDA-MB-231</CellLine> and <CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine>, it was found that there was a suppression of nuclear factor kappa-light-chain-enhancer of activated B-cells (<CellLine>NF-B</CellLine>) protein in the <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> cancer cells exposed briefly to tumor necrosis factor-alpha (<CellLine>TNFalpha</CellLine>)19,20.

The protective and therapeutic effects of squalenecontaining compounds on the promotion of tumor cells have been reported.

Relevant reviews on the bioactive properties of <Compound>squalene</Compound> have been provided,23.

Thus, <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, was reported to exhibit <BioAct>cytotoxic</BioAct> properties against colon and <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> cancer cells which corroborate our findings that <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, showed high cytotoxicity against colon cancer cells, <CellLine>HT29</CellLine> and <CellLine>HCT-116</CellLine>, and <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> cancer cells, <CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine>, with IC50 values of 0.84, 7.859 and <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, 404 g/mL, respectively.

<Compound>Polyprenols</Compound> from <Synonym>Ginkgo biloba</Synonym> L. showed hepatoprotective effects against CCl4-stimulated hepatotoxicity in rats and exhibited antitumor activity.

<Compound>Polyprenols</Compound> inhibited Heps, S (180) and EC transplanted <Illness>tumors</Illness> by at least 50%25.

<Compound>Polyprenol</Compound>, with concentrations between 10-3-10-4 M, induced apoptosis in multidrug-resistant <CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine> cells by reducing the resistance marker, <Compound>P-glycoprotein</Compound> (Pgp), in the plasma membrane.

In a related study, <CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine> cells treated with 10-4 M of <Compound>polyprenol</Compound> resulted in the downregulation of DPAGT overexpression which led to the regulation of <Compound>E-cadherin</Compound> expression, an important factor in the prevention of <Illness>tumors</Illness> and metastasis.

To the best of our knowledge, this is the first report on the cytotoxicity of <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, against colon cancer cells <CellLine>HT-29</CellLine> and <CellLine>HCT116</CellLine> and <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> cancer cells <CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine>, with IC50 values of <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, 059, 9.258 and <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, 786 g/mL, respectively.

<Compound>Triacylglycerols</Compound> from Tuna (1000 mg/kg) was reported to significantly inhibit the tumor growth in the <BodyPart>spleen</BodyPart> of mice with intrasplenically-implanted Lewis lung carcinoma.

<Compound>Triacylglycerols</Compound>, which account for 1220% of the total <PlantPart>seed</PlantPart> weight of <Compound>pomegranate</Compound> (<Synonym>Punica granatum</Synonym>) <PlantPart>seed</PlantPart> oil (PSO) <Preparation>extract</Preparation>, was found to significantly decrease cell viability in two <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> cancer cell lines, <CellLine>MDA-MB-231</CellLine> and <CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine>.

To our knowledge, this is the first report on the cytotoxicity of <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, against colon cancer cells, <CellLine>HT-29</CellLine> and <CellLine>HCT116</CellLine>, and <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> cancer cells, <CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine>, with IC50 values of <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, 738, 13.05, and 16.12 g/mL, respectively.

<Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound> was found to affect the programmed cell death pathway in human <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> cancer cells (<CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine>) and human adenocarcinoma cells (<CellLine>MDA-MB-231</CellLine>), hindering tumor growth by promoting apoptosis.

<Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound> also inhibited cell proliferation of human colon cancer cells (<CellLine>HT-29</CellLine>)31.

<Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound> inhibited the growth of HT116 human colon cancer cells by different mechanisms including the activation of caspase-3 and caspase-9, accompanied by proteolytic cleavage of <Location>Mariquit</Location> et al. /<BioAct>Cytotoxic</BioAct> Compounds from <Location>IJPPR</Location>, Volume 8, Issue 4: April 2016 Page 673 poly(ADP-ribose)-polymerase and the reduction of the expression of the anti-apoptotic Bcl-2 protein and mRNA and a subsequent increase of the pro-apoptotic Bax protein and mRNA.

In vitro studies showed that <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, inhibited the proliferation of human colon cancer cells (<CellLine>COLO 320 DM</CellLine>) with an IC50 of 266.

M, inducing apoptosis by scavenging oxidants and attenuating <Compound>beta-catenin</Compound> and PCNA expression while in vivo studies showed that <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, reduced the number of aberrant crypt and crypt multiplicity in DMHinitiated rats in a dose-dependent fashion.

<Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound> significantly decreased the expression of NiemannPick C1-like <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, (<CellLine>NPC1L1</CellLine>) in human small <BodyPart>intestine</BodyPart> epithelial cells (FHs 74 Int), reducing intestinal cholesterol absorption at the cellular level.

<Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound> also promoted apoptosis mediated by the activation of ERK and the downregulation of Akt in <Compound>murine</Compound> fibrosarcoma cells (MCA-102)35.

<Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound> was reported that <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> exhibited <BioAct>anti-proliferative</BioAct> activities against human prostate cancer cells (<CellLine>DU-145</CellLine>) by increasing the expression of p53 protein and inhibiting carcinoma development by decreasing the expression of p21 and p27 proteins.

Thus, <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, was reported to exhibit <BioAct>cytotoxic</BioAct> properties against several cancer cell lines such as colon and <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> cancer cell lines which corroborate our findings that <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, showed high cytotoxicity against colon cancer cells, <CellLine>HT-29</CellLine>, and <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> cancer cells, <CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine>, with IC50 values of <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, 41 and <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, 277 g/mL, respectively..

<Compound>Squalene</Compound> , <Compound>polyprenols</Compound> , <Compound>triglycerides</Compound> , and <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound> , isolated from the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of <Synonym>Dysoxylum gaudichaudianum</Synonym> <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart>, exhibited varying <BioAct>cytotoxic</BioAct> activities against three human cancer cell lines, <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> (<CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine>) and colon (<CellLine>HT-29</CellLine> and <CellLine>HCT-116</CellLine>), and a normal cell line, human dermal fibroblast, neonatal (<CellLine>HDFn</CellLine>).

The <BioAct>anti-proliferative</BioAct> activities of <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, were highest against <CellLine>HT-29</CellLine>, with IC50 values ranging from 0.84 to <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, 738 g/mL, followed by <CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine>, with IC50 values ranging from <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, 277 to 16.12 g/mL, and <CellLine>HCT-116</CellLine>, with IC50 values ranging from 7.859 to 13.05 g/mL.

All compounds (<Compound>Squalene</Compound>, <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, ) were moderately <BioAct>cytotoxic</BioAct> against <CellLine>HDFn</CellLine> with IC50 values >10 g/mL.

Overall, <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, <Compound>polyprenols</Compound>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, were more <BioAct>cytotoxic</BioAct> to the <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> and colon cancer cell lines than to the normal cell line..

A research grant from the De La Salle University Science Foundation, through the University Research Coordination Office, is gratefully acknowledged.