Available online at www.ijpcr.com International Journal of Pharmaceutical and Clinical Research 2015; 7: 356-359 ISSN 1556 Research Article *Author for Correspondence Secondary Metabolites from <Synonym>Cycas lacrimans</Synonym> Vincent Antonio S. Ng1, Esperanza Maribel Agoo, Chien-Chang Shen, Consolacion Y. Ragasa <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, 1Chemistry Department, De La Salle University, 2401 <Location>Taft Avenue</Location>, 1004 <Location>Manila</Location>, <Location>Philippines</Location> 2Biology Department, De La Salle University, 2401 <Location>Taft Avenue</Location>, 1004 <Location>Manila</Location>, <Location>Philippines</Location> <Compound>3National</Compound> Research Institute of Chinese Medicine, Ministry of Health and Welfare, 155-1, Li-Nong St., <Location>Sec</Location>. , <Location>Taipei</Location>, <Location>Taiwan</Location> 4Chemistry Department, De La Salle University Science & Technology Complex Leandro <Compound>1,2-dioleylglycerol</Compound>, Locsin Campus, <Location>Binan City</Location>, <Location>Laguna</Location>, <Location>Philippines</Location> Available Online: 31st August, 2015.

Chemical investigation of the <PlantPart>sarcotesta</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Cycas lacrimans</Synonym>, a plant endemic to the <Location>Philippines</Location> afforded <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3betaglucopyranoside-6'-O-palmitate</Compound> , a mixture of alkyl <Compound>4-hydroxy-trans-cinnamate esters</Compound> and alkyl <Compound>4-hydroxy-ciscinnamate esters</Compound> , <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> , unsaturated <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound> , and <Compound>methyl fatty acid esters</Compound> .

The structures of <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-Opalmitate</Compound>, <Compound>Beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, <Compound>methyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, were identified by comparison of their NMR data with those reported in the literature.

Keywords: <Synonym>Cycas lacrimans</Synonym>, <Family>Cycadaceae</Family>, <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-O-palmitate</Compound>, alkyl <Compound>4-hydroxy-transcinnamate esters</Compound>, alkyl <Compound>4-hydroxy-cis-cinnamate esters</Compound>, <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, <Compound>methyl fatty acid esters</Compound>.

Cycas, the only currently known <MedicinalPlant>genus</MedicinalPlant> of the Family <Family>Cycadaceae</Family>, are considered as fossil plants though they may have evolved only about 12 million years ago1.

Their long existence and persistence through time have sparked special interest in their biology and evolution.

The cycads resemble palms in morphology thus are commonly called <MedicinalPlant>sago palm</MedicinalPlant>.

They bear naked <PlantPart>seeds</PlantPart> and are dioecious (male and female as separate individuals).

These are widely distributed in the <Location>Tropics</Location>, with species found in <Location>Asia</Location>, <Location>Africa</Location>, Southeast <Location>Asia</Location>, <Location>Pacific</Location>, and <Location>Australia</Location>.

They also grow on volcanic, limestone, ultramafic, sandy, or even water-logged soils in grassland and forest habitats.

In the <Location>Philippines</Location>, there are eleven (11) cycad species namely, <Synonym>Cycas aenigma</Synonym> K. D. Hill & Lindstrom, <Synonym>Cycas curranii</Synonym> (J. Schust.) K. D. Hill, C.edentata de Laub., <Synonym>Cycas lacrimans</Synonym> Lindstrom & K. D. Hill, <Synonym>Cycas nitida</Synonym> K. D. Hill & Lindstrom, <Synonym>Cycas riuminiana</Synonym> Porte ex Regel, <Synonym>Cycas saxatilis</Synonym> K. D. Hill & Lindstrom, Cycas sancti-lasallei Agoo & Madulid, <Synonym>Cycas wadei</Synonym> Merr., <Synonym>Cycas vespertilio</Synonym> Lindstrom & K. D. Hill, and <Synonym>Cycas zambalensis</Synonym> Madulid & Agoo-5. All species, except for <Synonym>Cycas edentata</Synonym>, are endemic to the country.

<Synonym>Cycas revoluta</Synonym>, a widely cultivated species, is an introduced species from <Location>Japan</Location> and <Location>Taiwan</Location>.

The demand of Cycas species for domestic and international horticultural trade, grassland and forest fires of anthropogenic origin, and conversion of their natural habitats to settlements and other land uses have threatened to varying degrees the wild populations of the <MedicinalPlant>genus</MedicinalPlant>.

Some of these species which have been assessed and evaluated in the 2010 IUCN Red List of Threatened Species are <Synonym>Cycas curranii</Synonym>, <Synonym>Cycas wadei</Synonym> and <Synonym>Cycas zambalensis</Synonym> as Critically Endangered (CR)7, <Synonym>Cycas riuminiana</Synonym> as Endangered (E)7, and Cycas saxatilisas Vulnerable 9.

This study is part of our research on the chemical constituents of Cycas species that are endemic to the <Location>Philippines</Location>.

We earlier reported the isolation of <Compound>isopimaran-19-ol</Compound> from the <Compound>megasporophyll</Compound> lamina; <Compound>9alphaH-isopimara-7,15-diene</Compound> and <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound> from the <PlantPart>bark</PlantPart>; <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, <Compound>oleic acid</Compound> , and <Compound>1,2-dioleylglycerol</Compound> from the leaflets; <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> , and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> from the <PlantPart>petiole and rachis</PlantPart>; <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, from the <PlantPart>roots</PlantPart>; and <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, and <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, from the <PlantPart>endotesta</PlantPart> and <PlantPart>sclerotesta</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Cycas lacrimans</Synonym>.

In another study, we reported the isolation of <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, and <Compound>squalene</Compound> from the <PlantPart>sarcotesta</PlantPart>; <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, and <Compound>phytyl fatty acid esters</Compound> from the <PlantPart>endotesta</PlantPart>; <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, and <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid esters</Compound> from the <PlantPart>sclerotesta</PlantPart>; and <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, and <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid esters</Compound>, from the <PlantPart>bark</PlantPart> of Cycas sancti-lasallei.

Another Cycas species, <Synonym>Cycas vespertilio</Synonym> yielded <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, a mixture of <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, <Compound>pinoresinol</Compound> , <Compound>sesamin</Compound> , and <Compound>paulownin</Compound> from the <PlantPart>cone base</PlantPart>; <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, <Compound>pinoresinol</Compound>, <Compound>paulownin</Compound>, and <Compound>lariciresinol</Compound> from the cataphylls; <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, from the <Compound>megasporophyll</Compound> lamina; <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, and a mixture of <Compound>trans-4-hydroxycinnamate fatty acid esters</Compound> and <Compound>cis-4-hydroxycinnamate fatty acid esters</Compound> from the <PlantPart>unripe sarcotesta</PlantPart>; and <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, and <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, from the <PlantPart>ripe sarcotesta</PlantPart>.

We recently reported the isolation of <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-Opalmitate</Compound> from the <PlantPart>sarcotesta</PlantPart>; <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid esters</Compound>, <Compound>unsaturated fatty acid methyl esters</Compound> , <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, from the <PlantPart>endotesta</PlantPart>; <Compound>chlorophyll a</Compound> from the leaflets; and <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound> from the <PlantPart>male cone</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Cycas edentata</Synonym> 13.

We report herein the isolation of <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3betaglucopyranoside-6'-O-palmitate</Compound> , a mixture of alkyl 4Vincent Antonio et al. / Secondary Metabolites from <Location>IJPCR</Location>, September 2015 October 2015, Volume 7, Issue <Compound>methyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, Page 357 <Compound>hydroxy-trans-cinnamate esters</Compound> and alkyl <Compound>4-hydroxycis-cinnamate esters</Compound> , <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> , unsaturated <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound> , and <Compound>methyl fatty acid esters</Compound> from the <PlantPart>sarcotesta</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Cycas lacrimans</Synonym>.

The structures of <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-Opalmitate</Compound>, <Compound>Beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, <Compound>methyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, were elucidated by comparison of their 1H and/or 13C NMR data with those reported in the literature.

To the best of our knowledge this is the first report on the isolation of 1-2b and <Compound>methyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, from <Synonym>Cycas lacrimans</Synonym>.

MATERIALS AND METHODS General Experimental Procedure NMR spectra were recorded on a Varian VNMRS spectrometer in CDCl at 600 MHz for 1H NMR and 150 MHz for 13C NMR spectra.

Column chromatography was performed with silica gel 60 (70-230 mesh).

Thin layer chromatography was performed with plastic backed plates coated with silica gel F254 and the plates were visualized by spraying with <Compound>vanillin</Compound>/H2SO4 solution followed by warming.

Sample Collection <Synonym>Cycas lacrimans</Synonym> <PlantPart>sarcotesta</PlantPart> were collected in 2013.

Voucher specimens were collected and authenticated by CH2OCR O CHOCR' O CH2OCR" O <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, R, R', R" = long <Compound>chain fatty acids</Compound> <Compound>Beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-Opalmitate</Compound>, O O OH HO HO O (CH2)14CH3 O <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-Opalmitate</Compound>, <Compound>Beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>methyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, 810 11 14 17 18 19 20 23 26 29 1'3' 5' 6' <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-Opalmitate</Compound>, CH3(CH2)nCOOCH <Compound>methyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, HO O OR HO O OR <Compound>4-hydroxy-transcinnamate esters</Compound>, R = long <Compound>chain fatty acids</Compound> <Compound>4-hydroxy-cis-cinnamate esters</Compound>, R = long <Compound>chain fatty acids</Compound> 9 7 <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-Opalmitate</Compound>, <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, RO <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-Opalmitate</Compound>, <Compound>Beta-sitosterol</Compound>, 6 10 11 14 17 18 19 22 24 26 29 Figure 1: Chemical structures of <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-O-palmitate</Compound> , alkyl <Compound>4-hydroxy-trans-cinnamate esters</Compound> , alkyl <Compound>4-hydroxy-cis-cinnamate esters</Compound> , <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> , unsaturated <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound> , and <Compound>methyl fatty acid esters</Compound> from <Synonym>Cycas lacrimans</Synonym>.

Vincent Antonio et al. / Secondary Metabolites from <Location>IJPCR</Location>, September 2015 October 2015, Volume 7, Issue <Compound>methyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, Page 358 one of the authors (EMGA) and deposited in the De La Salle UniversityManila Herbarium (DLSUH).

General Isolation Procedure A glass column 18 inches in height and <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-Opalmitate</Compound>, 0 inch internal diameter was used for the fractionation of the crude extracts.

Ten milliliter fractions were collected.

Fractions with spots of the same Rf values were combined and rechromatographed in appropriate solvent systems until TLC pure isolates were obtained.

A glass column 12 inches in height and 0 <Compound>methyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, inch internal diameter was used for the rechromatography.

Five milliliter fractions were collected.

Final purifications were conducted using Pasteur pipettes as columns.

One milliliter fractions were collected.

Isolation of the Chemical Constituents of the <PlantPart>Sarcotesta</PlantPart> The freeze-dried <PlantPart>sarcotesta</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Cycas lacrimans</Synonym> (105 g) were <Preparation>ground</Preparation> in a blender, soaked in CH2Cl2 for <Compound>Beta-sitosterol</Compound>, days and then <Preparation>filtered</Preparation>.

The filtrate was concentrated under vacuum to afford a crude <Preparation>extract</Preparation> (0 <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, g) which was chromatographed using increasing proportions of <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 at 10% increment.

The 20% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed (2 ) using 10% EtOAc in petroleum ether to yield <Compound>methyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, mg).

The 40% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed using 10% EtOAc in petroleum ether.

The less polar fractions were combined and rechromatographed (2 ) using 7.5% EtOAc in petroleum ether to afford <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, <Compound>methyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, mg).

The more polar fractions were combined and rechromatographed <Compound>Beta-sitosterol</Compound>, ) using CH3CN:Et2O:CH2Cl2 (0.5:0.5:9, v/v) to yield a mixture of <Compound>4-hydroxy-transcinnamate esters</Compound>, and <Compound>4-hydroxy-cis-cinnamate esters</Compound>, <Compound>Beta-sitosterol</Compound>, mg).

The 60% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed <Compound>Beta-sitosterol</Compound>, ) using CH3CN:Et2O:CH2Cl2 (2.5:2.5:5, v/v) to yield <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-Opalmitate</Compound>, <Compound>methyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, mg).

In the second isolation the freeze-dried <PlantPart>sarcotesta</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Cycas lacrimans</Synonym> (140 g) were <Preparation>ground</Preparation> in a blender, soaked in CH2Cl2 for <Compound>Beta-sitosterol</Compound>, days and then <Preparation>filtered</Preparation>.

The filtrate was concentrated under vacuum to afford a crude <Preparation>extract</Preparation> <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-Opalmitate</Compound>, 2 g) which was chromatographed using increasing proportions of <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 at 10% increment.

The 30% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed <Compound>Beta-sitosterol</Compound>, ) in 7.5% EtOAc in petroleum ether to afford <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, (12 mg).

The 40% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, ) in 15% EtOAc in petroleum ether to afford <Compound>Beta-sitosterol</Compound>, (15 mg) after washing with petroleum ether.

<Compound>Beta-Sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-O-palmitate</Compound> : 1H NMR (600 MHz, CDCl): <Compound>Beta-sitosterol</Compound>, 55 (m, H-3), <Compound>methyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, 34 (m, H-6), 0.66 (s, CH3-18), 0.99 (s, CH3-19), 0.92 (3H, d, J = 6. Hz, CH3-21), 0.82 (3H, d, J = 7. Hz, CH3-26), 0.85 (d, J = 7. Hz, CH3-27), 0.86 (t, J = 7. Hz, CH3-29), <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, 37 (d, J = 7. Hz, H-1'), <Compound>Beta-sitosterol</Compound>, 36 (dd, J = 7 <Compound>methyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, 9.0, H-2'), <Compound>Beta-sitosterol</Compound>, 56 (dd, J = 9.0, 10.0, H-3'), <Compound>Beta-sitosterol</Compound>, 36 (dd, J = 9.0, 10.

Hz, H-4'), <Compound>Beta-sitosterol</Compound>, 43 (m, H5'), <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, 23 (dd, J = 12.0, 2. Hz, H-6a'), <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, 49 (dd, J = <Compound>methyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, 0, 12.

Hz, H-6b'), 2.34 (t, J = 7. Hz, H-2"); 13C NMR (150 MHz; CDCl): 37.24 (C-1), 29.71 (C-2), 79.53 (C-3), 38.88 (C-4), 140.26 (C-5), 122.19 (C-6), 31.93, 31.85 (C7, C-8), 50.15 (C-9), 36.72 (C-10), 21.06 (C-11), 39.74 (C12), 42.31 (C-13), 56.74 (C-14), 24.28 (C-15), 28.24 (C16), 56.05 (C-17), 11.84 (C-18), 19.34 (C-19), 36.13 (C20), 18.77 (C-21), 33.93 (C-22), 26.05 (C-23), 45.81 (C24), 29.13 (C-25), 19.01 (C-26), 19.81 (C-27), 23.05 (C28), 11.97 (C-29), 101.18 (C-1'), 73.58 (C-2'), 75.87 (C3'), 69.98 (C-4'), 73.98 (C-5'), 75.87 (C-6'), 174.80 (C-1"), 34.21 (C-2"), 24.94 (C-3"), 29.31 (C-4"), 29.52 (C-5"), 29.71 (C-6"), 29.71 (C-7"-C-12"), 29.36 (C-13"), 31.93 (C-14"), 22.69 (C-15"), 14.12 (C-16"). <Compound>Trans-4-hydroxycinnamate fatty acid esters</Compound> : 1H NMR (600 MHz, CDCl): 6.83 (d, J = 9. Hz, H-3, H5), 7.43 (d, J = 9. Hz, H-2, H-6), 7.61 (d, J = 15.

Hz, H7), 6.28 (d, J = 15.

Hz, H-8), <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, 16 (t, J = 6. Hz, H-1'), <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-Opalmitate</Compound>, 67 (2H, quintet, J = 6. Hz, H-2'), <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-Opalmitate</Compound>, 231.38 (H-3'Hn'), 0.88 (t, J = 6. Hz, Me); 13C NMR (150 MHz, CDCl): 127.41 (C-1), 115.81 (C-3, C-5), 129.90 (C-2, C-6), 157.47 (C-4), 144.10 (C-7), 115.87 (C-8), 167.44 (C-9), 64.46/64.61 (C-1'), 28.24 (C-2'), 129.90 (=CH), 27.79 (allylic CH2'), 22.69, 26.04, 29.06-29.70 (CH2')n, 31.9231.65 (CH2'), 14.12 (CH3' terminal).

<Compound>Cis-4-hydroxycinnamate fatty acid esters</Compound> : 1H NMR (600 MHz, CDCl): 0.88 (3H, t, J = 6. Hz, Me), <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-Opalmitate</Compound>, 23 <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-Opalmitate</Compound>, 38 (m), <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-Opalmitate</Compound>, 67 (2H, quintet, J = 6. Hz, H-2'), <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, 09 (2H, t, J = 6. Hz, H-1'), <Compound>methyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, 83 (1H, d, J = 12.

Hz. H-8), 6.78 (2H, d, J = 9. Hz, H-3, H-5), 6.82 (1H, d, J = 12.

Hz, H-7), 7.59 (2H, d, J = 9. Hz, H-2, H-6); 13C-NMR (150 MHz, CDCl): 127.11 (C-1), 114.90 (C-3, C-5), 132.33 (C-2, C-6), 156.48 (C-4), 143.02 (C-7), 117.42 (C-8), 166.59 (C9), 64.46/64.61 (C-1'), 22.69, 26.04, 28.24 (C-2'), 129.90 (=CH), 29.0629.70 (CH2')n, 31.9231.65 (CH2'), 14.12 (CH3' terminal).

<Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound> : 1H NMR (600 MHz, CDCl): <Compound>Beta-sitosterol</Compound>, 51 (m, H-3), 2.28, 2.24 (H2-4), <Compound>methyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, 33 (dd, J = <Compound>methyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, 2. Hz, H-6), 0.66 (s, CH3-18), 0.99 (s, CH3-19), 0.91 (d, J = 6. Hz, CH3-21), 0.80 (d, J = 6. Hz, CH3-26), 0.82 (d, J = 7. Hz, CH3-27), 0.86 (t, J = 7. Hz, CH3-29).

C NMR (150 MHz, CDCl): 37.24 (C-1), 31.66 (C-2), 71.81 (C-3), 42.30 (C-4), 140.75 (C-5), 121.72 (C-6), 31.90, 31.91 (C7, C-8), 50.12 (C-9), 36.14 (C-10), 21.07 (C-11), 39.76 (C12), 42.30 (C-13), 56.76 (C-14), 24.30 (C-15), 28.24 (C16), 56.04 (C-17), 11.85 (C-18), 19.39 (C-19), 36.50 (C20), 19.02 (C-21), 33.93 (C-22), 29.14 (C-23), 45.82 (C24), 26.06 (C-25), 18.77 (C-26), 19.81 (C-27), 23.06 (C28), 11.97 (C-29).

<Compound>Triacylglycerols</Compound> : 1H NMR (600 MHz, CDCl): <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, 28 (2H, dd, J = <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, 2, 12.

Hz, <Compound>glyceryl</Compound> CH2O), <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, 12 (2H, dd, J = 6.0, 12.

Hz, <Compound>glyceryl</Compound> CH2O), <Compound>methyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, 32 (1H, m, <Compound>glyceryl</Compound> CHO), 2.30 (6H, t, J = 7. Hz, alpha-CH2), <Compound>methyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, 33 (m, olefinic H), 2.75 (double allylic CH2), <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-Opalmitate</Compound>, 98-2.05 (allylic, CH2), <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-Opalmitate</Compound>, 23-1.35 (CH2), 0.87 (t, J = 6. Hz, CH3); 13C NMR (150 MHz, CDCl): 62.09 (<Compound>glyceryl</Compound> CH2), 68.87 (<Compound>glyceryl</Compound> CH), 173.29, 173.25 (C=O alpha), 172.84 (C=O beta), 34.03, 34.05, 34.19 (C-2), 24.84, 24.86 (C-3), 29.05, 29.08, 29.12 (C-4), 29.17, 29.20, 29.27 (C-5), 29.48 (C-6), 22.57, 22.68 (C-8), 130.23, 130.01, 129.70 (C-9), 127.74, 128.29, 129.68 (C-10), 25.61, 27.17, 27.20, 27.22, 29.32, 29.35, 29.36, 29.52, 29.62, 29.66, 29.70, 29.76 (CH2), 31.52, 31.90, 31.92 (CH2), 14.07, 14.11, 14.27 (terminal CH3).

Fatty <Compound>acid methyl esters</Compound> : 1H NMR (600 MHz, CDCl): 0.86 (t, J = 6. Hz), 0.96 (t, J = 7. Hz), <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-Opalmitate</Compound>, 23-1.35 (m), <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-Opalmitate</Compound>, 53-1.61 (m), 2.02-2.06 (m), 2.28 (t, J = 7. Hz), 2.78 (t, J = <Compound>methyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, Hz), <Compound>Beta-sitosterol</Compound>, 65 (s), <Compound>methyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, 30-5.37 (m); 13C NMR (150 MHz, CDCl): 14.07, 14.12, 14.27, 20.54, 22.57, 22.69, 24.94, 24.96, 25.52, 25.60, 25.62, 27.15, 27.19, 27.19, 29.09, 29.11, 29.15, 29.25, 29.31, 29.34, 29.35, 29.45, 29.52, Vincent Antonio et al. / Secondary Metabolites from <Location>IJPCR</Location>, September 2015 October 2015, Volume 7, Issue <Compound>methyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, Page 359 29.58, 29.66, 29.70, 29.76, 31.52, 31.90, 31.92, 34.10, 34.12, 51.44, 127.10, 127.72, 127.90, 128.03, 128.24, 128.27, 129.75, 130.00, 130.05, 130.21, 130.27, 131.96, 174.32..

Silica gel chromatography of the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of the <PlantPart>sarcotesta</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Cycas lacrimans</Synonym> afforded <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3betaglucopyranoside-6'-O-palmitate</Compound> 14,15, a mixture of alkyl <Compound>4-hydroxy-trans-cinnamate ester</Compound> 12 and alkyl <Compound>4hydroxy-cis-cinnamate ester</Compound> 12,16, <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> 10,17, unsaturated <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound> 10, and <Compound>methyl fatty acid esters</Compound> 18.

The structures of <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-Opalmitate</Compound>, <Compound>Beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, <Compound>methyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, were identified by comparison of their 1H and 13C NMR data with literature data.

<Compound>Beta-sitosterol</Compound> isolated from the <PlantPart>sarcotesta</PlantPart> was also present in the <PlantPart>petiole and rachis</PlantPart>, <PlantPart>roots</PlantPart>, <PlantPart>endotesta</PlantPart> and <PlantPart>sclerotesta</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Cycas lacrimans</Synonym>, while <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound> obtained from the <PlantPart>sarcotesta</PlantPart> were also found in the <PlantPart>bark</PlantPart>, leaflets, <PlantPart>petiole and rachis</PlantPart>, <PlantPart>roots</PlantPart>, <PlantPart>endotesta</PlantPart> and <PlantPart>sclerotesta</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Cycas lacrimans</Synonym>.

Results of this study indicate that <Synonym>Cycas lacrimans</Synonym> shares similar chemical characteristics with other members of the family <Family>Cycadaceae</Family>: <Synonym>Cycas edentata</Synonym> which contained <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-Opalmitate</Compound> and <Compound>methyl fatty acid esters</Compound> 13 and <Synonym>Cycas vespertilio</Synonym> which yielded alkyl <Compound>4-hydroxy-transcinnamate esters</Compound> and alkyl <Compound>4-hydroxy-cis-cinnamate esters</Compound> 12..

A research grant from the Commission on Higher Education - Philippine Higher Education Research Network (CHED-PHERNet) of the <Location>Philippines</Location> is gratefully acknowledged.