See discussions, stats, and author profiles for this publication at: https://www.researchgate.net/publication/330218492 <ChemicalClass>Triterpenes</ChemicalClass> and <ChemicalClass>Sterols</ChemicalClass> from <PlantPart>Leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Hoya meliflua</Synonym> Merr ArticleinPharmacognosy Journal January 2019 DOI: 10.5530/pj. .

1.

CITATIONS 0 READS 100 4 authors: Some of the authors of this publication are also working on these related projects: Natural Products Chemistry View project Graduate School View project Vincent Antonio Santos Ng De La Salle University 50 PUBLICATIONS CITATIONS SEE PROFILE Raymond Malabed De La Salle University 15 PUBLICATIONS CITATIONS SEE PROFILE Fernando Aurigue Philippine Nuclear Research Institute 20 PUBLICATIONS CITATIONS SEE PROFILE Consolacion Ragasa De La Salle University 346 PUBLICATIONS,935 CITATIONS SEE PROFILE All content following this page was uploaded by Raymond Malabed on 17 June 2019.

The user has requested enhancement of the downloaded file.

Pharmacogn J. 2019; 11:48-52 A Multifaceted Journal in the field of Natural Products and Pharmacognosy www.phcogj.com | www.journalonweb.com/pj | www.phcog.net Original Article 48 Pharmacognosy Journal, Vol 11, Issue 1, Jan-Feb, 2019.

<Location>Hoya</Location> Br is considered the largest genus of flowering plants in the family <Family>Apocynaceae</Family>.

Commonly called <MedicinalPlant>wax plants</MedicinalPlant> due to the waxy appearance of their <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> and <PlantPart>flowers</PlantPart>, most species have ornamental value.

A few have been reported to have medicinal properties or used in traditional medicine.

In the <Location>Philippines</Location>, there are at least 109 species of <Location>Hoya</Location>; 88 of these are endemic to the country.

One such endemic species is <Synonym>Hoya meliflua</Synonym> Merr found in <Location>Apayao</Location>, <Location>Bataan</Location>, <Location>Laguna</Location>, <Location>La Union</Location> and <Location>Rizal</Location> in <Location>Luzon Island</Location> and in <Location>Leyte</Location>, <Location>Mindoro</Location>, <Location>Negros</Location>, <Location>Palawan</Location> and <Location>Panay</Location> islands in Central <Location>Philippines</Location> all at low altitudes.

New records of occurrence in other provinces, such as <Location>Laguna</Location>, have not been published yet.

The Plant List.

States that <Synonym>Hoya meliflua</Synonym> is an unresolved name because some data suggest that it is synonymous with <Synonym>Hoya diversifolia</Synonym> Blume which is also found in other countries.

This may be attributed to the confusion on the identity of the two Philippine native species.

This study is part of our research on the chemical constituents of Philippine native hoyas.

We earlier reported the isolation of <Compound>lupenone</Compound> and <Compound>lupeol</Compound> from the <PlantPart>roots</PlantPart>; <Compound>lupeol</Compound>, <Compound>squalene</Compound> and <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> from the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart>; and <Compound>betulin</Compound> from the <PlantPart>stems</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Hoya mindorensis</Synonym> Schlechter.

In another study, we reported the isolation of <Compound>lupeol</Compound>, <Compound>alpha-amyrin</Compound> , <Compound>beta-amyrin</Compound> , <Compound>lupeol acetate</Compound> , <Compound>alpha-amyrin acetate</Compound> <ChemicalClass>Triterpenes</ChemicalClass> and <ChemicalClass>Sterols</ChemicalClass> from <PlantPart>Leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Hoya meliflua</Synonym> Merr..

.: <Location>Hoya</Location> plants are also called <MedicinalPlant>wax plants</MedicinalPlant> due to the waxy appearance of their <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> and <PlantPart>flowers</PlantPart>.

Most species are cultivated as ornamental plants.

In the <Location>Philippines</Location>, there are at least 109 species of <Location>Hoya</Location>; 88 of these are endemic to the country.

One of the endemic species is <Synonym>Hoya meliflua</Synonym> often confused with <Synonym>Hoya diversifolia</Synonym>, which can also be found in other countries.

This study is part of our research on the chemical constituents of Philippine native Hoyas.

Methods: The compounds were isolated by silica gel chromatography and identified by NMR spectroscopy.

Results: Chemical investigation of the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> from the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Hoya meliflua</Synonym> afforded <Compound>squalene</Compound> and mixtures of <Compound>beta-amyrin</Compound> , <Compound>alpha-amyrin</Compound> and <Compound>lupeol</Compound> in about 1:1:0.25 ratio; <Compound>oleanone</Compound> , <Compound>ursenone</Compound> and <Compound>lupenone</Compound> in about 1:1:0.3 ratio; <Compound>beta-amyrin cinnamate</Compound> , <Compound>alpha-amyrin cinnamate</Compound> and <Compound>lupenyl cinnamate</Compound> in about 0.5:0.3:1 ratio; and <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> in about 5:1 ratio. .: The results of our study indicate that <Synonym>Hoya meliflua</Synonym> shares similar chemical characteristics with other members of the genus <Location>Hoya</Location>.

The <ChemicalClass>triterpenes</ChemicalClass> and <ChemicalClass>sterols</ChemicalClass> obtained from <Synonym>Hoya meliflua</Synonym> were also identified from other <Location>Hoya</Location> species.

<Synonym>Hoya meliflua</Synonym> is interesting to note that although most <Location>Hoya</Location> plants have no known biological activity and medicinal property, the compounds isolated from <Synonym>Hoya meliflua</Synonym> possess diverse bioactivities.

Key words: <Synonym>Hoya meliflua</Synonym>, <Family>Apocynaceae</Family>, <Compound>Squalene</Compound>, <Compound>beta-amyrin</Compound>, <Compound>alpha-amyrin</Compound>, <Compound>Lupeol</Compound>, <Compound>Oleanone</Compound>, <Compound>Ursenone</Compound>, <Compound>Lupenone</Compound>, <Compound>beta-amyrin Cinnamate</Compound>, <Compound>alpha-amyrin Cinnamate</Compound>, <Compound>Lupenyl Cinnamate</Compound>, <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>Stigmasterol</Compound>.

Vincent Antonio S. Ng1,*, Raymond S. Malabed, Fernando B. Aurigue, Consolacion Y. Ragasa,4 Vincent Antonio S. Ng1,*, Raymond S. Malabed, Fernando B. Aurigue, Consolacion Y. Ragasa,4 1Chemistry Department, De La Salle University, 2401 <Location>Taft Avenue</Location>, <Location>Manila</Location> 1004, PHILIPPINES.

2Department of Chemistry, Graduate School of Science, <Location>Osaka</Location> University, <Location>Osaka</Location> 560-0043, <Location>JAPAN</Location>.

3Agriculture Research Section, Atomic Research Division, Philippine Nuclear Research Institute-Department of Science and Technology, <Location>Commonwealth Avenue</Location>, Diliman, <Location>Quezon City</Location> 1101, PHILIPPINES.

4Chemistry Department, De La Salle University Science and Technology Complex Leandro <Compound>betulin</Compound>, Locsin Campus, <Location>Binan City</Location>, <Location>Laguna</Location> 4024, PHILIPPINES.

Correspondence Dr.

Vincent Antonio S. Ng Chemistry Department, De La Salle University, 2401 <Location>Taft Avenue</Location>, <Location>Manila</Location> 1004, PHILIPPINES.

Phone no : +632-5360230 E-mail: vincent.ng@dlsu.edu.ph History Submission Date: 25-07-2018; Review completed: 04-10-2018; Accepted Date: 01-11-2018 DOI : 10.5530/pj. .

1.

Article Available online http://www.phcogj.com/v11/i1 Copyright 2019 Phcog.

Net.

This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4. International license.

Cite this article: Vincent AS.

NG, Malabed RS, Aurigue FB, Ragasa CY.

<ChemicalClass>Triterpenes</ChemicalClass> and <ChemicalClass>Sterols</ChemicalClass> from <PlantPart>Leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Hoya meliflua</Synonym> Merr.

Pharmacog J. 2019;11:48-52. and <Compound>beta-amyrin acetate</Compound> from the <PlantPart>stems</PlantPart>; and <Compound>squalene</Compound>, <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>alpha-amyrin</Compound>, <Compound>bauerenol</Compound> , <Compound>lutein</Compound> and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> from the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Hoya multiflora</Synonym> Blume.

Furthermore, the isolation of <Compound>beta-amyrin cinnamate</Compound> and <Compound>taraxerol</Compound> from the <PlantPart>stems</PlantPart>; and <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, <Compound>taraxerol</Compound>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound> and <Compound>chlorophyll a</Compound> from the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Hoya wayetii</Synonym> Kloppenb has been reported.

Moreover, the isolation of <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, <Compound>beta-amyrin cinnamate</Compound>, <Compound>taraxerol</Compound>, <Compound>taraxerone</Compound> and <Compound>alpha-amyrin cinnamate</Compound> from the <PlantPart>stems</PlantPart>; <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>taraxerol</Compound>, and <Compound>taraxerone</Compound>, from the <PlantPart>roots</PlantPart>; <Compound>beta-amyrin cinnamate</Compound>, and <Compound>alpha-amyrin cinnamate</Compound>, from the <PlantPart>flowers</PlantPart>; and <Compound>squalene</Compound>, <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, and saturated hydrocarbons from the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Hoya buotii</Synonym> has been reported.

We also reported the isolation of <Compound>lupeol</Compound>, <Compound>squalene</Compound>, <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>alpha-amyrin</Compound>, <Compound>beta-amyrin</Compound>, <Compound>beta-amyrin cinnamate</Compound>, and XX from the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart>; and <Compound>squalene</Compound>, <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, <Compound>taraxerol</Compound>, and <Compound>lupeol cinnamate</Compound> from the <PlantPart>stems</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Hoya diversifolia</Synonym> Blume.

Chemical investigation of the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> extracts of <Synonym>Hoya cumingiana</Synonym> Decne yielded <Compound>lupeol</Compound>, <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>alpha-amyrin</Compound>, <Compound>beta-amyrin</Compound>, <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, and <Compound>bauerenol</Compound> from the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart>; and <Compound>taraxerol</Compound>, from the <PlantPart>stems</PlantPart>.

Recently, wereported the isolation of <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, and <Compound>taraxerol</Compound>, from the <PlantPart>stems</PlantPart> and <Compound>lupenone</Compound>, <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, <Compound>2-hydroxyethylbenzoate</Compound> and <Compound>fatty acid methyl esters</Compound> from the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Hoya pubicalyx</Synonym>.

In another study, the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> extracts of <Synonym>Hoya paziae</Synonym> Kloppenb yielded <Compound>alpha-amyrin acetate</Compound>, <Compound>beta-amyrin acetate</Compound>, <Compound>taraxerol</Compound>, and <Compound>taraxeryl acetate</Compound> from the <PlantPart>stems</PlantPart> and <Compound>lupeol</Compound>, <Compound>alpha-amyrin</Compound>, <Compound>beta-amyrin</Compound>, <Compound>lupeol fatty acid esters</Compound> Vincent, et al.: <ChemicalClass>Triterpenes</ChemicalClass> and <ChemicalClass>Sterols</ChemicalClass> Pharmacognosy Journal, Vol 11, Issue 1, Jan-Feb, 2019 49 , <Compound>alpha-amyrin fatty acid esters</Compound> and <Compound>beta-amyrin fatty acid esters</Compound> from the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart>.

Furthermore, the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> extracts of <Synonym>Hoya cagayanensis</Synonym> afforded <Compound>lupenone</Compound>, <Compound>lupeol</Compound>, <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, XX and <Compound>dihydrocanaric acid</Compound> , from the <PlantPart>stems</PlantPart>; and <Compound>2-hydroxyethyl benzoate</Compound> from the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart>.

Recently, the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> extracts of <Synonym>Hoya madulidii</Synonym> yielded <Compound>lupeol</Compound>, <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, <Compound>beta-amyrin cinnamate</Compound>, <Compound>alpha-amyrin cinnamate</Compound>, XX and <Compound>lupeol cinnamate</Compound>, from the <PlantPart>stems</PlantPart> and <Compound>squalene</Compound>, <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, <Compound>chlorophyll a</Compound>, and XX from the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart>.

In this study, the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Hoya meliflua</Synonym> yielded <Compound>squalene</Compound>, <Compound>beta-amyrin</Compound> , <Compound>alpha-amyrin</Compound> , <Compound>lupeol</Compound> , <Compound>oleanone</Compound> , <Compound>ursenone</Compound> , <Compound>lupenone</Compound> , <Compound>beta-amyrin cinnamate</Compound> , <Compound>alpha-amyrin cinnamate</Compound> , <Compound>lupenyl cinnamate</Compound> , <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> (Figure 1).

MATERIALS AND METHODS General Experimental Procedure Sample spectra were obtained on a JEOL ECS 400 spectrometer with CDCl as solvent.

Column chromatography was performed, with silica gel 60 (70-230 mesh).

Thin layer chromatography was performed with plastic backed plates coated with silica gel F254 and the plates were visualized by spraying with <Compound>vanillin</Compound>/H2SO4 solution followed by warming.

Sample Collection <Synonym>Hoya meliflua</Synonym> <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> and <PlantPart>stems</PlantPart> were collected from healthy vines of a clone that has been cultivated for more than 10 years.

Samples labeled as PNRI-H.CA were provided under Material Transfer Agreement No. -004 dated June 24, 2016.

The original plant came from <Location>Quezon Province</Location>, <Location>Philippines</Location> and authenticated by one of the authors (FBA).

General Isolation Procedure A glass column 12 inches in height with 0.5 inch internal diameter was used for the fractionation of the crude <Preparation>extract</Preparation>.

Fractions of 10 mL volumes were collected and monitored by thin layer chromatography.

Fractions containing spots with similar Rf values were combined and rechromatographed using the appropriate solvent.

Final purification was carried out using Pasteur pipette as the column, collecting 1 mL fractions.

TLC-pure isolates were combined and after evaporation of the solvent, were subjected to NMR analysis.

Isolation of Chemical Constituents of the <PlantPart>Leaves</PlantPart> The air-dried <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> (252.8 g) were <Preparation>ground</Preparation> in a blender, soaked in CH2Cl2 for three days and then <Preparation>filtered</Preparation>.

The filtrate was concentrated under vacuum to afford a crude <Preparation>extract</Preparation> (7.8 g) which was chromatographed by gradient elution with CH2Cl2, followed by increasing amounts of <Compound>acetone</Compound> at 10% increment by volume as eluents.

The CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed (2 ) using petroleum ether to afford <Compound>squalene</Compound> (12.8 mg).

The 10% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed (3 ) using 1% EtOAc in petroleum ether to yield a mixture of <Compound>beta-amyrin cinnamate</Compound>, <Compound>alpha-amyrin cinnamate</Compound>, and <Compound>lupenyl cinnamate</Compound>, (5.0 mg), after washing with petroleum ether.

The 20% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed (3 ) using 2.5% EtOAc in petroleum ether to yield a mixture of <Compound>oleanone</Compound>, <Compound>ursenone</Compound>, and <Compound>lupenone</Compound>, (10.3 mg), after washing with petroleum ether.

The 30% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed (4 ) using 7.5% EtOAc in petroleum ether to afford a mixture of <Compound>beta-amyrin</Compound>, <Compound>alpha-amyrin</Compound>, and <Compound>lupeol</Compound>, (10.6 mg) after washing with petroleum ether.

The 40% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fractions was rechromatographed (3 ) using 10% EtOAc in petroleum ether to yield a mixture of <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> (21.0 mg) after washing with petroleum ether..

Silica gel chromatography of the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> from the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Hoya meliflua</Synonym> afforded <Compound>squalene</Compound> and mixtures of <Compound>beta-amyrin</Compound> , <Compound>alpha-amyrin</Compound> and <Compound>lupeol</Compound> in about 1:1:0.25 ratio; <Compound>oleanone</Compound> , <Compound>ursenone</Compound> and <Compound>lupenone</Compound> in about 1:1:0.3 ratio; <Compound>beta-amyrin cinnamate</Compound> , <Compound>alpha-amyrin cinnamate</Compound> and <Compound>lupenyl cinnamate</Compound> in about 0.5:0.3:1 ratio; and <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> in about 5:1 ratio.

The structures of these compounds were identified by comparison of their NMR data with those reported in the literature.

The NMR spectra of <Compound>beta-amyrin</Compound>, are in accordance with data reported in the literature for <Compound>beta-amyrin</Compound>, <Compound>alpha-amyrin</Compound>, for <Compound>alpha-amyrin</Compound>, <Compound>lupeol</Compound>, for <Compound>lupeol</Compound>, <Compound>oleanone</Compound>, for <Compound>oleanone</Compound>, <Compound>ursenone</Compound>, for <Compound>ursenone</Compound>, <Compound>lupenone</Compound>, for <Compound>lupenone</Compound>, <Compound>beta-amyrin cinnamate</Compound>, for <Compound>beta-amyrin cinnamate</Compound>, <Compound>alpha-amyrin cinnamate</Compound>, for <Compound>alpha-amyrin cinnamate</Compound>, <Compound>lupenyl cinnamate</Compound>, for <Compound>lupeol cinnamate</Compound>, <Compound>squalene</Compound>, <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>.

The ratio of about 1:1:0.25 for the mixture of <Compound>beta-amyrin</Compound> , <Compound>alpha-amyrin</Compound> and <Compound>lupeol</Compound> was deduced from the intensities and integrations of the 1H NMR resonances for the olefinic protons of <Compound>beta-amyrin</Compound>, at 5.16 (brs),7,12 <Compound>alpha-amyrin</Compound>, at 5.11 (brs)7,12 and <Compound>lupeol</Compound>, at 4.68 (brs) and 4.56 (brs). ,12,18 The ratio of about 1:1:0.30 for the mixture of <Compound>oleanone</Compound> , <Compound>ursenone</Compound> and <Compound>lupenone</Compound> was deduced from the intensities and integrations of the 1H NMR resonances for the olefinic protons of <Compound>oleanone</Compound>, at 5.19 (t, J = 3. Hz),15 <Compound>ursenone</Compound>, at 5.14 (t, J = 3. Hz)15 and <Compound>lupenone</Compound>, at 4.67 (brs) and 4.55 (brs).

The ratio of about 0.5:0.3:1 for the mixture of <Compound>beta-amyrin cinnamate</Compound> , <Compound>alpha-amyrin cinnamate</Compound> and <Compound>lupenyl cinnamate</Compound> was deduced from the intensities and integrations of the 1H NMR resonances for the olefinic protons of <Compound>beta-amyrin cinnamate</Compound>, 5.18 (brs),6,17 <Compound>alpha-amyrin cinnamate</Compound>, at 5.13 (brs);6,17 and <Compound>lupenyl cinnamate</Compound>, at 4.68 (br s) and 4.56 (br s).

The ratio of about 5:1 for the mixture of <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> was deduced from the intensities and integrations of the 1H NMR resonances for olefinic protons at 5.33 (brs, H-5) and methyl protons at 0.66 (s) for <Compound>beta-sitoterol</Compound> and olefinic protons at 5.33 (brs, H-5), 5.13 (dd, J = 8.4, 15.

Hz) and 5.00 (dd, J = 8.4, 15.

Hz) and the methyl protons at 0.68 (s) for <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>.

<Synonym>Hoya meliflua</Synonym> is cultivated as an ornamental plant in the <Location>Philippines</Location>.

There is no reported biological activity and medicinal property for the plant, but Blanco mentioned as early as 1845 a record that <Synonym>Hoya meliflua</Synonym> causes stoppage of birth, or perhaps as an abortifacient.

However, literature search revealed that the compounds isolated from the plant possess diverse activities.

<Compound>Beta-Amyrin</Compound> and <Compound>alpha-amyrin</Compound> were reported to possess <BioAct>anti-inflammatory</BioAct>. -23 and analgesic-25 properties <ChemicalClass>Triterpene</ChemicalClass> <Compound>beta-amyrin</Compound>, showed <BioAct>antifungal</BioAct> activity againstA rabiei with an MIC value of 0.0156 mg/mL, while <Compound>alpha-amyrin</Compound>, was proposed as a possible biomarker for the fungal resistance of <Compound>grape-vine</Compound> <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> (<Synonym>Vitis vinifera</Synonym>).

The mixture of <Compound>beta-amyrin</Compound>, and <Compound>alpha-amyrin</Compound>, effectively reduced the elevated plasma glucose levels during the oral glucose tolerance test (OGTT).

Furthermore, the mixture of <Compound>beta-amyrin</Compound>, and <Compound>alpha-amyrin</Compound>, at 100mg/kg significantly decreased the VLDL and LDL cholesterol and increased the HDL cholesterol.

A review on the sources and biological activities of <Compound>beta-amyrin</Compound>, and <Compound>alpha-amyrin</Compound>, has beenprovided.

Figure 1: Chemical structures of <Compound>beta-amyrin</Compound> , <Compound>alpha-amyrin</Compound> , <Compound>lupeol</Compound> , <Compound>oleanone</Compound> , <Compound>ursenone</Compound> , <Compound>lupenone</Compound> , <Compound>beta-amyrin cinnamate</Compound> , <Compound>alpha-amyrin cinnamate</Compound> and <Compound>lupenyl cinnamate</Compound> .

Vincent, et al.: <ChemicalClass>Triterpenes</ChemicalClass> and <ChemicalClass>Sterols</ChemicalClass> 50 Pharmacognosy Journal, Vol 11, Issue 1, Jan-Feb, 2019 On the other <BodyPart>hand</BodyPart>, <Compound>lupeol</Compound> exhibited antiurolithiatic and diuretic activity.

<Compound>lupeol</Compound> prevented the formation of vesical calculi and reduced the size of the preformed stones in rats.

<Compound>lupeol</Compound> also showed <BioAct>antifungal</BioAct> activity against Fusarium oxysporum and Penicillium notatum.

<ChemicalClass>Triterpene</ChemicalClass> <Compound>lupeol</Compound>, significantly reduced the <CellLine>451Lu</CellLine> tumor growth in athymic nude mice, inhibited the proliferation of <CellLine>MDA-MB-231</CellLine> human <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> cancer cells in a dose dependent manner and induced growth inhibition and apoptosis in hepatocellular carcinoma SMMC cells by downregulation of the death receptor 3 (DR3) expression.

<Compound>lupeol</Compound> exhibited potent <BioAct>anti-inflammatory</BioAct> activity in an allergic airway inflammation model by a significant reduction in eosinophils infiltration and in Th2-associated cytokines levels that trigger the immune responses in asthma.

Another study reported that <Compound>lupeol</Compound>, and <Compound>lupeol acetate</Compound> have shown hypotensive activity.

A review on the biological activities of <Compound>lupeol</Compound> has been provided.

<Compound>Lupenone</Compound> inhibited adipocyte differentiation by suppressing PPAR and C/EBPalpha protein levels.

<Compound>Lupenone</Compound> also increased the tyrosinase enzyme expression via mitogen-activated protein kinase phosphorylated extracellular signal regulated kinases 1 and 2 phosphorylation inhibition which results to stimulation of melanogenesis.

This suggests that <Compound>lupenone</Compound>, could be a possible treatment for hypopigmentation.

<Compound>Beta-Amyrin cinnamate</Compound> was reported to inhibit the TPAS-induced inflammation (ID500.27 mol/<BodyPart>ear</BodyPart>;CI 95% 0.23-0.33 mol/<BodyPart>ear</BodyPart>) which is more inhibitory than the positive control, indomethacin (ID50 0.91 mol/ <BodyPart>ear</BodyPart> ;CI 95% 0.23-0.33 mol/<BodyPart>ear</BodyPart>). <Compound>alpha-Amyrin cinnamate</Compound> , <Compound>lupeol cinnamate</Compound> and <Compound>beta-amyrin cinnamate</Compound>, exhibited marked <BioAct>anti-inflammatory</BioAct> activity against <CellLine>TPA-induced</CellLine> inflammation (ID50 = 0.15-0.75 mol/<BodyPart>ear</BodyPart>).

<ChemicalClass>Triterpene</ChemicalClass> <Compound>lupenyl cinnamate</Compound>, showed the highest activity with ID50 of 0.15 mol/<BodyPart>ear</BodyPart>.

This <ChemicalClass>triterpene</ChemicalClass> at a dose of 10 mg/kg also exhibited <BioAct>anti-inflammatory</BioAct> activity on rat hind paw edema induced by carrageenan.

Furthermore, <Compound>lupenyl cinnamate</Compound>, exhibited inhibitory effect on skin tumor promotion in an in vivo two-stage carcinogenesis test using DMBA as an initiator and <CellLine>TPA</CellLine> as a promoter.

<ChemicalClass>Triterpenes</ChemicalClass> <Compound>beta-amyrin cinnamate</Compound>, <Compound>alpha-amyrin cinnamate</Compound>, <Compound>lupenyl cinnamate</Compound>, showed moderate inhibitory effects on Epstein-Barr virus early antigen (EBV-EA) in <CellLine>Raji</CellLine> cells as a primary screening test for inhibitors of tumor promoters.

<Compound>Squalene</Compound> was reported to significantly suppress colonic ACF formation and crypt multiplicity which strengthened the hypothesis that it possesses chemopreventive activity against colon carcinogenesis.

<Compound>Squalene</Compound> showed cardioprotective effect which is related to inhibition of lipid accumulation by its hypolipidemic properties and/or its <BioAct>antioxidant</BioAct> properties.

A recent study reported that <ChemicalClass>tocotrienols</ChemicalClass>, <ChemicalClass>carotenoids</ChemicalClass>, <Compound>squalene</Compound> and coenzyme Q10 have <BioAct>anti-proliferative</BioAct> effects on <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> cancer cells.

The preventive and therapeutic potential of <Compound>squalene</Compound> containing compounds on tumor promotion and regression have been reported.

A recent review on the bioactivities of <Compound>squalene</Compound> has been provided.

<Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound> was observed to have growth inhibitory effects on human <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> <CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine> and <CellLine>MDAMB-231</CellLine> adenocarcinoma cells.

<Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound> was shown to be effective for the treatment of benign prostatic hyperplasia.

<Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound> was also reported to attenuate <Compound>beta-catenin</Compound> and PCNA expression, as well as quench radical in-vitro, making <Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound> a potential <BioAct>anticancer</BioAct> drug for colon carcinogenesis.

<Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound> can inhibit the expression of <CellLine>NPC1L1</CellLine> in the enterocytes to reduce intestinal cholesterol uptake.

<Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound> was reported to induce apoptosis mediated by the activation of ERK and the downregulation of Akt in MCA-t102 <Compound>murine</Compound> fibrosarcoma cells.

<Compound>Stigmasterol</Compound> showed therapeutic efficacy against Ehrlich ascites carcinoma bearing mice while conferring protection against cancer induced altered physiological conditions.

<Compound>Stigmasterol</Compound> lowered plasma cholesterol levels, inhibited intestinal cholesterol and plant <ChemicalClass>sterol</ChemicalClass> absorption and suppressed hepatic cholesterol and classic <Compound>bile acid</Compound> synthesis in Winstar as well as WKY rats.

Other studies reported that <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> showed cytostatic activity against <CellLine>Hep-2</CellLine> and <CellLine>McCoy</CellLine> cells, markedly inhibited tumour promotion in two stage carcinogenesis experiments, exhibited <BioAct>antimutagenic</BioAct>, topical <BioAct>anti-inflammatory</BioAct>, antiosteoarthriticand <BioAct>antioxidant</BioAct> activities..

The results of our study indicate that <Synonym>Hoya meliflua</Synonym> shares similar chemical characteristics with other members of the genus <Location>Hoya</Location>: <Synonym>Hoya multiflora</Synonym>, <Synonym>Hoya diversifolia</Synonym>, <Synonym>Hoya cumingiana</Synonym>, and <Synonym>Hoya paziae</Synonym> which yielded <Compound>beta-amyrin</Compound> and <Compound>alpha-amyrin</Compound> ; <Synonym>Hoya mindorensis</Synonym>, <Synonym>Hoya multiflora</Synonym>, <Synonym>Hoya diversifolia</Synonym>, <Synonym>Hoya cumingiana</Synonym>, <Synonym>Hoya paziae</Synonym>, <Synonym>Hoya cagayanensis</Synonym>, and <Synonym>Hoya madulidii</Synonym> which contained <Compound>lupeol</Compound> ; <Synonym>Hoya mindorensis</Synonym>, <Synonym>Hoya pubicalyx</Synonym>, and <Synonym>Hoya cagayanensis</Synonym> which afforded <Compound>lupenone</Compound> ; <Synonym>Hoya wayetii</Synonym>, <Synonym>Hoya buotii</Synonym>, and <Synonym>Hoya madulidii</Synonym> which yielded <Compound>beta-amyrin cinnamate</Compound> ; <Synonym>Hoya buotii</Synonym>, and <Synonym>Hoya madulidii</Synonym> which afforded <Compound>alpha-amyrin cinnamate</Compound> ; <Synonym>Hoya diversifolia</Synonym> and <Synonym>Hoya madulidii</Synonym> which provided <Compound>lupenyl cinnamate</Compound> ; <Synonym>Hoya mindorensis</Synonym>, <Synonym>Hoya multiflora</Synonym>, <Synonym>Hoya wayetii</Synonym>, <Synonym>Hoya buotii</Synonym>, <Synonym>Hoya diversifolia</Synonym>, <Synonym>Hoya cumingiana</Synonym>, <Synonym>Hoya pubicalyx</Synonym>, <Synonym>Hoya cagayanensis</Synonym>, and <Synonym>Hoya madulidii</Synonym> which contained <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>; and <Synonym>Hoya mindorensis</Synonym>, <Synonym>Hoya buotii</Synonym>, <Synonym>Hoya diversifolia</Synonym> and <Synonym>Hoya madulidii</Synonym> which contained <Compound>squalene</Compound>.

The most common constituents of the eleven native <Location>Hoya</Location> species studied are <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> which are found in ten species.

Of the twelve compounds isolated from <Synonym>Hoya meliflua</Synonym>, <Compound>lupeol</Compound> is found in eight species, <Compound>squalene</Compound>, <Compound>beta-amyrin</Compound> and <Compound>alpha-amyrin</Compound> in five species, <Compound>lupenone</Compound> and <Compound>beta-amyrin cinnamate</Compound> in four species, <Compound>alpha-amyrin cinnamate</Compound> and <Compound>lupenyl cinnamate</Compound> in three species.

<Compound>Oleanone</Compound> and <Compound>ursenone</Compound> are reported for the first time from Philippine <Location>Hoya</Location> species.

<Compound>Oleanone</Compound> is interesting to note that although most <Location>Hoya</Location> plants have no known biological activity and medicinal property, the compounds isolated from <Synonym>Hoya meliflua</Synonym> possess diverse bioactivities.

Lastly, the difference in results of phytochemical analysis of <Synonym>Hoya meliflua</Synonym> is a proof that it is an entirely different and distinct species from <Synonym>Hoya diversifolia</Synonym>..

VASN would like to thank Prof.

Michio Murata of <Location>Osaka</Location> University for his generous assistance with the NMR measurements.

A research grant from the University Research Coordinating Office (URCO) of De La Salle University <Location>Manila</Location> (07N1TAY16-2TAY17) is gratefully acknowledged.

CONFLICT OF INTEREST The authors declare no conflict of interest.

ABBREVIATIONS CH2Cl2: <Compound>Dichloromethane</Compound>; EtOAc: <Compound>Ethyl acetate</Compound>; Et2O: <Compound>Diethyl</Compound> ether.