Pharmacogn J. 2017; 9:654-.
 <Compound>anacardic acid</Compound>,

A Multifaceted Journal in the field of Natural Products and Pharmacognosy www.phcogj.com | www.journalonweb.com/pj | www.phcog.net Original Article 654 Pharmacognosy Journal, Vol <Compound>linoleic acid</Compound>, Issue <Compound>anacardic acid</Compound>, Sep-Oct, 2017 INTRODUCTON <Synonym>Dracontomelon <MedicinalPlant>dao</MedicinalPlant></Synonym> Blanco Merr et Rolfe of the family <Family>Anacardiaceae</Family>, locally known as <MedicinalPlant>dao</MedicinalPlant> is an indigenous Philippine tree which is also widely distributed through out the <Location>South</Location> and Southeast Asia.

The <MedicinalPlant>dao</MedicinalPlant> <PlantPart>bark</PlantPart> is used against <Illness>dysentery</Illness>.

The mature <PlantPart>fruits</PlantPart> and kernel of the <PlantPart>seeds</PlantPart> are edible, while the <PlantPart>flowers</PlantPart> and young <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> are eaten as vegetables.

The wood of <MedicinalPlant>dao</MedicinalPlant> is employed in light construction, timber and firewood.

The EtOAc <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of D. <MedicinalPlant>dao</MedicinalPlant> was observed to exhibit strong <BioAct>antibacterial</BioAct> activity with an IC50 of 98 <Compound>anacardic acid</Compound>, g/mL.

The crude methanolic extracts of the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart>, <PlantPart>stem</PlantPart> and <PlantPart>root</PlantPart> barks ofD <MedicinalPlant>dao</MedicinalPlant> exhibited a very good level of broad spectrum <BioAct>antibacterial</BioAct> activity, while the <PlantPart>leaf</PlantPart> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> exhibited <BioAct>antifungal</BioAct> activity.

The essential oil was <Preparation>extracted</Preparation> from the skins of <PlantPart>stem</PlantPart> of D. <MedicinalPlant>dao</MedicinalPlant> by steam distillation.

GCMS analysis identified 13 compounds with the following major components: <Compound>nhexadecanoic acid</Compound> (46.13%), octadeca <Compound>noic acid</Compound> (15.44%), (<Compound>E)9octadecenoic acid</Compound> (13.73%), and (<Compound>Z,Z9, 12octadecadienoic acid</Compound> <Compound>monoacylglycerol</Compound>,

79%).

We earlier reported the isolation of <Compound>anacardic acid</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosterylbetaglucopyranoside'Ofatty acid esters</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>phytol</Compound>, <Compound>phytyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid esters</Compound>, <Compound>chlorophyll a</Compound>, <Compound>squalene</Compound>, longchain fatty alcohols, and longchain hydrocarbons from the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of D. <MedicinalPlant>dao</MedicinalPlant>.

We report herein the isolation <Compound>ofcardol</Compound> , <Compound>betasitosterylbetaglucopyranoside</Compound>, <Compound>Ofatty acid esters</Compound> , <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid esters</Compound> , and a mixture Chemical Constituents of Dracontomelon DaoBlanco Merr et Rolfe.

.: The <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart>, <PlantPart>twigs</PlantPart> and <PlantPart>flowers</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Dracontomelon <MedicinalPlant>dao</MedicinalPlant></Synonym> Blanco Merr et Rolfe, an indigenous Philippine tree were investigated for their chemical constituents.

Methods: The compounds were isolated by silica gel chromatography and their structures were identified by NMR spectroscopy.

Results: Chemical investigation of D. <MedicinalPlant>dao</MedicinalPlant> led to the isolation of <Compound>cardol</Compound> , <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside</Compound>-6, <Compound>O-fatty acid esters</Compound> , <Compound>beta-sitosteryl fatty acid esters</Compound> , and a mixture of <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> from the petiole; <Compound>cardol</Compound>, a mixture of <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, <Compound>anacardic acid</Compound> , <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound> , <Compound>monoacylglycerol</Compound> , <Compound>long-chain fatty acid esters</Compound> , and <Compound>linoleic acid</Compound> from the <PlantPart>twigs</PlantPart>; and a mixture of <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, <Compound>anacardic acid</Compound>, <Compound>cylglycerols</Compound>, <Compound>longchain fatty acid esters</Compound>, long-chain fatty alcohols (10), and longchain hydrocatbons (11) from the <PlantPart>flowers</PlantPart> of D. <MedicinalPlant>dao</MedicinalPlant>.The structures of <Compound>cardol</Compound>, and <Compound>anacardic acid</Compound>, were elucidated by extensive 1D and 2D NMR spectroscopy, while those of <Compound>glucopyranoside'Ofatty acid esters</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid esters</Compound>, and 6-11 were identified by NMR spectroscopy. .: This is the first report on the isolation of <Compound>cardol</Compound>, <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, and <Compound>cylglycerols</Compound>, <Compound>monoacylglycerol</Compound>, <Compound>longchain fatty acid esters</Compound>, <Compound>linoleic acid</Compound>, from D. <MedicinalPlant>dao</MedicinalPlant>.

Key words: Dracontomelon Dao Blanco Merr et Rolfe, Anacardaceae, <Compound>Cardol</Compound>, <Compound>Anacardic Acid</Compound>, <Compound>3-Alkylphenols</Compound>, <Compound>B-Sitosteryl-3beta-Glucopyranoside-6'-O-Fatty Acid Esters</Compound>, <Compound>B-Sitosteryl Fatty Acid Esters</Compound>.

Consolacion Y. Ragasa <Compound>glucopyranoside'Ofatty acid esters</Compound>, *,Tyson C. Batarra, Julius Leonard A. Vivar <Compound>cardol</Compound>, Mariquit M. De Los Reyes, and Chien-Chang Shen Consolacion Y. Ragasa <Compound>glucopyranoside'Ofatty acid esters</Compound>, *, Tyson C. Batarra, Julius Leonard A. Vivar <Compound>cardol</Compound>, Mariquit M. De Los Reyes, and Chien-Chang Shen 1Chemistry Department, De La Salle University, 2401 <Location>Taft Avenue</Location>, <Location>Manila</Location> 1004, PHILIPPINES.

2Chemistry Department, De La Salle University Science & Technology Complex Leandro V. Locsin Campus, <Location>Binan City</Location>, <Location>Laguna</Location> 4024, PHILIPPINES.

3Biology Department, De La Salle University, 2401 <Location>Taft Avenue</Location>, <Location>Manila</Location> 1004, PHILIPPINES.

<Compound>4National</Compound> Research Institute of Chinese Medicine, Ministry of Health and Welfare, 155-1, Li-Nong St., <Location>Sec</Location>. , <Location>Taipei</Location> 112, <Location>TAIWAN</Location>.

Correspondence Consolacion Y. Ragasa, Chemistry Department, De La Salle University, 2401 <Location>Taft Avenue</Location>, <Location>Manila</Location> 1004, <Location>Philippines</Location> & Chemistry Department, De La Salle University Science & Technology Complex Leandro V. Locsin Campus, <Location>Binan City</Location>, <Location>Laguna</Location> 4024, PHILIPPINES.

Tel/Fax: (+0632) 5360230 E-mail: consolacion.ragasa@dlsu.edu.ph History Submission Date: 01-05-2017; Review completed: 18-05-2017; Accepted Date: 08-06-2017 DOI : 10.5530/pj. .
 <Compound>anacardic acid</Compound>,

Article Available online http://www.phcogj.com/v9/i5 Copyright 2017 Phcog.

Net.

This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4. International license.

Cite this article : Ragasa CY, Batarra TC, Vivar JLA, Reyes MMDL, Shen C. Chemical Constituents of Dracontomelon DaoBlanco Merr et Rolfe.

Pharmacog J. 2017;9:654-6. of <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound> and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> from the petiole; <Compound>1,anacardic acid</Compound> , a mixture of <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound> , <Compound>monoacylglycerol</Compound> , long <Compound>chain fatty acid esters</Compound> and <Compound>linoleic acid</Compound> and from the <PlantPart>twigs</PlantPart>; and , <Compound>longchain fatty acid esters</Compound>, longchain fatty alcohols (10), and long chainhydrocatbons (11) from the <PlantPart>flowers</PlantPart> of D. <MedicinalPlant>dao</MedicinalPlant>.

The structures of <Compound>cardol</Compound>, <Compound>glucopyranoside'Ofatty acid esters</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid esters</Compound>, <Compound>anacardic acid</Compound>, <Compound>cylglycerols</Compound>, <Compound>monoacylglycerol</Compound>, <Compound>longchain fatty acid esters</Compound>, <Compound>linoleic acid</Compound>, are presented in Figure <Compound>cardol</Compound>, To the best of our knowledge this is the first report on the isolation of <Compound>cardol</Compound>, <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, and <Compound>cylglycerols</Compound>, <Compound>monoacylglycerol</Compound>, <Compound>longchain fatty acid esters</Compound>, <Compound>linoleic acid</Compound>, from D. <MedicinalPlant>dao</MedicinalPlant>.

MATERIALS AND METHODS General Experimental Procedure NMR spectra were recorded on a Varian VNMRS spectrometer in CDCl at 600 MHz for 1H NMR and 150 MHz for 13C NMR spectra.

Column chroma tography was performed with silica gel 60 (70230 mesh).

Thin layer chromatography was performed with plastic backed plates coated withsilica gel F254 and the plates were visualized by spraying with <Compound>vanillin</Compound>/H2SO4 solution followed by warming.

Sample Collection Samples of the petiole, <PlantPart>twigs</PlantPart> and <PlantPart>flowers</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Dracontomelon <MedicinalPlant>dao</MedicinalPlant></Synonym> Blanco Merr et Rolfe were collected from De La Salle University - Science and Technology Complex DLSUSTC Complex Leandro V. Locsin Campus, <Location>Binan City</Location>, <Location>Laguna</Location>, <Location>Philippines</Location> in March Ragasa et al.: Dracontomeladao Pharmacognosy Journal, Vol <Compound>linoleic acid</Compound>, Issue <Compound>anacardic acid</Compound>, Sep-Oct, 2017 655 volume.

The 10% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed <Compound>glucopyranoside'Ofatty acid esters</Compound>, ) using 1% EtOAc in petroleum ether to afford <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid esters</Compound>, <Compound>glucopyranoside'Ofatty acid esters</Compound>, mg).

The first 30% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed using 10% EtOAc in petroleum ether.

The less polar fractions were combined and rechro matographed using 10% EtOAc in petroleum ether to afford <Compound>cardol</Compound>, (4 mg).

The second 30% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed using 15% EtOAc in petroleum ether to yield <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid esters</Compound>, mg) after washing with petroleum ether.

The 60% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid esters</Compound>, ) using CH3CN:Et2O:CH2Cl2 (1:1:8, v/v) to afford <Compound>glucopyranoside'Ofatty acid esters</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid esters</Compound>, mg) after washing with petroleum ether.

Isolation of the chemical constituents from the <PlantPart>twigs</PlantPart> of D. <MedicinalPlant>dao</MedicinalPlant> The airdried D. <MedicinalPlant>dao</MedicinalPlant> <PlantPart>twigs</PlantPart> (87 g) were <Preparation>ground</Preparation> in a blender, soaked in CH2Cl2 for <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid esters</Compound>, days and then <Preparation>filtered</Preparation>.

The solvent was evaporated under vacuum to afford a crude <Preparation>extract</Preparation> (0.30 g) which was chromatographed using increasing proportions of <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 at 10% increment by volume.

The CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed using petroleum ether.

A second rechromatography was conducted using 1% EtOAc in petroleum ether to yield <Compound>longchain fatty acid esters</Compound>, <Compound>glucopyranoside'Ofatty acid esters</Compound>, mg).

The 10% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed by gradient elution using 5% EtOAc in petroleum ether; followed by 10% EtOAc in petroleum ether; then 15% EtOAc in petroleum ether; and finally 20% EtOAc in petroleum ether.

The fractions eluted with 5% EtOAc in petroleum ether were combined and rechro matographed using the same solvent to afford <Compound>cardol</Compound>, <Compound>glucopyranoside'Ofatty acid esters</Compound>, mg) and <Compound>linoleic acid</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid esters</Compound>, mg).

The fractions eluted with% EtOAc in petroleum ether were combined and rechromatographed using the same solvent to yielda mixture of <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, <Compound>cylglycerols</Compound>, mg) after washing with petroleum ether.

The fractions eluted with 20% EtOAc in petroleum ether were combined and rechromatographed using the same solvent to afford <Compound>cylglycerols</Compound>, (4 mg).

The 30% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed using 20% EtOAc in petroleum ether.

The less polar fractions were rechromatographed using CH2Cl2 to yield <Compound>anacardic acid</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid esters</Compound>, mg) after washing with petroleum ether.

The more polar fractions yielded <Compound>monoacylglycerol</Compound>, <Compound>glucopyranoside'Ofatty acid esters</Compound>, mg) after washing with petroleum ether.

Isolation of the chemical constituents from the <PlantPart>flowers</PlantPart> of D. <MedicinalPlant>dao</MedicinalPlant> The airdried D. <MedicinalPlant>dao</MedicinalPlant> <PlantPart>flowers</PlantPart> (19 g) were <Preparation>ground</Preparation> in a blender, soaked in CH2Cl2 for <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid esters</Compound>, days and then <Preparation>filtered</Preparation>.

The solvent was evaporated under vacuum to afford a crude <Preparation>extract</Preparation> (0.300 g) which was chromatographed using increasing proportions of <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 at 10% increment by volume.

The CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed using petroleum ether <Compound>glucopyranoside'Ofatty acid esters</Compound>, ) to afford 11 <Compound>anacardic acid</Compound>, mg) after washing with petroleum ether.

The 10% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed using 1% EtOAc in petroleum ether to yield <Compound>cylglycerols</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid esters</Compound>, mg) and <Compound>longchain fatty acid esters</Compound>, (4 mg).

The 20% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed using 5% EtOAc in petroleum ether to afford 10 <Compound>anacardic acid</Compound>, mg) and a mixture of <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, <Compound>cylglycerols</Compound>, mg) after washing with petroleum ether.

The 30% to 50% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fractions were combined and rechromatographed <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid esters</Compound>, ) using 20% EtOAc in petroleum ether to yield <Compound>anacardic acid</Compound>, (12 mg) after washing with petroleum ether..

Silica gel chromatography of the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> extracts of D. <MedicinalPlant>dao</MedicinalPlant> yielded 1-11.

The NMR spectra of <Compound>cardol</Compound>, are in accordance with data reported in the literature <Compound>forcardanol</Compound> <Compound>monoacylglycerol</Compound>, <Compound>glucopyranoside'Ofatty acid esters</Compound>, for <Compound>betasitosterylbetaglucopyranoside</Compound>' <Compound>Ofatty acid esters</Compound> <Compound>longchain fatty acid esters</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid esters</Compound>, for <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid ester</Compound> <Compound>linoleic acid</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, for <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>;10 <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, for <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>;10 <Compound>anacardic acid</Compound>, for <Compound>anacardic acid</Compound>;11 <Compound>cylglycerols</Compound>, for <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>;12 <Compound>monoacylglycerol</Compound>, for <Compound>monoacylglycerol</Compound>;10 <Compound>longchain fatty acid esters</Compound>, for <Compound>longchain fatty acid esters</Compound>;13 <Compound>linoleic acid</Compound>, for <Compound>linoleic acid</Compound>;14 10 for longchain fatty alcohols;15 and 11 for longchain hydro carbons..

The petiole, <PlantPart>twigs</PlantPart>, <PlantPart>flowers</PlantPart> and <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of D. <MedicinalPlant>dao</MedicinalPlant> afforded phenolics, <ChemicalClass>sterols</ChemicalClass> and lipids.

The following compounds were obtained from the 2016.

The samples were authenticated at the Botany Division, Philippine National Museum.

General Isolation Procedure A glass column 12 inches in height and 0 <Compound>anacardic acid</Compound>, inch internal diameter was used for the chromatography.

The crude extracts were fractionated by silica gel chromatography using increasing proportions of <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 at 10% increment by volume as eluents.

Five milliliter fractions were collected.

All fractions were monitored by thin layer chromatog raphy.

Fractions with spots of the same Rf values were combined and rechromatographed in appropriate solvent systems until TLC pure isolates were obtained.

Final purifications were conducted using Pasteur pipettes as columns.

One milliliter fractions were collected.

Isolation of the chemical constituents from the petole of D. <MedicinalPlant>dao</MedicinalPlant> The airdried <Synonym>Dracontomelon daopetiole</Synonym> (179 <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid esters</Compound>, g) were <Preparation>ground</Preparation> in a blender, soaked in CH2Cl2 for <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid esters</Compound>, days and then <Preparation>filtered</Preparation>.

The solvent was evaporated under vacuum to afford a crude <Preparation>extract</Preparation> (0.90 g) which was chromatographed using increasing proportions of <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 at 10% increment by Figure 1: Chemical structures of cardanols , <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3betaglucopyranoside</Compound>-6, <Compound>O-fatty acid esters</Compound> , <Compound>beta-sitosteryl fatty acid esters</Compound> , <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> , <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> , <Compound>anacardic acid</Compound> , <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound> , <Compound>monoacylglycerol</Compound> , <Compound>long-chain fatty acid esters</Compound> and <Compound>linoleic acid</Compound> from D. <MedicinalPlant>dao</MedicinalPlant>.

Ragasa et al.: Dracontomeladao 656 Pharmacognosy Journal, Vol <Compound>linoleic acid</Compound>, Issue <Compound>anacardic acid</Compound>, Sep-Oct, 2017 different parts of the tree: <Compound>cardol</Compound> from the petiole; betasitosterylbeta <Compound>glucopyranoside'Ofatty acid esters</Compound> from the petiole and <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart>; <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid esters</Compound> from the petiole; <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound> from the petiole, <PlantPart>twigs</PlantPart>, <PlantPart>flowers</PlantPart> and <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart>; <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> from the petiole, <PlantPart>twigs</PlantPart> and <PlantPart>flowers</PlantPart>; <Compound>anacardic acid</Compound> from the <PlantPart>twigs</PlantPart>, <PlantPart>flowers</PlantPart> and <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart>; tria <Compound>cylglycerols</Compound> from the <PlantPart>twigs</PlantPart> and <PlantPart>flowers</PlantPart>; <Compound>monoacylglycerol</Compound> from the <PlantPart>twigs</PlantPart>; <Compound>longchain fatty acid esters</Compound> from the <PlantPart>twigs</PlantPart> and <PlantPart>flowers</PlantPart>; <Compound>linoleic acid</Compound> from the <PlantPart>twigs</PlantPart>; longchain fatty alcohols (10) and long chain hydrocarbons (11) from the <PlantPart>flowers</PlantPart>..

A research grant from the Science Foundation through the URCO is gratefully acknowledged.

CONFLICT OF INTEREST There is no conflict of interest.

List of Abbreviations: NMR - Nuclear Magnetic Resonance, EtOAc - <Compound>Ethyl acetate</Compound>, Et2O - <Compound>Diethyl</Compound> ether.