Pharmacogn J. 2018; 10:620-621 A Multifaceted Journal in the field of Natural Products and Pharmacognosy www.phcogj.com | www.journalonweb.com/pj | www.phcog.net Original Article 620 Pharmacognosy Journal, Vol 10, Issue 4, Jul-Aug, 2018.

<Synonym>Cymodocea rotundata</Synonym> is a widespread seagrass that occurs in shallow water, on sand-mud in sheltered coves or bays, lagoons, <BodyPart>mouth</BodyPart> of rivers and coral reefs throughout the <Location>Philippines</Location>.

<Synonym>Cymodocea rotundata</Synonym> has a wide IndoPacific distribution and is relatively common within its range.

<Synonym>Cymodocea rotundata</Synonym> extracts exhibited predominant growth inhibitory activity against UTI bacteria and human pathogens.

Phytochemical analysis of <Synonym>Cymodocea rotundata</Synonym> extracts indicated the presence of tannins, saponins, resins, proteins, acidic compounds, reducing sugars, terpenoids, cardiac <Compound>glycosides</Compound> and <ChemicalClass>alkaloids</ChemicalClass>.

Another study reported that <Synonym>Cymodocea rotundata</Synonym> contained vitamin C (28.43 mg g-) and <Compound>p-coumaric acid</Compound>.

<Synonym>Cymodocea rotundata</Synonym> extracts gave a total <BioAct>antioxidant</BioAct> activity of 6.65 mg <Compound>ascorbic acid</Compound> equivalent/g and was found to be a potent DPPH radical scavenger (70.

30%).

This study is part of our research on the chemical constituents of seagrasses found in the <Location>Philippines</Location>.

We earlier reported the isolation of bis(2-ethylhexyl) <Compound>phthalate</Compound>, <Compound>chlorophyll a</Compound>, <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> from <Synonym>Cymodocea serrulata</Synonym>.

We report herein the isolation of <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-Ofatty acid esters</Compound> , <Compound>chlorophyll a</Compound> and a mixture of <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> from <Synonym>Cymodocea rotundata</Synonym>.

To the best of our knowledge, this is the first report on the isolation of 1-3b from <Synonym>Cymodocea rotundata</Synonym>.

MATERIALS AND METHODS NMR spectra were recorded on a Varian VNMRS spectrometer in CDCl at 600 MHz for 1H NMR and 150 MHz for 13C NMR spectra.

Column chromatography was performed with silica gel 60 (70-230 mesh).

Chemical Constituents of <Synonym>Cymodocea rotundata</Synonym> Asch and Schweinf.

.: <Synonym>Cymodocea rotundata</Synonym> Asch and Schweinf, a widespread seagrass with reported <BioAct>antimicrobial</BioAct> activity, was investigated for its chemical constituents.

Methods: The compounds were isolated by silica gel chromatography and identified by NMR spectroscopy.

Results: This study has led to the isolation of <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-O-fatty acid esters</Compound> , <Compound>chlorophyll a</Compound> and a mixture of <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> in about 1:1 ratio from the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of <Synonym>Cymodocea rotundata</Synonym>. .: This is the first report on the isolation of 1-3b from <Synonym>Cymodocea rotundata</Synonym>.

Compounds 2-3b were reported to exhibit <BioAct>antibacterial</BioAct> activity and may be partly responsible for the reported <BioAct>antimicrobial</BioAct> activity of the <Synonym>Cymodocea rotundata</Synonym> <Preparation>extract</Preparation>.

Key words: <Synonym>Cymodocea rotundata</Synonym>, <Family>Cymodoceaceae</Family>, <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-Ofatty acid esters</Compound>, <Compound>Chlorophyll</Compound> , <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>Stigmasterol</Compound>.

Judy D. V. Perez <Compound>chlorophyll a</Compound>, Chien Chang Shen, Consolacion Y. Ragasa* Judy D.

V.

Perez <Compound>chlorophyll a</Compound>, Chien Chang Shen, Consolacion Y. Ragasa,4* 1Chemistry Department, De La Salle University, 2401 <Location>Taft Avenue</Location>, <Location>Manila</Location> 1004, PHILIPPINES.

2Natural Science Department, College of Arts and Sciences, Ateneo de Naga University, P. Santos St, <Location>Penafrancia</Location>, Naga, <Location>Camarines Sur</Location>, PHILIPPINES.

<Compound>3National</Compound> Research Institute of Chinese Medicine, Ministry of Health and Welfare, 155-1, Li-Nong St., <Location>Sec</Location>. , <Location>Taipei</Location> 112, <Location>TAIWAN</Location>.

4Chemistry Department, De La Salle University Science and Technology Complex Leandro V. Locsin Campus, <Location>Binan City</Location>, <Location>Laguna</Location> 4024, PHILIPPINES.

Correspondence Consolacion Y Ragasa Chemistry Department, De La Salle University Science and Technology Complex Leandro V. Locsin Campus, <Location>Binan City</Location>, <Location>Laguna</Location> 4024, PHILIPPINES.

E-mail: consolacion.ragasa@dlsu.edu.ph History Submission Date: 01-01-2018; Review completed: 14-02-2018; Accepted Date: 05-03-2018 DOI : 10.5530/pj. .

4.

Article Available online http://www.phcogj.com/v10/i4 Copyright 2018 Phcog.

Net.

This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4. International license.

Cite this article: Perez J, Shen CC, Ragasa CY.

Chemical Constituents of <Synonym>Cymodocea rotundata</Synonym> Asch and Schweinf.

Pharmacog J. 2018;10:620-1. Thin layer chromatography was performed with plastic backed plates coated with silica gel F254 and the plates were visualized by spraying with <Compound>vanillin</Compound>/ H2SO4 solution followed by warming.

Sample Collection Samples of the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Cymodocea rotundata</Synonym> Asch and Schweinf were collected from the seagrass meadow of <Location>Caramoan</Location>, <Location>Camarines Sur</Location> <Location>Philippines</Location> in September 2016.

The samples were authenticated at the Botany Division, Philippine National Museum.

General Isolation Procedure A glass column 6 inches in height and 0.25 inch internal diameter was used for the chromatography.

The crude extracts were fractionated by silica gel chromatography using increasing proportions of <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 at 10% increment by volume as eluents.

Five milliliter fractions were collected.

All fractions were monitored by thin layer chromatography.

Fractions with spots of the same Rf values were combined and rechromatographed in appropriate solvent systems until TLC pure isolates were obtained.

Final purifications were conducted using Pasteur pipettes as columns.

One milliliter fractions were collected.

Isolation of the Chemical Constituents from the <PlantPart>Leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Cymodocea rotundata</Synonym> The air-dried <Synonym>Cymodocea rotundata</Synonym> (50 g) <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> were <Preparation>ground</Preparation> in a blender, soaked in CH2Cl2 for 3 days and then <Preparation>filtered</Preparation>.

The solvent was evaporated under vacuum to afford a crude <Preparation>extract</Preparation> (0.3 g) which was chromatoRagasa et al.: <Synonym>Cymodocea rotundata</Synonym> Pharmacognosy Journal, Vol 10, Issue 4, Jul-Aug, 2018 621 graphed using increasing proportions of <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 at 10% increment by volume.

The 10% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed using 10% EtOAc in petroleum ether.

The less polar fractions were combined and rechromatographed using 10% EtOAc in petroleum ether to afford <Compound>chlorophyll a</Compound>, (4 mg) after washing with petroleum ether, followed by Et2O.

The more polar fractions were combined and rechromatographed <Compound>chlorophyll a</Compound>, ) using 15% EtOAc in petroleum ether to yield a mixture of <Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound>, and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, (6 mg) after washing with petroleum ether.

The 60% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed using CH3CN:Et2O:CH2Cl2 (1:1:8, v/v) to afford <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-O-fatty acid esters</Compound>, (3 mg) after washing with petroleum ether..

Silica gel chromatography of the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of <Synonym>Cymodocea rotundata</Synonym> has led to the isolation of <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-O-fatty acid esters</Compound> , <Compound>chlorophyll a</Compound> and a mixture of <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> .

The NMR data of <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-O-fatty acid esters</Compound>, are in accordance with the data reported in the literature for <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-O-fatty acid esters</Compound>;8 <Compound>chlorophyll a</Compound>, for <Compound>chlorophyll a</Compound>9 <Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound>, for <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>;10,11 and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, for <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>.

Although no biological activity tests were conducted on the isolated compounds, literature search revealed that 2-3b exhibited <BioAct>antibacterial</BioAct> activities.

<Compound>Chlorophyll</Compound> and its derivatives were reported to exhibit <Illness>wound</Illness> healing properties and <BioAct>antibacterial</BioAct> activities.

<Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound> and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> were also reported to possess <BioAct>antibacterial</BioAct> activities. ,15,16,17.

This is the first report on the isolation of 1-3b from <Synonym>Cymodocea rotundata</Synonym>.

Compounds 2-3b were reported to exhibit <BioAct>antibacterial</BioAct> activity and may be partly responsible for the reported <BioAct>antimicrobial</BioAct> property of the <Synonym>Cymodocea rotundata</Synonym> <Preparation>extract</Preparation>..

A research grant from the De La Salle University Science Foundation through the URCO is gratefully acknowledged.

ABBREVAITINS EtOAc: <Compound>ethyl acetate</Compound>; Et2O: <Compound>diethyl</Compound> ether.

CONFLICT OF INTEREST The authors declare no conflict of interest.