Int.

J. Pharm.

Sci. Rev.

Res., 33, July - August 2015; Article No. , Pages: 107-109 ISSN 0976 - 044X International Journal of Pharmaceutical Sciences Review and Research Available online at www.globalresearchonline.net Copyright protected.

Unauthorised republication, reproduction, distribution, dissemination and copying of this document in whole or in part is strictly prohibited.

Copyright protected.

Unauthorised republication, reproduction, distribution, 107 Consolacion Y. Ragasaa,b*, Vincent Antonio S. Ngb, Esperanza Maribel G. Agooc, Chien-Chang Shend aChemistry Dept, De La Salle University Science & Technology Complex, Leandro V. Locsin Campus, <Location>Binan City</Location>, <Location>Laguna</Location>, <Location>Philippines</Location> bChemistry Department, De La Salle University 2401 Taft Avenue, <Location>Manila</Location>, <Location>Philippines</Location> cBiology Department, De La Salle University 2401 Taft Avenue, <Location>Manila</Location>, <Location>Philippines</Location> <Compound>dNational</Compound> Research Institute of Chinese Medicine, Ministry of Health and Welfare, 155-1, Li-Nong St., <Location>Sec</Location>. , <Location>Taipei</Location>, <Location>Taiwan</Location>. *Corresponding author's E-mail: consolacion.ragasa@dlsu.edu.ph Accepted on: 07-06-2015; Finalized on: 31-07-2015..

Chemical investigation of the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> extracts of <Synonym>Cycas edentata</Synonym> led to the isolation of <Compound>9alphaH-isopimara-7,15-diene</Compound> , <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid ester</Compound> , and a mixture of <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> from the <PlantPart>bark</PlantPart>; and <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid ester</Compound>, and a mixture of <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, from the <PlantPart>sclerotesta</PlantPart>.

The structure of <Compound>alphaH-Isopimara-7,15-diene</Compound>, was elucidated by extensive 1D and 2D NMR spectroscopy, while those of 2-3b were identified by comparison of their NMR data with those reported in the literature.

Keywords: <Synonym>Cycas edentata</Synonym>, <Family>Cycadaceae</Family>, <Compound>9alphaH-isopimara-7,15-diene</Compound>, <Compound>beta-sitosteryl fatty acid ester</Compound>, <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>.

ycas edentata of the <Family>Cycadaceae</Family> family is classified as near threatened by the IUCN.

This species which occurs along shorelines is declining due to loss of coastal habitat.

<Synonym>Cycas edentata</Synonym> is native to <Location>Indonesia</Location>, <Location>Malaysia</Location>, <Location>Myanmar</Location>, <Location>Philippines</Location>, <Location>Thailand</Location> and <Location>Vietnam</Location>.

There are no reported chemical and biological activity studies on <Synonym>Cycas edentata</Synonym>.

This study was conducted as part of our research on the chemical constituents of Cycas species that are endemic and native to the <Location>Philippines</Location>.

We recently reported the isolation of <Compound>squalene</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, and <Compound>triglycerides</Compound> from the <PlantPart>sarcotesta</PlantPart>; <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound> and <Compound>phytyl fatty acid esters</Compound> from the <PlantPart>endotesta</PlantPart>; <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, and <Compound>beta-sitosteryl fatty acid esters</Compound> from the <PlantPart>sclerotesta</PlantPart>; and <Compound>beta-sitosteryl fatty acid esters</Compound> from the <PlantPart>bark</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Cycas sancti-lasallei</Synonym>.

Another Cycas species, <Synonym>Cycas lacrimans</Synonym> yielded <Compound>isopimaran-ol</Compound> from the <Compound>megasporophyll</Compound> lamina; <Compound>9alphaH-isopimara,15-diene</Compound> and <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound> from the <PlantPart>bark</PlantPart>; <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, <Compound>oleic acid</Compound>, and <Compound>1,2-dioleylglycerol</Compound> from the leaflets; <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> from the <PlantPart>petiole and rachis</PlantPart>; <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> from the <PlantPart>roots</PlantPart>; and <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound> and <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> from the <PlantPart>endotesta</PlantPart> and <PlantPart>sclerotesta</PlantPart>.

We report herein the isolation of <Compound>9alphaH-isopimara-7,15diene</Compound> , <Compound>beta-sitosteryl fatty acid ester</Compound> , and a mixture of <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> in about 3.5:1 ratio from the <PlantPart>bark</PlantPart>; and <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid ester</Compound>, and a mixture of <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, in about 3.5:1 ratio from the <PlantPart>sclerotesta</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Cycas edentata</Synonym>.

To the best of our knowledge this is the first report on the isolation of 1-3b from the plant.

MATERIALS AND METHODS General Experimental Procedure NMR spectra were recorded on a Varian VNMRS spectrometer in CDCl at 600 MHz for 1H NMR and 150 MHz for 13C NMR spectra.

Column chromatography was performed with silica gel 60 (70-230 mesh).

Thin layer chromatography was performed with plastic backed plates coated with silica gel F254 and the plates were visualized by spraying with <Compound>vanillin</Compound>/H2SO4 solution followed by warming.

Plant Material <Synonym>Cycas edenta</Synonym> <PlantPart>bark</PlantPart> and <PlantPart>sclerotesta</PlantPart> were collected in November 2014 and authenticated by one of the authors (EMGA).

Voucher specimens were deposited in the De La Salle University-Manila Herbarium (DLSUH 3114).

General Isolation Procedure A glass column 18 inches in height and <Compound>alphaH-Isopimara-7,15-diene</Compound>, 0 inch internal diameter was used for the chromatography of the crude extracts.

Twenty milliliter fractions were collected.

All fractions were monitored by thin layer chromatography.

Fractions with spots of the same Rf values were combined and rechromatographed in appropriate solvent systems until TLC pure isolates were obtained.

A glass column 12 inches in height and 0.5 inch internal diameter was used for the rechromatography of smaller fractions from the first column.

Five milliliter fractions were collected.

Chemical Constituents of <Synonym>Cycas edentata</Synonym> C Research Article Int.

J. Pharm.

Sci. Rev.

Res., 33, July - August 2015; Article No. , Pages: 107-109 ISSN 0976 - 044X International Journal of Pharmaceutical Sciences Review and Research Available online at www.globalresearchonline.net Copyright protected.

Unauthorised republication, reproduction, distribution, dissemination and copying of this document in whole or in part is strictly prohibited.

Copyright protected.

Unauthorised republication, reproduction, distribution, 108 Final purifications were conducted using Pasteur pipettes as columns.

One milliliter fractions were collected.

Isolation of the Chemical Constituents of the <PlantPart>Bark</PlantPart> The air-dried <PlantPart>bark</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Cycas edentata</Synonym> (144 g) were <Preparation>ground</Preparation> in a blender, soaked in CH2Cl2 for 3 days and then <Preparation>filtered</Preparation>.

The solvent was evaporated under vacuum to afford a crude <Preparation>extract</Preparation> (0.7 g) which was chromatographed using increasing proportions of <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 at 10% increment.

The CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed (3 ) using petroleum ether to afford <Compound>alphaH-Isopimara-7,15-diene</Compound>, (3 mg) after washing with petroleum ether.

The 10% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid ester</Compound>, ) in 5% EtOAc in petroleum ether to yield <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid ester</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid ester</Compound>, mg) after washing with petroleum ether.

The 30% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed (4 ) in CH3CN:Et2O:CH2Cl2 (0.5:0.5:9 by volume) to yield a mixture of <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, (4 mg) after washing with petroleum ether.

Isolation of the Chemical Constituents of the <PlantPart>Sclerotesta</PlantPart> The air-dried <PlantPart>sclerotesta</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Cycas edentata</Synonym> (48 g) were <Preparation>ground</Preparation> in a blender, soaked in CH2Cl2 for 3 days and then <Preparation>filtered</Preparation>.

The solvent was evaporated under vacuum to afford a crude <Preparation>extract</Preparation> (0 <Compound>alphaH-Isopimara-7,15-diene</Compound>, g) which was chromatographed using increasing proportions of <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 at 10% increment.

The CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed (3 ) in 5% EtOAc in petroleum ether to yield <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid ester</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid ester</Compound>, mg) after washing with petroleum ether.

The 40% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid ester</Compound>, ) in 20% EtOAc in petroleum ether to yield a mixture of <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, (7 mg) after washing with petroleum ether. <Compound>alphaH-Isopimara-7,15-diene</Compound> : 1H NMR (600 MHz, CDCl): 0.85 (6H, s, H-17, H-20), 0.86 (3H, s, H-18); 0.90 (3H, s, H-19), 4.85 (d, J=10.

Hz, H-16), 4.92 (d, J=17.

Hz, H-16), 5.34 (brs, H-7), 5.80 (dd, J=17.4, 10.

Hz, H-15).

CNMR (150 MHz, CDCl): 14.94 (C-20), 18.85 (C-2), 20.19 (C11), 21.46 (C-17), 22.69 (C-19), 23.46 (C-6), 32.82 (C-4), 33.62 (C-18), 35.43 (C-10), 36.22 (C-12), 37.38 (C-13), 39.87 (C-1), 42.28 (C-3), 46.18 (C-14), 50.38 (C-5), 52.00 (C-9), 109.13 (C-16), 121.68 (C-7), 135.52 (C-8), 150.50 (C15).

<Compound>Beta-Sitosteryl Fatty Acid Esters</Compound> :13C NMR (150 MHz, CDCl): 36.99 (C-1), 31.52 (C-2), 73.68 (C-3), 42.30 (C-4), 139.71 (C-5), 122.58 (C-6), 32.19, 31.92 (C-7, C-8), 50.01 (C-9), 36.15 (C-10), 21.02 (C-11), 39.71(C-12), 42.30 (C13), 56.67 (C-14), 24.28 (C-15), 28.24 (C-16), 56.01(C-17), 11.84 (C-18), 19.32 (C-19), 36.59 (C-20), 19.02 (C-21), 33.92 (C-22), 29.13 (C-23), 45.82 (C-24), 26.04 (C-25), 18.76 (C-26), 19.81 (C-27), 23.05 (C-28), 11.97 (C-29), 173.30 (C-1'), 34.70 (C-2'), 29.76, 29.70, 29.65, 29.59, 29.52, 29.47, 29.36, 29.34, 29.32, 29.27, 29.25, 29.16, 29.13, 29.10, 29.08, 27.80, 27.21, 27.19, 27.16, 26.39, 26.04, 25.62, 25.06, 25.04, 24.28, 23.42, 23.05, 22.69, 22.57 (CH2), 130.21, 130.06, 129.98, 129.76 (CH=), 14.12, 14.07 (terminal CH3).

<Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound> : 13C NMR (150 MHz, CDCl): 37.24 (C1), 31.65 (C-2), 71.81 (C-3), 42.31 (C-4), 140.74 (C-5), 121.72 (C-6), 31.89, 31.90 (C-7, C-8), 50.14 (C-9), 36.49 (C10), 21.07 (C-11), 39.76 (C-12), 42.20 (C-13), 56.75 (C-14), 24.35 (C-15), 28.24 (C-16), 56.03 (C-17), 11.97 (C-18), 19.39 (C-19), 36.14 (C-20), 18.77 (C-21), 33.93 (C-22), 26.04 (C-23), 45.82 (C-24), 29.13 (C-25), 19.02 (C-26), 19.81 (C-27), 23.05 (C-28), 11.85 (C-29).

<Compound>Stigmasterol</Compound> : 13C NMR (150 MHz, CDCl): 37.24 (C1), 31.65 (C-2), 71.81 (C-3), 42.29 (C-4), 140.74 (C-5), 121.72 (C-6), 31.89 (C-7, C-8), 50.11 (C-9), 36.49 (C-10), 21.09 (C-11), 39.67 (C-12), 42.20 (C-13), 56.85 (C-14), 24.35 (C-15), 28.92 (C-16), 55.93 (C-17), 12.04 (C-18), 19.39 (C-19), 40.49 (C-20), 21.09 (C-21), 138.31 (C-22), 129.25 (C-23), 51.23 (C-24), 31.89 (C-25), 21.20 (C-26), 18.97 (C-27), 25.40 (C-28), 12.25 (C-29)..

Silica gel chromatography of the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> extracts of <Synonym>Cycas edentata</Synonym> yielded 1-3b from the <PlantPart>bark</PlantPart>; and 23b from the <PlantPart>sclerotesta</PlantPart>.

The structure of <Compound>alphaH-Isopimara-7,15-diene</Compound>, was elucidated by extensive 1D and 2D NMR spectroscopy and confirmed by comparison of its NMR data with those reported in the literature for <Compound>9alphaHisopimara-7,15-diene</Compound>.

Compounds 2-3b were identified by comparison of their NMR data with those reported in the literature for <Compound>betasitosteryl fatty acid ester</Compound> ,3 <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> ,4 and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> .

The mixture of <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, in about 3.5:1 ratio was deduced from the 1H NMR resonances for the olefinic protons of <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, at 5.33 (dd, J <Compound>alphaH-Isopimara-7,15-diene</Compound>, 8, 5. Hz, H-6) and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, at 5.33 (dd, J <Compound>alphaH-Isopimara-7,15-diene</Compound>, 8, 5. Hz, H-6), 5.13 (dd, J=9.0, 15.

Hz, H22) and 5.00 (dd, J=9.0, 15.

Hz, H-23). .: A research grant from the Commission on Higher <Compound>Education-Philippine</Compound> Higher Education Research Network (CHED-PHERNet) of the <Location>Philippines</Location> is gratefully acknowledged.