Available online www.jocpr.com Journal of Chemical and Pharmaceutical Research, 2013, <Compound>trilinolenin</Compound>, 12):1237-1243 Research Article ISSN : 0975-7384 <Location>CODEN</Location>(<Location>USA</Location>) : JCPRC 1237 <ChemicalClass>Sterols</ChemicalClass>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound> and <Compound>essential fatty acid</Compound> constituents of <Synonym>Brassica oleracea</Synonym> varieties, <Synonym>Brassica juncea</Synonym> and <Synonym>Raphanus sativus</Synonym> Consolacion Y. Ragasa*, Vincent Antonio S. Ng2, Oscar B. Torres, Nicole Samantha Y. Sevilla, Kim Valerie M. Uy2, Ma.

Carmen S. Tan2, Marissa G. Noel and Chien-Chang Shen 1Chemistry Department, De La Salle University Science & Technology Complex Leandro V. Locsin Campus, <Location>Binan City</Location>, <Location>Laguna</Location>, <Location>Philippines</Location> 2Chemistry Department De La Salle University, 2401 <Location>Taft Avenue</Location>, <Location>Manila</Location>, <Location>Philippines</Location> <Compound>3National</Compound> Research Institute of Chinese Medicine, 155-1, Li-Nong St., <Location>Sec</Location>. , <Location>Taipei</Location> 112, <Location>Taiwan</Location>.

. The <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> extracts of the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Brassica oleracea</Synonym> var capitata f. rubra L (red cabbage) and <Synonym>Brassica oleracea</Synonym> L (green/white cabbage) and the <PlantPart>stem</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Brassica oleracea</Synonym> L var italic (broccoli) afforded <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> and unsaturated <Compound>triglycerides</Compound> .

The red cabbage also afforded <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> , while the green/white cabbage and broccoli <PlantPart>stem</PlantPart> also yielded the <Compound>essential fatty acid</Compound>, <Compound>linoleic acid</Compound> .

<Synonym>Brassica juncea</Synonym> (mustard) <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> and <Synonym>Raphanus sativus</Synonym> (radish) <PlantPart>roots</PlantPart> afforded <Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound>, and the <Compound>essential fatty acids</Compound> <Compound>Linoleic acid</Compound>, and <Compound>alpha-linolenic acid</Compound> .

Mustard <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> also yielded <Compound>trilinolenin</Compound> , <Compound>lutein</Compound> and <Compound>beta-carotene</Compound> , while radish <PlantPart>roots</PlantPart> also afforded <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, These compounds were reported to exhibit <BioAct>anticancer</BioAct> properties.

Keywords: <Synonym>Brassica oleracea</Synonym> var capitata f. rubra L, red cabbage, <Synonym>Brassica oleracea</Synonym> L., green/white cabbage, <Synonym>Brassica oleracea</Synonym> L var italic, broccoli, <Synonym>Brassica juncea</Synonym>, mustard, <Synonym>Raphanus sativus</Synonym>, radish, <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, <Compound>linoleic acid</Compound>, <Compound>trilinolenin</Compound>, <Compound>linolenic acid</Compound>, <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, <Compound>lutein</Compound>, <Compound>beta-carotene</Compound>.

. The vegetables of the <Family>Brassicaceae</Family> family include <Synonym>Brassica oleracea</Synonym> var capitata f. rubra L (red cabbage), <Synonym>Brassica oleracea</Synonym> L. (green/white cabbage), <Synonym>Brassica oleracea</Synonym> L var italic (broccoli), <Synonym>Brassica juncea</Synonym> (mustard) and <Synonym>Raphanus sativus</Synonym> (radish) which have been shown to exhibit cancer preventing effects due to their high content of glucosinolates which hydrolyze to form products such as bioactive isothiocyanates.

Phytochemical screening on the <PlantPart>leaf</PlantPart> extracts of <Synonym>Brassica oleracea</Synonym> L. var capitata revealed the presence of <ChemicalClass>alkaloids</ChemicalClass>, tannins, saponins, <Compound>phenols</Compound>, <Compound>glycosides</Compound>, steroids, terpenoids and <ChemicalClass>flavonoids</ChemicalClass>.

The ethanolic <Preparation>extract</Preparation> with the highest phenolic compounds exhibited the greatest anti-oxidant activity.

The <PlantPart>leaf</PlantPart> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of <Synonym>Brassica oleracea</Synonym> L. var capitata possesses significant hepatoprotective activity.

Chemical components analysis of <Synonym>Brassica oleracea</Synonym> L. var capitata has shown that it is rich in phenolic compounds , <ChemicalClass>carotenoids</ChemicalClass> and glucosinolates.

Methanolic extracts of <Synonym>Brassica oleracea</Synonym> var capitata f. rubra L were shown to exhibit synergistic <BioAct>anticancer</BioAct> effects against HeLa and HepG cells.

An earlier study reported that the major constituents of red cabbage are isothiocyanates (<Compound>glucosinolate</Compound>), vitamins A, B, C and anthocyanins.

In a recent study, it was reported that Consolacion Y. Ragasa et al J. Chem.

Pharm. Res., 2013, <Compound>trilinolenin</Compound>, 12):1237-1243.

1238 polyphenolic compounds (<Compound>phenyl</Compound> propanoids, <ChemicalClass>flavonols</ChemicalClass> and anthocyanins) are the major antioxidants in red cabbage.
 <Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound>, HO HO <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, H2C HC OC(CH2)7CH=CHCHCH=CHCHCH=CHCHCH3 OC(CH2)7CH=CHCHCH=CHCHCH=CHCHCH3 H2C OC(CH2)7CH=CHCHCH=CHCHCH=CHCHCH3 O O O <Compound>trilinolenin</Compound>, COOH <Compound>Linoleic acid</Compound>, <Compound>alpha-linolenic acid</Compound>, COOH <Compound>Beta-carotene</Compound>, OH HO <Compound>lutein</Compound>, H2C HC OCR OCR' H2C OCR" O O O <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, R, R', R" = <Compound>linoleic acid</Compound>, <Compound>linolenic acid</Compound> Chemical constituents of <Synonym>Brassica oleracea</Synonym> varieties, <Synonym>Brassica juncea</Synonym> and <Synonym>Raphanus sativus</Synonym>: <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> , <Compound>triglyceride</Compound> , <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> , <Compound>linoleic acid</Compound> , <Compound>trilinolenin</Compound> , <Compound>alpha-linolenic acid</Compound> , <Compound>lutein</Compound> and <Compound>beta-carotene</Compound> <Compound>beta-Sitosterol</Compound> is a major <ChemicalClass>sterol</ChemicalClass> of <Synonym>Brassica oleracea</Synonym> L. var botrytis italica Plenck.

The vegetable contains glucosinolates, <ChemicalClass>flavonoids</ChemicalClass>, vitamins and mineral nutrients as well as antioxidants such as <Compound>beta-carotene</Compound>, <Compound>alphatocopherol</Compound>, indoles and isothiocyanates.

<Compound>3,3'-Indolylmethane</Compound> and <Compound>indole-3-carbinol</Compound>, hydrolysis by-products of Consolacion Y. Ragasa et al J. Chem.

Pharm. Res., 2013, <Compound>trilinolenin</Compound>, 12):1237-1243.

1239 broccoli, exhibited multiple chemo-preventive effects through the inhibition of androgen and estrogen related mechanisms and signaling pathways mediating the cell cycle.

.

The isothiocyanates commonly found in broccoli, <Compound>sulforaphane</Compound> and erucin, inhibited the expression of LasR, a <Compound>transcriptional</Compound> activator, through the disruption of quorum sensing in <Synonym>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</Synonym>.

Mammospheres or <PlantPart>stem</PlantPart>/progenitor cells from <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> adenocarcinoma immortalized cell lines, <CellLine>MCF7</CellLine> and SUM159, were treated with <Compound>sulforaphane</Compound>.

Anti-proliferation of these cells was induced due to the decreased presence of <Compound>aldehyde</Compound> dehydrogenase enzyme activity.

The major constituents of the essential oils in the <PlantPart>seeds</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Brassica juncea</Synonym> (L.) Coss., grown in <Location>Hebei</Location>, <Location>Shaanxi</Location> and <Location>Shandong Province</Location> were allyl <Compound>isothiocyanate</Compound> (61.3%), <Compound>diallyl trisulfide</Compound> (9.7%) and <Compound>3-butenyl isothiocyanate</Compound> <Compound>trilinolenin</Compound>, 9%).

Another study reported that <Synonym>Brassica juncea</Synonym> <PlantPart>seed</PlantPart> oil afforded <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>campesterol</Compound> and <Compound>brassicasterol</Compound>.

The chemical constituents of <Synonym>Brassica juncea</Synonym> include glucosinolates, ascorbate, <Compound>folate</Compound> and <ChemicalClass>sterols</ChemicalClass> (<Compound>brassicasterol</Compound>, <ChemicalClass>sitosterol</ChemicalClass> and brassinosteroids).

<Synonym>Raphanus sativus</Synonym> (radish) sprouts and mature radish taproot contained glucosinolates, isothiocyanates, phenolics and anthocyanins.

The <Compound>major fatty acids</Compound> in <PlantPart>seed</PlantPart> lipids of radish were erucic, oleic, linoleic, and linolenic acids, while the <Compound>major fatty acids</Compound> in radish family lipids were <Compound>linolenic acid</Compound> (52-55%), <Compound>erucic acid</Compound> (30-33%), and <Compound>palmitic acid</Compound> (20-22%).

This study was conducted on the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> extracts of the Brassica vegetables red cabbage (<Synonym>Brassica oleracea</Synonym> var capitata f. rubra L), green/white cabbage (<Synonym>Brassica oleracea</Synonym> L.), broccoli (<Synonym>Brassica oleracea</Synonym> L var italic), mustard (<Synonym>Brassica juncea</Synonym>) and radish (<Synonym>Raphanus sativus</Synonym>).

Results of this study identified the relatively nonpolar constituents which may contribute to the <BioAct>anticancer</BioAct> properties of these vegetables.

We report herein the <ChemicalClass>sterols</ChemicalClass>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound> and <Compound>essential fatty acid</Compound> constituents of local collections of <Synonym>Brassica oleracea</Synonym> varieties, <Synonym>Brassica juncea</Synonym> and <Synonym>Raphanus sativus</Synonym>.

<ChemicalClass>Carotenoids</ChemicalClass> were also isolated as the major constituents of <Synonym>Brassica juncea</Synonym>.

These compounds have been reported to exhibit <BioAct>anticancer</BioAct> properties.

EXPERIMENTAL SECTION General Experimental Procedures NMR spectra were recorded on a Varian VNMRS spectrometer in CDCl at 600 MHz for 1H NMR and 150 MHz for 13C NMR spectra.

Column chromatography was performed with silica gel 60 (70-230 mesh).

Thin layer chromatography was performed with plastic backed plates coated with silica gel F254 and the plates were visualized by spraying with <Compound>vanillin</Compound>/H2SO4 solution followed by warming.

Plant Materials Five kg each of red and green cabbage and broccoli were purchased from Arranque market in September 2011.

The samples were authenticated as <Synonym>Brassica oleracea</Synonym> var capitata f. rubra L (red cabbage), <Synonym>Brassica oleracea</Synonym> L (green/white cabbage) and <Synonym>Brassica oleracea</Synonym> L var italica (broccoli) at the Bureau of Plant industry, <Location>Quirino Avenue</Location>, <Location>Manila</Location>, <Location>Philippines</Location>.

One kg of mustard was collected from a private farm in Sitio Usiwan, <Location>Barangay Palola</Location>, <Location>Lucban</Location>, <Location>Quezon</Location> in March 2013.

<Synonym>Brassica oleracea</Synonym> was identified as <Synonym>Brassica juncea</Synonym> at the Bureau of Plant industry, <Location>Quirino Avenue</Location>, <Location>Manila</Location>, <Location>Philippines</Location>.

One kg of radish <PlantPart>roots</PlantPart> was bought from Arranque market in March 2013.

<Synonym>Brassica oleracea</Synonym> was identified as <Synonym>Raphanus sativus</Synonym> at the Botany Division, Philippine National Museum.

Extraction and Isolation The air-dried <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Brassica oleracea</Synonym> var capitata f. rubra L (red cabbage) (480 g), <Synonym>Brassica oleracea</Synonym> L (green/white cabbage) (515 <Compound>trilinolenin</Compound>, g) and the freeze-dried <PlantPart>stems</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Brassica oleracea</Synonym> L var italic (broccoli) (87 <Compound>trilinolenin</Compound>, g) were separately <Preparation>ground</Preparation> in a blender, soaked in CH2Cl2 for three days, and then <Preparation>filtered</Preparation>.

The filtrates were concentrated under vacuum to afford the crude extracts: red cabbage <Compound>alpha-linolenic acid</Compound>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, g), green/white cabbage <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, <Compound>Linoleic acid</Compound>, g) and broccoli (0 <Compound>alpha-linolenic acid</Compound>, g).

The freeze-dried mustard <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> (379 <Compound>Linoleic acid</Compound>, g) and radish <PlantPart>roots</PlantPart> (56 <Compound>trilinolenin</Compound>, g) were <Preparation>ground</Preparation> in a blender, soaked in CH2Cl2 for three days, and then <Preparation>filtered</Preparation> to afford crude extracts: mustard <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> (9 <Compound>Beta-carotene</Compound>, g) and radish <PlantPart>roots</PlantPart> (170 <Compound>trilinolenin</Compound>, mg).

The crude extracts were separately fractionated by silica gel chromatography using increasing proportions of <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 (10% increment) as eluents.

A glass column 18 inches in height and <Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound>, 0 inch internal diameter was used for the fractionation of the crude extracts.

Five milliliter fractions were collected.

Fractions with spots of the same Rf values were combined and rechromatographed in appropriate solvent systems until TLC pure isolates were obtained.

A glass column 12 inches in height and 0 <Compound>trilinolenin</Compound>, inch internal diameter was used Consolacion Y. Ragasa et al J. Chem.

Pharm. Res., 2013, <Compound>trilinolenin</Compound>, 12):1237-1243.

1240 for the rechromatography.

Two milliliter fractions were collected.

Final purifications were conducted using Pasteur pipettes as columns.

One milliliter fractions were collected.

The 20% to 40% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fractions from the chromatography of the crude red cabbage <Preparation>extract</Preparation> were combined and rechromatographed in 15% EtOAc in petroleum ether.

The less polar fractions were rechromatographed <Compound>Linoleic acid</Compound>, ) in 5% EtOAc in petroleum ether to afford a mixture of <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, (25 mg).

The more polar fractions were rechromatographed <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, ) in 15% EtOAc in petroleum ether to afford a mixture of <Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound>, and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, (12 mg) in about 7:1 ratio after washing with petroleum ether.

The CH2Cl2 to 40% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fractions from the chromatography of the crude green/white cabbage <Preparation>extract</Preparation> were combined and rechromatographed in 15% EtOAc in petroleum ether.

The less polar fractions were rechromatographed <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, ) in 5% <Compound>ethyl acetate</Compound> in petroleum ether to afford <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, (12 mg).

The more polar fractions were rechromatographed in 15% <Compound>ethyl acetate</Compound> in petroleum ether.

The less polar fractions were rechromatographed <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, ) in 15% <Compound>ethyl acetate</Compound> in petroleum ether to afford <Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound>, (12 mg) after washing with petroleum ether.

The more polar fractions were rechromatographed in 15% <Compound>ethyl acetate</Compound> in petroleum ether to afford <Compound>Linoleic acid</Compound>, (18 mg).

The 40% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction from the chromatography of the crude broccoli <PlantPart>stems</PlantPart> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> was rechromatographed <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, ) in 15% EtOAc in petroleum ether to afford <Compound>Linoleic acid</Compound>, (9 mg).

The 60% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction from the chromatography of the crude broccoli <Preparation>extract</Preparation> was rechromatographed in 15% EtOAc in petroleum ether.

The less polar fractions were rechromatographed <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, ) in 5% EtOAc in petroleum ether to afford <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, (14 mg).

The more polar fractions were rechromatographed <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, ) in 15% EtOAc in petroleum ether to afford <Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound>, (11 mg) after washing with petroleum ether.

The 10% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction from the chromatography of the crude mustard <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> was rechromatographed <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, ) in <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, 5% EtOAc in petroleum ether to afford <Compound>Beta-carotene</Compound>, (13 mg) after washing with petroleum ether.

The 30% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction from the chromatography of the crude mustard <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> was rechromatographed <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, ) in <Compound>lutein</Compound>, 5% EtOAc in petroleum ether to afford <Compound>trilinolenin</Compound>, (15 mg).

The 40% to 50% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fractions from the chromatography of the crude mustard <Preparation>extract</Preparation> were combined and rechromatographed in 20% EtOAc in petroleum ether.

The less polar fractions were rechromatographed <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, ) in 20% EtOAc in petroleum ether to afford <Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>Beta-carotene</Compound>, mg) after washing with petroleum ether.

The more polar fractions were rechromatographed <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, ) in acetonitrile:Et2O:CH2Cl2 (0.5:0.5:9 by volume) to afford a mixture of <Compound>Linoleic acid</Compound>, and <Compound>alpha-linolenic acid</Compound>, (14 mg) in a 1:2 ratio and <Compound>lutein</Compound>, (19 mg) after washing with petroleum ether, followed by <Compound>diethyl</Compound> ether.

The 10% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction from the chromatography of the crude radish <PlantPart>roots</PlantPart> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> was rechromatographed <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, ) in 5% EtOAc in petroleum ether to afford <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, <Compound>alpha-linolenic acid</Compound>, mg).

The 40% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction from the chromatography of the crude radish <PlantPart>roots</PlantPart> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> was rechromatographed <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, ) in 15% EtOAc in petroleum ether to afford <Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound>, mg) after washing with petroleum ether.

The 50% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction from the chromatography of the crude radish <PlantPart>roots</PlantPart> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> was rechromatographed <Compound>Linoleic acid</Compound>, ) in acetonitrile:Et2O:CH2Cl2 (0.5:0.5:9 by volume) afford a mixture of <Compound>Linoleic acid</Compound>, and <Compound>alpha-linolenic acid</Compound>, <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, mg)..

The <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> extracts from the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Brassica oleracea</Synonym> var capitata f. rubra L (red cabbage) and <Synonym>Brassica oleracea</Synonym> L (green/white cabbage) and the <PlantPart>stem</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Brassica oleracea</Synonym> L var itali (broccoli) afforded <Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound>, and <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, The red cabbage also yielded <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, while the green/white cabbage and broccoli <PlantPart>stem</PlantPart> also yielded <Compound>Linoleic acid</Compound>, The structures of <Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, and <Compound>Linoleic acid</Compound>, were identified by comparison of their 13C NMR data with those reported in the literature for <Compound>betasitosterol</Compound> , unsaturated <Compound>triglyceride</Compound> , <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> and <Compound>linoleic acid</Compound> , respectively.

The <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> extracts of the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Brassica juncea</Synonym> (mustard) and the <PlantPart>roots</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Raphanus sativus</Synonym> (radish) yielded <Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound>, and the <Compound>essential fatty acids</Compound>, <Compound>Linoleic acid</Compound>, and <Compound>alpha-linolenic acid</Compound> .

Mustard <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> also afforded <Compound>trilinolenin</Compound> , <Compound>lutein</Compound> and <Compound>beta-carotene</Compound> , while radish <PlantPart>roots</PlantPart> also yielded <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, The structures of <Compound>trilinolenin</Compound>, <Compound>alpha-linolenic acid</Compound>, <Compound>lutein</Compound>, and <Compound>Beta-carotene</Compound>, were identified by comparison of their 13C NMR data with those reported in the literature for <Compound>trilinolenin</Compound> , <Compound>alpha-linolenic acid</Compound> , <Compound>lutein</Compound> and <Compound>beta-carotene</Compound> , respectively.

The presence of <Compound>alpha-linolenic acid</Compound> in the <Compound>triglyceride</Compound> was deduced from the methyl triplet at 0.96 (t, J = <Compound>lutein</Compound>, Hz), the double allylic methylenes at <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, 78 and the olefinic protons at <Compound>trilinolenin</Compound>, 34 (m).

The presence <Compound>linoleic acid</Compound> Consolacion Y. Ragasa et al J. Chem.

Pharm. Res., 2013, <Compound>trilinolenin</Compound>, 12):1237-1243.

1241 was deduced from the methyl triplet at 0.86 (t, J = <Compound>alpha-linolenic acid</Compound>, Hz), the double allylic <Compound>methylene</Compound> at <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, <Compound>Beta-carotene</Compound>, and the olefinic protons at <Compound>trilinolenin</Compound>, 34 (m).

Based on integrations of the <Compound>triglyceride</Compound> methyls at 0.96 (t, J = <Compound>lutein</Compound>, Hz) and 0.86 (t, J = <Compound>alpha-linolenic acid</Compound>, Hz), the ratio of <Compound>linolenic acid</Compound> and <Compound>linoleic acid</Compound> in the <Compound>triglycerides</Compound> of red cabbage and radish is about 1:1. On the other <BodyPart>hand</BodyPart>, the <Compound>triglyceride</Compound> in mustard is <Compound>trilinolenin</Compound> based on the methyl resonance at 0.96 (t, J = <Compound>lutein</Compound>, Hz).

No other methyl resonance in the shielded region of the spectrum was detected for the <Compound>triglyceride</Compound> in mustard.

A mixture of <Compound>alpha-linolenic acid</Compound> and <Compound>linoleic acid</Compound> in a 1:1 ratio was deduced from the integrals of the methyl triplets at 0.96 (t, J = <Compound>lutein</Compound>, Hz) and 0.86 (t, J = <Compound>lutein</Compound>, Hz) for the <Compound>fatty acids</Compound> in red cabbage and radish.

In mustard, a mixture of <Compound>alpha-linolenic acid</Compound> and <Compound>linoleic acid</Compound> in a 2:1 ratio was deduced from the integrals of the methyl triplets at 0.96 (t, J = <Compound>lutein</Compound>, Hz) and 0.86 (t, J = <Compound>lutein</Compound>, Hz) for the <Compound>fatty acids</Compound>.

Although no biological activity tests were conducted on the isolated compounds, literature search revealed that these have several known bioactivities.

<Compound>alpha-linolenic acid</Compound> is interesting to note that <Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, <Compound>Linoleic acid</Compound>, <Compound>trilinolenin</Compound>, <Compound>alpha-linolenic acid</Compound>, <Compound>lutein</Compound>, <Compound>Beta-carotene</Compound>, were all reported as <BioAct>anticancer</BioAct> compounds.

<Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound> was observed to have growth inhibitory effects on human <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> <CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine> and <CellLine>MDA-MB-231</CellLine> adenocarcinoma cells.

<Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound> was shown to be effective for the treatment of benign prostatic hyperplasia.

<Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound> was also reported to attenuate <Compound>beta-catenin</Compound> and PCNA expression, as well as quench radical in-vitro, making <Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound> a potential <BioAct>anticancer</BioAct> drug for colon carcinogenesis.

<Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound> can inhibit the expression of <CellLine>NPC1L1</CellLine> in the enterocytes to reduce intestinal cholesterol uptake.

<Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound> was reported to induce apoptosis mediated by the activation of ERK and the downregulation of Akt in MCA-102 <Compound>murine</Compound> fibrosarcoma cells.

On the other <BodyPart>hand</BodyPart>, <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> shows therapeutic efficacy against Ehrlich ascites carcinoma bearing mice while conferring protection against cancer induced altered physiological conditions.

A <Compound>triglyceride</Compound>, <Compound>trilinolein</Compound> exhibited protective effects against cardiovascular disorders.

<Compound>triglyceride</Compound> also inhibits ischemiainduced ventricular arrhythmias and <Compound>triglyceride</Compound> exhibits anti-oxidant effect.

<Compound>triglyceride</Compound> was also reported to inhibit the growth of human non-small cell lung carcinoma A549 and induce apoptosis in a doseand timedependent manner.

Another study reported that <Compound>triglycerides</Compound> showed a direct relationship between toxicity and increasing unsaturation, which in turn correlated with increasing susceptibility to oxidation.

<Compound>Trilinolenin</Compound> (18:3; -3) was toxic only after prolonged incubation.

<Compound>Linoleic acid</Compound> belongs to the <Compound>omega-6 fatty acids</Compound>.

<Compound>Linoleic acid</Compound> was reported to be a strong anticarcinogen in a number of animal models.

<Compound>Linoleic acid</Compound> reduces risk of colon and <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> cancer and lowers cardiovascular disease risk and inflammations.

Omega-3 <Compound>polyunsaturated fatty acids</Compound> (n-3 PUFA), <Compound>eicosapentaenoic acid</Compound> (EPA), <Compound>docosahexaenoic acid</Compound> (DHA) and <Compound>alpha-linolenic acid</Compound> (ALA) , and <Compound>their fatty acid ethyl esters</Compound>, exhibited strong <BioAct>antibacterial</BioAct> activity against various oral pathogens, including <Synonym>Streptococcus mutans</Synonym>, <Synonym>Candida albicans</Synonym>, <Synonym>Aggregatibacter actinomycetemcomitans</Synonym>, <Synonym>Fusobacterium nucleatum</Synonym>, and <Synonym>Porphyromonas gingivalis</Synonym>.

They also showed <BioAct>anti-inflammatory</BioAct> effects.

Peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor- (PPAR-) and cyclooxygenase-2 (COX-2) inhibition serve as two signaling pathways for the inhibitory effects of <Compound>alpha-linolenic acid</Compound> (ALA) on the human renal cell carcinoma (RCC) cell proliferation.

Another study reported that apoptosis of hepatoma cells was induced by the <Compound>alpha-linolenic acid</Compound>enriched diet which correlated with a decrease in <Compound>arachidonate</Compound> content in hepatoma cells and decreased cyclooxygenase-2 expression.

-Linolenic acid (GLA) and <Compound>alpha-linolenic acid</Compound> (ALA) exhibited greater than 90% cytotoxicity between 500 M and <Compound>Beta-Sitosterol</Compound>, mM against all but two malignant micro-organ cultures tested in 5-10% serum.

GLA and ALA killed tumor at concentrations of <Compound>triglycerides</Compound>, mM and above in tests using 30-40% serum.

Dietary <Compound>lutein</Compound> , especially at 0.002%, inhibited tumor growth by selectively modulating apoptosis, and by inhibiting angiogenesis.

Another study reported that the chemopreventive properties of all-trans <Compound>retinoic acid</Compound> (ATRA) and <Compound>lutein</Compound> may be attributed to their differential effects on apoptosis pathways in normal versus transformed mammary cells.

A previous study reported that very low amounts of dietary <Compound>lutein</Compound> (0.002%) can efficiently decrease mammary tumor development and growth in mice.

<Compound>Beta-carotene</Compound> dose-dependently induced apoptosis and cell differentiation in cultured leukemia cells, but not in normal cells.

Another study reported that <Compound>beta-carotene</Compound> could reduce damage caused by radiation therapy and decrease local cancer recurrence.

<Compound>beta-carotene</Compound> also inhibited angiogenesis by altering the <Compound>cytokine</Compound> profile and the activation and nuclear translocation of transcription factors.

Consolacion Y. Ragasa et al J. Chem.

Pharm. Res., 2013, <Compound>trilinolenin</Compound>, 12):1237-1243.

1242.

The <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> extracts of Brassica vegetables (red cabbage, green cabbage, broccoli and mustard) and radish afforded similar major constituents: <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, unsaturated <Compound>triglycerides</Compound> and <Compound>essential fatty acids</Compound> (linoleic and linolenic acids) which were reported to exhibit <BioAct>anticancer</BioAct> properties.

Thus, the <BioAct>anticancer</BioAct> properties of Brassica vegetables and radish are not only attributed to the high content of glucosinolates, but also to the presence of <ChemicalClass>sterols</ChemicalClass>, unsaturated <Compound>triglycerides</Compound> and <Compound>essential fatty acids</Compound>.

Acknowledgment A research grant from the De La Salle University Challenge Grant through the Office of the Vice Chancellor for Research and Innovation of is gratefully acknowledged.