Available online at www.derpharmachemica.com ISSN 0975-413X <Location>CODEN</Location> (<Location>USA</Location>): PCHHAX Der Pharma Chemica, 2016, 8(20):193-196 (http://derpharmachemica.com/archive.html) 193 Chemical Constituents of <Synonym>Alstonia scholaris</Synonym> (L.) R. Br.

Consolacion Y. Ragasa,2,*, Tyson C. Batarra, Maria Carmen S. Tan1 and Ian A. van Altena 1Chemistry Department, De La Salle University, 2401 <Location>Taft Avenue</Location>, <Location>Manila</Location> 1004, <Location>Philippines</Location> 2Chemistry Department, De La Salle University Science & Technology Complex Leandro V. Locsin Campus, <Location>Binan City</Location>, <Location>Laguna</Location> 4024, <Location>Philippines</Location> <Compound>3School</Compound> of Environmental and Life Sciences, Faculty of Science and Information Technology, Chemistry, The University of Newcastle-Australia, Callaghan, NSW, 2308, <Location>Australia</Location>.

. Chemical investigation of the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Alstonia scholaris</Synonym> (L.) R. Br has yielded mixtures of <Compound>erythrodiol</Compound> , <Compound>uvaol</Compound> , and <Compound>betulin</Compound> in a 1:1:1 ratio, <Compound>oleanolic acid</Compound> and <Compound>ursolic acid</Compound> in a 2:1 ratio, <Compound>beta-amyrin acetate</Compound> and <Compound>alpha-amyrin acetate</Compound> in a 1:4 ratio, and <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> in a 3:2 ratio; <Compound>squalene</Compound> , <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-O-fatty acid</Compound> esters , and <Compound>chlorophyll a</Compound>.

The structures of <Compound>squalene</Compound>, <Compound>chlorophyll a</Compound>, were identified by comparison of their NMR data with literature data.

Keywords: <Synonym>Alstonia scholaris</Synonym>, <Family>Apocynaceae</Family>, <Compound>erythrodiol</Compound>, <Compound>uvaol</Compound>, <Compound>erythrodiol</Compound>, <Compound>betulin</Compound>, <Compound>oleanolic acid</Compound>, <Compound>ursolic acid</Compound>, <Compound>betaamyrin acetate</Compound>, <Compound>alpha-amyrin acetate</Compound>, <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, <Compound>squalene</Compound>, <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-O-fatty acid</Compound> esters, <Compound>chlorophyll a</Compound>

. <Synonym>Alstonia scholaris</Synonym> (L.) R. Br., locally known as <MedicinalPlant>dita</MedicinalPlant>, is used for the treatment of <Illness>fever</Illness>, chronic <Illness>diarrhea</Illness>, dysentery, beri-beri, congestion of the <BodyPart>liver</BodyPart>, and ulcers.

Previous studies reported the isolation of 2,3-secofernane <ChemicalClass>triterpenoids</ChemicalClass>, alstonic acids A and B ; 3beta-aceta<CellLine>te-2</CellLine>-<Compound>nor-urs-4,12-diene ester</Compound> <ChemicalClass>triterpene</ChemicalClass>, <Compound>3beta-hydroxy-24-nor-urs4,12,28-triene</Compound> <ChemicalClass>triterpene</ChemicalClass>, <Compound>3,28-beta-diacetoxy-5-olea-triterpene</Compound>, <Compound>alpha-amyrin acetate</Compound>, and <Compound>ursolic acid lupeol acetate</Compound> ; <ChemicalClass>flavonoids</ChemicalClass> ; <ChemicalClass>monoterpene</ChemicalClass> , <ChemicalClass>triterpene</ChemicalClass> [8-10]; iridoids ; <Compound>megastigmane-3beta,4alpha,9-triol</Compound>, <Compound>7-megastigmene,6,9-triol</Compound> and C13-norisoprenoid from <Synonym>Alstonia scholaris</Synonym>.

The essential oil of the <PlantPart>flowers</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Alstonia scholaris</Synonym> yielded 2-dodecyloxirane (31.83%), <Compound>1,2-dimethoxy-4-(2-propenyl)benzene</Compound> (8.49%), <Compound>spinacene</Compound> (6.09%), 1,54dibromotetrapentacontane <Compound>squalene</Compound>, 13%), 2,6,10,15-tetramethylheptadecane (4.91%), <Compound>terpinyl acetate</Compound> (3.74%), <Compound>linalool</Compound> (2.22%), tritetracontane (2.17%), <Compound>2-(3-methyl-1,3-butadienyl)-1,3,3-trimethyl-1-cyclohexanol</Compound> (1.78%), <Compound>9-methyl-5methylene-8-decen-2-one</Compound> (1.58%) as the main constituents.

The ethanolic <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of the <PlantPart>flowers</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Alstonia scholaris</Synonym> afforded <Compound>alstoprenyol</Compound>, 3-beta-hydroxy-28-beta-acetoxy-5-olea, <Compound>alstoprenylene</Compound> 3beta-aceta<CellLine>te-2</CellLine>-<Compound>nor-urs-4,12,2'-triene ester</Compound>, <Compound>alpha-amyrin acetate</Compound>, <Compound>alpha-amyrin</Compound>, <Compound>lupeol acetate</Compound>, and <Compound>3beta-hydroxy-24-nor-urs-4,12,28-triene</Compound>.

Many studies reported the isolation of <ChemicalClass>alkaloids</ChemicalClass> from <Synonym>Alstonia scholaris</Synonym> [15-24]. In an earlier study, we reported the isolation of <Compound>cycloeucalenol</Compound>, <Compound>cycloartanol</Compound>, <Compound>lupeol</Compound>, <Compound>lupeol acetate</Compound>, and <Compound>betulin</Compound> from the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Alstonia scholaris</Synonym>.

Recently, we obtained mixtures of <Compound>alpha-amyrin acetate</Compound>, <Compound>beta-amyrin acetate</Compound> and <Compound>lupeol</Compound> Consolacion Y. Ragasa et al Der Pharma Chemica, 2016,8 (20):193-196.

194 acetate; and <Compound>alpha-amyrin fatty acid esters</Compound>, <Compound>beta-amyrin fatty acid esters</Compound>, <Compound>lupeol fatty acid esters</Compound> and <Compound>phytyl fatty acid esters</Compound> from the <PlantPart>flowers</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Alstonia scholaris</Synonym>.

In this study, the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Alstonia scholaris</Synonym> afforded mixtures of <Compound>erythrodiol</Compound> , <Compound>uvaol</Compound> , and <Compound>betulin</Compound> ; <Compound>oleanolic acid</Compound> and <Compound>ursolic</Compound> ; <Compound>beta-amyrin acetate</Compound> and <Compound>alpha-amyrin acetate</Compound> ; <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> ; <Compound>squalene</Compound> ; <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside</Compound>-6' -<Compound>O-fatty acid</Compound> esters ; and <Compound>chlorophyll a</Compound>.

The structures of <Compound>squalene</Compound>, <Compound>chlorophyll a</Compound>, are presented in Fig..

R' R H R' R H <Compound>uvaol</Compound>, R = OH, R' = CH2OH <Compound>2a):ursolic acid</Compound>, R = OH, R' = COOH <Compound>3a):alpha-amyrin acetate</Compound>, R = CH3COO, R' = CH3 23 <Compound>erythrodiol</Compound>, R = OH, R'= CH2OH <Compound>oleanolic acid</Compound>, R = OH, R' = COOH 3a R = CH3COO, R' = CH3 CH2OH HO H <Compound>betulin</Compound>, <Compound>squalene</Compound>, N N CH3 N N Mg O H H3C H C O OH3CO O <Compound>chlorophyll a</Compound>, CH3 H3C <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, HO <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, HO 6 R = long <Compound>chain fatty acid</Compound> O O OH HO HO O R O Fig..

Chemical structures of <Compound>erythrodiol</Compound> , <Compound>uvaol</Compound> , <Compound>betulin</Compound> , <Compound>oleanolic acid</Compound> , <Compound>ursolic</Compound> , <Compound>beta-amyrin acetate</Compound> , <Compound>alpha-amyrin acetate</Compound> , <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> , <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> , <Compound>squalene</Compound> , <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-O-fatty acid</Compound> esters , <Compound>chlorophyll a</Compound> from the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Alstonia scholaris</Synonym> MATERIALS AND METHODS General Experimental Procedure 1H NMR spectra were recorded in CDCl on a Bruker Ascend 400 in CDCl at 400 MHz.

Column chromatography was performed with silica gel 60 (70-230 mesh, Merck).

Thin layer chromatography was performed with plastic backed plates coated with silica gel F254 (Merck) and the plates were visualized by spraying with <Compound>vanillin</Compound>/H2SO4 solution followed by warming.

All solvents used are analytical grade.

Sample Collection Samples of <Synonym>Alstonia scholaris</Synonym> (L.) R. Br <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> were collected from the De La Salle University - <Location>Manila</Location> campus in October 2015.

The samples were authenticated at the Botany Division, Philippine National Museum.

Consolacion Y. Ragasa et al Der Pharma Chemica, 2016,8 (20):193-196.

195 General Isolation Procedure A glass column 12 inches in height and 0 <Compound>squalene</Compound>, inch internal diameter was used for the chromatography.

The crude extracts were fractionated by silica gel chromatography using increasing proportions of <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 at 10% increment by volume as eluents.

Five milliliter fractions were collected.

All fractions were monitored by thin layer chromatography.

Fractions with spots of the same Rf values were combined and rechromatographed in appropriate solvent systems until TLC pure isolates were obtained.

Final purifications were conducted using Pasteur pipettes as columns.

One milliliter fractions were collected.

Isolation of the Chemical Constituents from the <PlantPart>Leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Alstonia scholaris</Synonym> The air-dried <Synonym>Alstonia scholaris</Synonym> <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> (113.21 g) were <Preparation>ground</Preparation> in a blender, soaked in CH2Cl2 for 3 days and then <Preparation>filtered</Preparation>.

The solvent was evaporated under vacuum to afford a crude <Preparation>extract</Preparation> (1.22 g) which was chromatographed using increasing proportions of <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 in 10% increments by volume.

The 10% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed (2 ) using petroleum ether to yield <Compound>squalene</Compound>, (4 mg).

The 20% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed (2 ) using petroleum ether to afford a mixture of 3a and <Compound>3a):alpha-amyrin acetate</Compound>, (4 mg) after washing with petroleum ether.

The 30% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed (3 ) using 10% EtOAc in petroleum ether to yield <Compound>chlorophyll a</Compound>, (3 mg) after washing with petroleum ether, followed by Et2O.

The 40% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed using 15% EtOAc in petroleum ether, followed by 20% EtOAc in petroleum ether.

The fractions eluted with 15% EtOAc in petroleum ether were combined and rechromatographed using the same solvent to afford a mixture of <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, (3 mg) after washing with petroleum ether.

The fractions eluted with 20% EtOAc in petroleum ether were combined and rechromatographed using the same solvent to yield a mixture of <Compound>erythrodiol</Compound>, <Compound>uvaol</Compound>, and <Compound>betulin</Compound>, <Compound>squalene</Compound>, mg) after washing with petroleum ether.

The 50% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed (3 ) using 20% EtOAc in petroleum ether to yield a mixture of <Compound>oleanolic acid</Compound>, and <Compound>2a):ursolic acid</Compound>, (3 mg) after washing with petroleum ether.

The 60% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed using CH3CN:Et2O:CH2Cl2 (1:1:8, v/v).

Fractions from this column were combined and rechromatographed using CH3CN:Et2O:CH2Cl2 (1.5:1.5:7, v/v) to afford 6 (3 mg) after trituration with petroleum ether..

Silica gel chromatography of the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Alstonia scholaris</Synonym> yielded <Compound>squalene</Compound>, <Compound>chlorophyll a</Compound>, . The NMR spectra of <Compound>erythrodiol</Compound>, are in accordance with data reported in the literature for <Compound>erythrodiol</Compound> ; <Compound>uvaol</Compound>, for <Compound>uvaol</Compound> ; <Compound>betulin</Compound>, for <Compound>betulin</Compound> ; <Compound>oleanolic acid</Compound>, for <Compound>oleanolic acid</Compound> ; <Compound>2a):ursolic acid</Compound>, for <Compound>ursolic acid</Compound> ; 3a for <Compound>beta-amyrin acetate</Compound> ; <Compound>3a):alpha-amyrin acetate</Compound>, for <Compound>alpha-amyrin acetate</Compound> ; <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, for <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> ; <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, for <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound> ; <Compound>squalene</Compound>, for <Compound>squalene</Compound> ; 6 for <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3betaglucopyranoside-6'-O-fatty acid</Compound> esters ; and <Compound>chlorophyll a</Compound>, for <Compound>chlorophyll a</Compound>

The 1:1:1 ratio of the mixture of :: was deduced from the integrations and intensities of the 1H NMR resonances for the olefinic protons of <Compound>erythrodiol</Compound>, at <Compound>squalene</Compound>, 17 (t, J = 3. Hz, H-12) , <Compound>uvaol</Compound>, at <Compound>squalene</Compound>, 12 (t, J = 3. Hz, H-12) , and <Compound>betulin</Compound>, at 4.66 (br d, J = 2 Hz, Ha-29) and 4.56 (br s, Hb-29).

The 2:1 ratio of the mixture of <Compound>oleanolic acid</Compound> (<Compound>2a):ursolic acid</Compound> was deduced from the integrations and intensities of the 1H NMR resonances for the olefinic protons of <Compound>oleanolic acid</Compound>, at <Compound>squalene</Compound>, 27 (t, J = 3. Hz, H-3) and <Compound>2a):ursolic acid</Compound>, at <Compound>squalene</Compound>, 24 (t, J = 3. Hz, H-3).

The 1:4 ratio of the mixture of <Compound>beta-amyrin acetate</Compound> (<Compound>3a):alpha-amyrin acetate</Compound> was deduced from the integrations and intensities of the 1H NMR resonances for the olefinic protons of 3a at <Compound>squalene</Compound>, 15 (t, J = 3. Hz, H-3) and <Compound>3a):alpha-amyrin acetate</Compound>, at <Compound>squalene</Compound>, 10 (t, J = 3. Hz, H3).

The presence of the acetate functional groups was deduced from the appearance of methyl singlets at 2.02 and 2.

03.

The integrations of the 1H NMR resonances for the olefinic protons of <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, at <Compound>squalene</Compound>, 33 (brd, J = <Compound>squalene</Compound>, Hz, H-6) and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, at <Compound>squalene</Compound>, 33 (brd, J = <Compound>squalene</Compound>, Hz, H-6), <Compound>squalene</Compound>, 13 (dd, J = 8.4, 15.

Hz, H-22) and <Compound>squalene</Compound>, 00 (dd, J = 8.8, 15.

Hz, H-23) suggested that the ratio of <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, is about 3:2..

A research grant from the Science Foundation through the University Research Coordination Office of De La Salle University is gratefully acknowledged.