www.ijcpr.comAvailable online on International Journal of Current Pharmaceutical Review and Research; 7; 223-224 ISSN: 0976 822X Research Article *Author for Correspondence Chemical Constituents of <Synonym>Dioscorea luzonensis</Synonym> Schauer Consolacion Y Ragasa <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, , Julian D Guardamano <Compound>ursolic acid</Compound>, Maria Carmen S Tan1, Roque A Ulep, Ian A van Altena 1Chemistry Department, De La Salle University, 2401 <Location>Taft Avenue</Location>, <Location>Manila</Location> 1004, <Location>Philippines</Location>.

Chemistry Department, De La Salle University Science & Technology Complex Leandro V. Locsin Campus, <Location>Binan City</Location>, <Location>Laguna</Location> 4024, <Location>Philippines</Location>.

Physical Sciences Department, De La Salle University-Dasmarinas, <Location>Cavite</Location>, <Location>Philippines</Location>.

Chemistry Department, Mariano Marcos State University, <Location>Batac</Location>, <Location>Ilocos</Location> Norte.

School of Environmental and Life Sciences, Faculty of Science and Information Technology, Chemistry, The University of Newcastle-Australia, Callaghan, NSW, 2308, <Location>Australia</Location>.

Available Online:15th July, 2016.

Chemical investigation of the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> extracts of <Synonym>Dioscorea luzonensis</Synonym> Schauer tubers led to the isolation of long chain alkyl trans-ferulates , a mixture of 1 and <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> , and <Compound>fatty acids</Compound> from the skin; and <Compound>ursolic acid</Compound> and <Compound>fatty acids</Compound> from the inner portion.

The structures of <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>ursolic acid</Compound>, were identified by comparison of their NMR data with literature data.

Keywords: <Synonym>Dioscorea luzonensis</Synonym>, <Family>Dioscoreaceae</Family>, alkyl trans-ferulates, <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>ursolic acid, fatty acids</Compound>..

<Synonym>Dioscorea luzonensis</Synonym>, also known as <MedicinalPlant>wild yam</MedicinalPlant> or <MedicinalPlant>camangeg</MedicinalPlant>, is a plant endemic to The <Location>Philippines</Location>.

<Synonym>Dioscorea luzonensis</Synonym> is a wild <PlantPart>root</PlantPart> crop that grows naturally in <Location>Ilocos</Location> province of The <Location>Philippines</Location>.

The tubers of this plant are usually harvested during the early part of August and these are used as a vegetable and in making delicacies such as haleya.

The tuber has a unique brown color with fine <PlantPart>roots</PlantPart> on its surface and an elongated and irregular morphology.

The tuber can also be eaten after 20 to 30 minutes <Preparation>boiling</Preparation> and has a unique taste and aroma.

The skin of the tuber is usually considered to be inedible and it is removed when it is used as a food supplement.

The inner portion of the tuber is the edible portion with uniform white color.

<Synonym>Dioscorea luzonensis</Synonym> has no reported biological activities and chemical constituents.

However, congeners of <Synonym>Dioscorea luzonensis</Synonym> have been studied for their chemical constituents.

<Synonym>Dioscorea bulbifera</Synonym> yielded <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, mono-arachidin, <Compound>1,7-bis-(4-hydroxyphenyl)-1E,4E,6Eheptatrien-3-one</Compound>, <Compound>behenic acid</Compound>, <Compound>demethyl</Compound> batatasin IV, <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, 3'-di-hydroxy-4',5'-dimethoxybibenzyl, diosbulbins B, and D, <Compound>docosyl ferulate</Compound>, <Compound>7-bis-(4-hydroxyphenyl</Compound>)-4E, <Compound>6Eheptadien-3-one</Compound>, <Compound>53, 4-trihydroxy-3,7-dimethoxy</Compound> <ChemicalClass>flavone</ChemicalClass>, tristin, <Compound>protocatechuic acid</Compound>, and <Compound>adenosine</Compound>.

Another study reported the isolation of <Compound>palmitic acid</Compound>, -sitosterol, <Compound>oleic acid</Compound>, -sitosterol acetate, <Compound>5-(hydroxymethyl</Compound>) furfural, <Compound>nonanedioic acid</Compound>, -daucosterol, cyclo-(Phe-Tyr), cyclo(Tyr-Tyr), <Compound>6-methyl</Compound> citrate, <Compound>1,5-dimethyl</Compound> citrate, <Compound>trimethyl</Compound> citrate from <Location>Dioscorea</Location> opposite.

Furthermore, another species, <Synonym>Dioscorea collettii</Synonym> var hyplauca, afforded <Compound>tricosanatine</Compound>, <Compound>1,7-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)-4,6-heptadien-3one</Compound>, <Compound>1,7-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)-1,4,6-heptatrien-3-one</Compound>, and dioscin, <Compound>dioscorone A</Compound>, <Compound>3S-6,8-dihydroxy-3-phenyl,4-dihydroisocoumarin</Compound>, <Compound>diosgenin</Compound>, <Compound>gracillin</Compound>, <Compound>3-O-alpha-Lrhamnopyranosyl-(12, -beta-D-gucopyranoside-diosgenin</Compound>, protodioscin, methyl protodiscin, <Compound>protogracillin</Compound>, methyl <Compound>protogracillin</Compound>, <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>daucosterol</Compound>, and <Compound>palmitic acid</Compound>.

<Compound>Hydroxybenzoic acid</Compound>, <Compound>hydroxycinnamic acid</Compound> and their derivatives were found in extracts of <Synonym>Dioscorea hispida</Synonym> Dennst tuber.

Moreover, the phenolic compounds <Compound>cyanidin-3-glucoside</Compound> and the procyanidin dimers B-1 and B-3 were reported from <Synonym>Dioscorea alata</Synonym>.

We report herein the isolation of long chain alkyl trans-ferulates , a mixture of 1 and <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> , and <Compound>fatty acids</Compound> from the skin of the tuber; and <Compound>ursolic acid</Compound> and <Compound>fatty acids</Compound> from the inner portion of the tuber of <Synonym>Dioscorea luzonensis</Synonym>.

The structures of <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>ursolic acid</Compound>, are presented in Fig..

To the best of our knowledge this is the first report on the chemical constituents of <Synonym>Dioscorea luzonensis</Synonym>.

MATERIALS AND METHODS General Experimental Procedure 1H NMR spectra were recorded inCDCl on a Bruker Avance 400 in CDCl at 400.

Column chromatography was performed with silica gel 60 (70-230 mesh).

Thin layer chromatography was performed with plastic backed plates coated with silica gel F254 and the plates were visualized by spraying with <Compound>vanillin</Compound>/H2SO4 solution followed by warming.

General Isolation Procedure A glass column 18 inches in height and 1.0 inch internal diameter was packed with silica gel.

The crude extracts were fractionated by silica gel chromatography using increasing proportions of <Compound>acetone</Compound> in <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> Consolacion et al. / Chemical Constituents of IJCPR, Volume 7, Issue 4, JulyAugust 2016 Page 224 (10% increment) as eluents.

Twenty milliliter fractions were collected.

All fractions were monitored by thin layer chromatography.

Fractions with spots of the same Rf value were combined and rechromatographed in appropriate solvent systems until TLC pure isolates were obtained.

A glass column 12 inches in height and 0.5 inch internal diameter was used for the rechromatography.

Five milliliter fractions were collected.

Final purifications were conducted using Pasteur pipettes as columns.

One milliliter fractions were collected.

Plant Material The tubers were bought from <Location>Batac</Location> Public Market in <Location>Batac</Location>, <Location>Ilocos</Location> Norte, <Location>Philippines</Location> in November 2014.

The sample was authenticated by Flordeliz Rapacon Estira of Mariano Marcos State University, <Location>Batac</Location>, <Location>Ilocos</Location> Norte, <Location>Philippines</Location>.

Isolation of the Chemical Constituents of the Skin of the Tuber The freeze-dried skin of the tuber (66.27 g) of <Synonym>Dioscorea luzonensis</Synonym> was <Illness>cut</Illness> into small pieces, <Preparation>ground</Preparation> in a blender, soaked in CH2Cl2 for <Compound>ursolic acid</Compound>, days and then <Preparation>filtered</Preparation>.

The solvent was evaporated from the filtrate under vacuum to afford a crude <Preparation>extract</Preparation> (0.6 g) which was chromatographed using increasing proportions of <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 at 10% increments by volume as eluents.

The 10% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed <Compound>ursolic acid</Compound>, ) using <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, 5% EtOAc in petroleum ether to afford 1 <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, mg).

The 20% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, ) using 7.5% EtOAc in petroleum ether to yield a mixture of 1 and <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>ursolic acid</Compound>, mg).

The 30% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed <Compound>ursolic acid</Compound>, ) using 15% EtOAc in petroleum ether to <Compound>afford fatty acids</Compound> (5 mg).

Isolation of the Chemical Constituents of the Inner Portion of the Tuber The freeze-dried inedible part of the tuber (301.96 g) of <Synonym>Dioscorea luzonensis</Synonym> were <Illness>cut</Illness> into about 1 cm, <Preparation>ground</Preparation> in an osterizer, soaked in CH2Cl2 for <Compound>ursolic acid</Compound>, days and then <Preparation>filtered</Preparation>.

The solvent was evaporated under vacuum to afford a crude <Preparation>extract</Preparation> (1.02 g), which was chromatographed using increasing proportions of <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 at 10% increments by volume as eluents.

The 40% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, ) using 20% EtOAc in petroleum ether to <Compound>afford fatty acids</Compound> (4 mg).

The 50% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed <Compound>ursolic acid</Compound>, ) using CH3CN:Et2O:CH2Cl2 (0.5:0.5:9, v/v) to yield 4 <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, mg) after washing with petroleum ether..

Silica gel chromatography of the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> extracts of <Synonym>Dioscorea luzonensis</Synonym> yielded compounds <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>ursolic acid</Compound>, and <Compound>fatty acids</Compound>.

The structures of <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound>, <Compound>ursolic acid</Compound>, and <Compound>fatty acids</Compound> were identified by comparison of their NMR data with literature data.

The NMR spectra are in accordance with data reported in the literature for alkyl trans-ferulates 7; <Compound>beta-sitosterol</Compound> 8, and <Compound>ursolic acid</Compound> 9.

<Compound>The fatty acid</Compound> fraction was determined to contain both saturated and <Compound>unsaturated fatty acids</Compound>.

ACKNOWLEGEMENTS A research grant from the De La Salle University Science Foundation through the University Research Coordination Office is gratefully acknowledged.