ISSN: 0975-8585 March - April 2015 RJPBCS 6 Page No.

Research Journal of Pharmaceutical, Biological and Chemical Sciences A <ChemicalClass>Flavone</ChemicalClass> from <Synonym>Eucalyptus deglupta</Synonym>.

Consolacion Y. Ragasa,2*, Virgilio D. Ebajo Jr. , Mariquit M. De Los Reyes,4, and Chien-Chang Shen <Compound>5-hydroxy-7,4'-dimethoxy-6,8-dimethylflavone</Compound>, Chemistry Department, De La Salle University Science & Technology Complex Leandro V. Locsin Campus, <Location>Binan City</Location>, <Location>Laguna</Location> 4024, <Location>Philippines</Location>.

Chemistry Department, De La Salle University, 2401 <Location>Taft Avenue</Location>, <Location>Manila</Location> 1004, <Location>Philippines</Location>.

Biology Department, De La Salle University Science & Technology Complex Leandro V. Locsin Campus, <Location>Binan City</Location>, <Location>Laguna</Location> 4024, <Location>Philippines</Location>.

Biology Department, De La Salle University, 2401 <Location>Taft Avenue</Location>, <Location>Manila</Location> 1004, <Location>Philippines</Location>.

National Research Institute of Chinese Medicine, 155-1, Li-Nong St., <Location>Sec</Location>. , <Location>Taipei</Location> 112, <Location>Taiwan</Location>..

Chemical investigations of the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of the <PlantPart>twigs</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Eucalyptus deglupta</Synonym> (Blume) led to the isolation of <Compound>5-hydroxy-7,4'-dimethoxy-6,8-dimethylflavone</Compound> .

The structure of <Compound>5-hydroxy-7,4'-dimethoxy-6,8-dimethylflavone</Compound>, was elucidated by extensive 1D and 2D NMR spectroscopy.

Keywords: <Synonym>Eucalyptus deglupta</Synonym>, <Family>Myrtaceae</Family>, <Compound>5-hydroxy-7,4'-dimethoxy-6,8-dimethylflavone</Compound> *Corresponding author ISSN: 0975-8585 March - April 2015 RJPBCS 6 Page No..

<Synonym>Eucalyptus deglupta</Synonym> (Blume) of the family <Family>Myrtaceae</Family>, commonly known as <MedicinalPlant>Mindanao gum</MedicinalPlant> or <MedicinalPlant>rainbow eucalyptus</MedicinalPlant>, is native to the <Location>Philippines</Location> and other western <Location>Pacific</Location> islands, adapting well in lowland humid tropical conditions and reaching up to 100 ft in height.

<Synonym>Eucalyptus deglupta</Synonym> is cultivated throughout the world as an ornamental tree, noted for its spectrum of colors developed by the peeling of its smooth <PlantPart>bark</PlantPart> in a fatigueinspired pattern, revealing multi-colored streaks of yellow, red, blue, orange, green, purple, brown, and gray shades <Compound>5-hydroxy-7,4'-dimethoxy-6,8-dimethylflavone</Compound>, 2]. The genus Eucalyptus has been a traditional source of timber, cellulose-related products and essential oils from the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> [3, 4]. An antihypertensive food and food additive containing an <Preparation>extract</Preparation> prepared from eucalyptus plants was reported.

Essential oils from the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Eucalyptus deglupta</Synonym> and other related aromatic plants were reported to inhibit the growth of <Synonym>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</Synonym>.

<Synonym>Eucalyptus deglupta</Synonym> was reported to exhibit a high percentage of <Compound>xanthine</Compound> oxidase inhibition (IC50 of 44.5 g/mL) and also prevented cataract development in streptozotocin diabetic rats.

A review on the chemical constituents and biological activities of the genus Eucalyptus has been provided.

More than two hundred nonvolatile compounds from this genus have been characterized for their chemical structures and biological activities.

<Compound>Phloroglucinol</Compound> derivatives from Eucalyptus have growth regulatory, antigranulation, antiinflammatory and <BioAct>antimalarial</BioAct> activities, while rutin and other <ChemicalClass>flavonoids</ChemicalClass>, terpenoids and tannins from Eucalyptus are of great pharmaceutical importance.

The essential oils from the dried <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of five species of the genus Eucalyptus (<Synonym>Eucalyptus camaldulensis</Synonym>, <Synonym>Eucalyptus deglupta</Synonym>, <Synonym>Eucalyptus grandis</Synonym>, <Synonym>Eucalyptus torelliana</Synonym>, <Synonym>Eucalyptus urophylla</Synonym>) were found to contain as major components the following <ChemicalClass>terpenes</ChemicalClass>: <Compound>alpha-pinene</Compound>, <Compound>beta-pinene</Compound>, <Compound>alpha-phellandrene</Compound>, <Compound>limonene</Compound>, <Compound>gamma-terpinene</Compound>, <Compound>p-cymene</Compound> and <Compound>beta-caryophyllene</Compound>.

Another study reported that the steam-volatile portion of <Synonym>Eucalyptus deglupta</Synonym> yielded 40% <ChemicalClass>terpene</ChemicalClass> fraction which contained ()-<Compound>alpha-pinene</Compound>, (-)-<Compound>alpha-phellandrene</Compound>, <Compound>p-cymene</Compound>, <Compound>ocimene</Compound>, isovaleraldehyde, (-)-carvotanacetone, and (+) -nerolidol.

Moreover, the <PlantPart>leaf</PlantPart> essential oil of <Synonym>Eucalyptus deglupta</Synonym> is mainly composed of sesquiterpenoids (48%), of which <Compound>E-nerolidol</Compound> was the major component (34.8%).

Another study reported the isolation of <Compound>tritriacontane-16,18-dione</Compound>, <Compound>8-methoxyellagic acid</Compound>-2rhamnoside, <Compound>ellagic acid</Compound>, and ellagitannins from the extracts of the wood and <PlantPart>bark</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Eucalyptus deglupta</Synonym>.

The extracts also afforded a low molecular weight Si containing compound which is effective in inhibiting HIV-1 virus.

The Si containing substance is manufactured by hot water extraction of <Synonym>Eucalyptus deglupta</Synonym> followed by gel filtration.

The isolation of <Compound>ursolic acid</Compound>, <Compound>oleanolic acid</Compound>, and <Compound>squalene</Compound> from the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> and <PlantPart>twigs</PlantPart> and <Compound>nerolidol</Compound> from the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Eucalyptus deglupta</Synonym> have been reported.

We report herein the isolation and structure elucidation of <Compound>5-hydroxy-7,4'-dimethoxy-6,8dimethylflavone</Compound> from the <PlantPart>twigs</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Eucalyptus deglupta</Synonym>.

To the best of our knowledge this is the first report on the isolation of <Compound>5-hydroxy-7,4'-dimethoxy-6,8-dimethylflavone</Compound>, from <Synonym>Eucalyptus deglupta</Synonym>.

O OCH3 CH3 H3CO H3C OH O <Compound>5-hydroxy-7,4'-dimethoxy-6,8-dimethylflavone</Compound>, 1 45 27 9 10 1' 4' 2' 6' MATERIALS AND METHODS General Experimental Procedure NMR spectra were recorded on a Varian VNMRS spectrometer in CDCl at 600 MHz for <Compound>5-hydroxy-7,4'-dimethoxy-6,8-dimethylflavone</Compound>, H NMR and 150 MHz for 13 C NMR spectra.

Column chromatography was performed with silica gel 60 (70-230 mesh).

Thin layer chromatography was performed with plastic backed plates coated with silica gel F254 and the plates were visualized by spraying with <Compound>vanillin</Compound>/H2SO4 solution followed by warming.

ISSN: 0975-8585 March - April 2015 RJPBCS 6 Page No.

Sample Collection Samples of <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> and <PlantPart>twigs</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Eucalyptus deglupta</Synonym> (Blume) were a generous gift collected from the Center for <Compound>Ecozoic</Compound> Living and Learning (CELL), <Location>Silang</Location>, <Location>Cavite</Location> in May 2014.

The samples were authenticated at the Botany Division of the National Museum, <Location>Manila</Location>, <Location>Philippines</Location> and deposited with voucher # 268-2014.

General Isolation Procedure A glass column 20 inches in height and 2.0 inches internal diameter was packed with silica gel.

The crude <Preparation>extract</Preparation> from the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> were fractionated by silica gel chromatography using increasing proportions of <Compound>acetone</Compound> in <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> (10% increment) as eluents.

One hundred milliliter fractions were collected.

All fractions were monitored by thin layer chromatography.

Fractions with spots of the same Rf values were combined and rechromatographed in appropriate solvent systems until TLC pure isolates were obtained.

A glass column 12 inches in height and 0.5 inch internal diameter was used for the rechromatography.

Five milliliter fractions were collected.

Final purifications were conducted using Pasteur pipettes as columns.

One milliliter fractions were collected.

Isolation The air-dried <PlantPart>twigs</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Eucalyptus deglupta</Synonym> (173 g) were <Preparation>ground</Preparation> in a blender, soaked in CH2Cl2 for 3 days and then <Preparation>filtered</Preparation>.

The solvent was evaporated under vacuum to afford a crude <Preparation>extract</Preparation> (18 g) which was chromatographed using increasing proportions of <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 at 10% increment.

The 30% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed (3 ) in 20% EtOAc in petroleum ether to afford <Compound>5-hydroxy-7,4'-dimethoxy-6,8-dimethylflavone</Compound>, (7 mg) after washing with petroleum ether, followed by Et2O.

<Compound>5-Hydroxy-7,4'-dimethoxy-6,8-dimethylflavone</Compound> : Yellowish solid.

H NMR (600 MHz, CDCl): 6.61 (1H, s, H-3), 12.89 (1H, 5-OH), 2.20 (3H, s, Me-6), 3.78 (3H, s, 7-OMe), 2.38 (3H, s, Me-8), 7.86 (2H, d, J = 9 Hz, H-2', H6'), 7.02 (2H, d, J = 9 Hz, H-3', H-5'), 3.88 (3H, s, 4'-OMe); 13 C NMR (150 MHz, CDCl): 163.88 (C-2), 104.09 (C3), 183.27 (C-4), 157.29 (C-5), 114.10 (C-6), 162.58 (C-7), 108.78 (C-8), 153.00 (C-9), 107.40 (C-10), 123.90 (<CellLine>C1</CellLine>'), 128.00 (C-2', C-6'), 114.56 (C-3', C-5'), 162.58 (C-4'), 8.27 (Me-6), 60.51 (7-OMe), 8.57 (Me-8), 55.53 (4'OMe)..

Silica gel chromatography of the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of the <PlantPart>twigs</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Eucalyptus deglupta</Synonym> (Blume) led to the isolation of <Compound>5-hydroxy-7,4'-dimethoxy-6,8-dimethylflavone</Compound> .

The structure of <Compound>5-hydroxy-7,4'-dimethoxy-6,8-dimethylflavone</Compound>, was elucidated by extensive 1D and 2D NMR spectroscopy as follows.

The <Compound>5-hydroxy-7,4'-dimethoxy-6,8-dimethylflavone</Compound>, H NMR spectrum of <Compound>5-hydroxy-7,4'-dimethoxy-6,8-dimethylflavone</Compound>, indicated resonances for two aromatic methyl singlets at 2.20 and 2.38; <Compound>methoxy</Compound> groups at 3.78 and 3.88; a deshielded olefinic proton singlet at 6.61; aromatic proton doublets at 7.02 (2H) and 7.86 (2H) othro coupled to each other by 9 Hz which was confirmed by COSY; and a chelated OH at 12.

89.

The 13 C NMR spectrum of <Compound>5-hydroxy-7,4'-dimethoxy-6,8-dimethylflavone</Compound>, gave resonances for a conjugated <Compound>carbonyl</Compound> carbon at 183.27; oxygenated aromatic carbons at 163.88, 162.58 (2C), 157.29 and 153.00; protonated aromatic carbons at 128.00 (2C), 114.56 (2C) and 104.09; four non-protonated aromatic carbons at 123,9, 114.10, 108.78 and 107.40; <Compound>methoxy</Compound> carbons at 60.51 and 55.53; and methyl carbons at 8.57 and 8.

27.

These resonances indicated a <ChemicalClass>flavone</ChemicalClass> with a hydroxyl, two <Compound>methoxy</Compound> and two methyl subtituents.

The protons attached to carbon atoms were assigned from HSQC 2D NMR data (see experimental), and the structure of <Compound>5-hydroxy-7,4'-dimethoxy-6,8-dimethylflavone</Compound>, was elucidated by analysis of the HMBC 2D NMR data.

Key HMBC correlations are shown in Fig..

The ortho coupled protons could only be in ring C of the <ChemicalClass>flavone</ChemicalClass> skeleton at C-2', C-3', C-5' and C-6', while the chelated hydroxyl could only be attached to C-5. One of the <Compound>methoxy</Compound> groups was attached to C4' on the basis of long-range correlations between this <Compound>methoxy</Compound>, the ortho aromatic protons and C-4'. The position of the hydroxyl proton was confirmed by correlations with C-5, C-6 and C-10.

One of the methyl groups was attached to C-6 due to long-range correlations between this methyl and C-6, C-5 and C-7. The second <Compound>methoxy</Compound> group was attached to C-7 based on long-range correlations between this <Compound>methoxy</Compound> and C-7. The second methyl group was attached to C-8 since long-range correlations were observed between this ISSN: 0975-8585 March - April 2015 RJPBCS 6 Page No. methyl and C-8, C-7 and C-9. The <Compound>carbonyl</Compound> was assigned to C-4 on the basis of long-range correlations between the H-3 olefinic proton singlet and this carbon.

All long-range correlations observed were consistent with the structure of <Compound>5-hydroxy-7,4'-dimethoxy-6,8-dimethylflavone</Compound>, The structure of <Compound>5-hydroxy-7,4'-dimethoxy-6,8-dimethylflavone</Compound>, was confirmed by positive ESI-MS which gave an [M+H] + = 327.18 corresponding to the molecular formula of C19H19O5.

O OCH3 CH3 H3CO H3C OH O Figure 1: HMBC correlations of <Compound>5-hydroxy-7,4'-dimethoxy-6,8-dimethylflavone</Compound>, The positions of the methyl and <Compound>methoxy</Compound> groups were confirmed by NOESY spectrum (Fig. ). One of the <Compound>methoxy</Compound> groups was close in space to two methyl groups in ring A. The olefinic proton singlet in ring C was close to the more deshielded aromatic proton doublet in ring B, which was in turn close to the relatively more shielded aromatic proton doublet, which was finally close to the second <Compound>methoxy</Compound> group.

These confirm the positions of the methyl and <Compound>methoxy</Compound> groups in <Compound>5-hydroxy-7,4'-dimethoxy-6,8-dimethylflavone</Compound>, O OCH3 CH3 H3CO H3C OH O Figure 2: NOESY correlations of <Compound>5-hydroxy-7,4'-dimethoxy-6,8-dimethylflavone</Compound>, Literature search revealed that <Compound>5-hydroxy-7,4'-dimethoxy-6,8-dimethylflavone</Compound> has been previously isolated from the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Callistemon lanceolatus</Synonym>.

The structure of this compound was determined by MS and 13 C NMR spectroscopy.

However, the 13 C NMR resonances in the literature do not match with our 13 C NMR data and assignments which were based on extensive 1D ( <Compound>5-hydroxy-7,4'-dimethoxy-6,8-dimethylflavone</Compound>, H and 13 C) and 2D (COSY, HSQC, HMBC and NOESY) NMR spectroscopy..

A research grant from the De La Salle University Science Foundation through the University Research Coordination Office is gratefully acknowledged.