www.scholarsresearchlibrary.comt Available online a Scholars Research Library Der Pharmacia Lettre, 2016, 8 (20):188-190 (http://scholarsresearchlibrary.com/archive.html) ISSN 0975-5071 <Location>USA CODEN</Location>: DPLEB 188 Scholar Research Library Xanthones from <Synonym>Garcinia mangostana</Synonym> Linn.

Pulp Consolacion Y Ragasa,2,*, Theresa Joyce <Compound>Tabin</Compound>, Jo <Compound>Madeleine</Compound> Ann Reyes, Maria Carmen S. Tan1 and Chien-Chang Shen 1Chemistry Department, De La Salle University, 2401 <Location>Taft Avenue</Location>, <Location>Manila</Location> 1004, <Location>Philippines</Location>.

Chemistry Department, De La Salle University Science & Technology Complex Leandro V. Locsin Campus, <Location>Binan City</Location>, <Location>Laguna</Location> 4024, <Location>Philippines</Location>.

National Research Institute of Chinese Medicine, Ministry of Health and Welfare, 155-1, <Location>LiNong St.</Location>, <Location>Sec</Location>. , <Location>Taipei</Location>, <Location>Taiwan</Location>..

. In an earlier study, we isolated alpha-mangostin as the major <Compound>xanthone</Compound> and 3-isomangostin as a minor constituent of the pulp of the ripe <PlantPart>fruit</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Garcinia mangostana</Synonym> Linn.

Further study on the pulp has led to the isolation of <Compound>garcinone D</Compound>.

The structure of <Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>, was elucidated by extensive 1D and 2D NMR spectroscopy.

<Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>as reported to exhibit <BioAct>anticancer</BioAct> property.

Keywords: <Synonym>Garcinia mangostana</Synonym>, Guttiferae, <Compound>garcinone D</Compound>

. <Synonym>Garcinia mangostana</Synonym> Linn., the queen of <PlantPart>fruits</PlantPart> and commonly known as <MedicinalPlant>mangosteen</MedicinalPlant>, is a natural source of xanthones which are antioxidants, <BioAct>anti-inflammatory</BioAct> [<Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>, ], <BioAct>antifungal</BioAct> , and are also used for chemoprevention.

Extracts and xanthones isolated from <Synonym>Garcinia mangostana</Synonym> have <BioAct>antioxidant</BioAct>, antitumor, anti-allergic, antiinflammatory, <BioAct>antibacterial</BioAct>, <BioAct>antifungal</BioAct>, and <BioAct>antiviral</BioAct> properties.

Consolacion Y Ragasa et al Der Pharmacia Lettre, 2016, 8 (20):188-190.

189 Scholar Research Library We earlier reported the isolation of alpha-mangostin, <Compound>gartanin</Compound> and 3-isomangostin from the pericarp of <Synonym>Garcinia mangostin</Synonym>.

Recently, we reported the isolation of -tocotrienol, alpha-mangostin, 3-isomangostin, <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, <Compound>betasitosteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-O-fatty acid</Compound> esters, and <Compound>stigmasteryl-3beta-glucopyranoside-6'-O-fatty acid</Compound> esters from the pulp; and <Compound>stigmasterol</Compound>, <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, and <Compound>linoleic acid</Compound> from the <PlantPart>seeds</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Garcinia mangostana</Synonym>.

This study reports on the isolation of <Compound>garcinone D</Compound> from the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of the pulp of the freeze-dried ripe <PlantPart>fruit</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Garcinia mangostana</Synonym>.

MATERIALS AND METHODS General Experimental Procedure NMR spectra were recorded on a Varian VNMRS spectrometer in CDCl at 600 MHz for 1H NMR and 150 MHz for 13C NMR spectra.

Column chromatography was performed, with silica gel 60 (70-230 mesh).

Thin layer chromatography, was performed with plastic backed plates coated with silica gel F254 and the plates were visualized by spraying with <Compound>vanillin</Compound>/H2SO4 solution followed by warming.

Sample Collection <Synonym>Garcinia mangostana</Synonym> Linn <PlantPart>fruit</PlantPart> was collected from <Location>Davao</Location>, <Location>Philippines</Location> in October 2015.

The <PlantPart>fruit</PlantPart> was authenticated at the Botany Division, Philippine National Museum.

General Isolation Procedure A glass column 18 inches in height and <Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>, inch internal diameter was used for the fractionation of the crude extracts.

Eleven 20 mL fractions were collected.

A glass column 12 inches in height and 0.5 inch internal diameter was used for the rechromatography of fractions from the crude extracts. mL fractions were collected.

Fractions with spots of the same Rf values were combined and rechromatographed in appropriate solvent systems until TLC pure isolates were obtained.

Rechromatography and final purifications were conducted using Pasteur pipettes as columns. mL fractions were collected.

Isolation of <Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>he freeze-dried pulp (143.3 g) of <Synonym>Garcinia mangostana</Synonym> was <Preparation>ground</Preparation> in a blender, soaked in CH2Cl2 for three days and then <Preparation>filtered</Preparation>.

The filtrate was concentrated under vacuum to afford a crude <Preparation>extract</Preparation> <Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>, 96 g) which was chromatographed by gradient elution with CH2Cl2, followed by increasing amounts of <Compound>acetone</Compound> at 10% increment by volume as eluents.

The 60% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed (4 ) using CH3CN:Et2O:CH2Cl2 (2:2:6, v/v) to afford <Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>, (3 mg) after trituration with petroleum ether.

<Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>: 1H NMR (600 MHz, CDCl): 6.27 (s, H-4), 6.81 (s, H-5), 3.41 (m, H2-1'), 5.26 (m, H-2'), <Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>, 82 (s, H3-4'), <Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>, 75 (s, H3-5'), 3.41 (m, H2-1''), <Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>, 78 (m, H2-2''), <Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>, 31 (s, H3-4''), <Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>, 31 (s, H3-5''), 13.62 (1-OH); 13C NMR (150 MHz, CDCl): 160.55 (C-1), 108.69 (C-2), 161.82 (C-3), 93.33 (C-4), 155.06 (C-4a), 156.00 (C-4b), 101.64 (C-5), 154.69 (C-6), 142.54 (C-7), 138.48 (C-8), 112.00 (C-8a), 182.01 (C-9), 103.57 (C-9a), 21.17 (C-1'), 121.44 (C-2'), 135.66 (C-3'), 17.92 (C-4'), 25.84 (C-5'), 22.17 (C-1''), 44.40 (C-2''), 70.79 (C-3''), 29.25 (C-4''), 29.25 (C-5'')..

Silica gel chromatography of the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of the freeze-dried pulp of the ripe <PlantPart>fruit</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Garcinia mangostana</Synonym> has led to the isolation of <Compound>garcinone D</Compound>.

The structure of <Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>, was elucidated by extensive 1D and 2D NMR spectroscopy.

Compound <Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>, indicated similar 1H NMR resonances to alpha-mangostin.

The differences were the non-appearance of the benzylic <Compound>methylene</Compound> protons of the <Compound>prenyl</Compound> group attached to ring B at 4.07 (H2-1'') in alphamangostin and the appearance of more overlapping benzylic <Compound>methylene</Compound> protons at 3.41 in <Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>, Furthermore, the vinylic proton at 5.26 (H-2'') in alpha-mangostin was replaced by <Compound>methylene</Compound> protons at <Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>, 78 in <Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>, The allylic methyl groups at <Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>, 67 (H3-4'') and <Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>, 82 (H3-5'') in alpha-mangostin were replaced by two overlapping methyl singlets at <Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>, 31 in <Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>, These relatively deshielded methyl singlets suggested that they were bonded to a hydroxylated quaternary carbon.

The change from a <Compound>prenyl</Compound> group with a double bond attached to ring B of alpha-mangostin to a hydroxylated <Compound>prenyl</Compound> group in <Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>, was supported by the 13C NMR spectrum of <Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>, The benzylic <Compound>methylene</Compound> carbon of the <Compound>prenyl</Compound> group attached to ring B of alpha-mangostin at 26.6 (C-1'') was shielded to 21.4 in <Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>, Moreover, the vinylic carbons at 123.5 (C-2'') and 132.2 (C-3'') in alpha-mangostin were shielded to 44.4 and 70.8, respectively in <Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>, The 1H and 13C NMR assignments of <Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>, in CDCl are given (see experimental).

The protons bonded to carbons were deduced from HSQC.

The structure of <Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>, was further supported by isolated spin systems from COSY and long-range correlations Consolacion Y Ragasa et al Der Pharmacia Lettre, 2016, 8 (20):188-190.

190 Scholar Research Library deduced from HMBC.

Previous literature reported the 1H and 13C NMR data of <Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>, in acetone-d6 , DMSO-d6 , and CD3OD.

However, to the best of our knowledge this is the first report on the 1H and 13C NMR data of <Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>, in CDCl.

<Compound>Garcinone D</Compound> exhibited cytotoxicity against the <CellLine>HT-29</CellLine> cell line with an ED50 value of 2. M and in an ELISA NF-B assay, <Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>, inhibited p65 activation with an IC50 value of 3. M.

<Compound>Garcinone D</Compound> showed significant activity against <CellLine>CEM-SS</CellLine> cell line with an IC50 value of 3.2 g/mL.

<Compound>Garcinone D</Compound> was found to possess inhibitory activity using a cell free, enzyme-based microsomal aromatase inhibition assay.

Furthermore, SKBR <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> cancer cells which are known to <Preparation>express</Preparation> high levels of aromatase were found to be inhibited by <Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>,

<Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>isolated from the young <PlantPart>fruit</PlantPart> (7 weeks maturity) of <Synonym>Garcinia mangostana</Synonym> was also shown to exhibit cytotoxicity against epidermal carcinoma of the <BodyPart>mouth</BodyPart> (<CellLine>KB</CellLine>), <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> cancer (BC-1), and small cell lung cancer (<CellLine>NCI-H187</CellLine>) with IC50 values of 3.56, 2.81 and 11.04 g/mL, respectively.

Another study reported that <Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>, exhibited cytotoxicity to human nasopharyngeal carcinoma cell lines: CNE1 (IC50 = 16.

M), CNE2 (IC50 = 9. M), SUNE (IC50 = 24.

M) and HONE (IC50 = 16.

M); human lung cancer cell lines: <CellLine>A549</CellLine> (IC50 = 20.

M) and GLC82 (IC50 = 16.

M); human <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> cancer cell line: <CellLine>MCF-7</CellLine> (IC50 = 19.

M); and human hepatic cancer cell line: Bel 7402 (IC50 = 16.

M) , Furthermore, <Compound>Garcinone D</Compound>, showed bacteria neuraminidase inhibitory activity with an IC50 value of 2. M.

. A research grant from the De La Salle University Science Foundation through the University Research Coordination Office is gratefully acknowledged.