www.scholarsresearchlibrary.comt Available online a Scholars Research Library Der Pharmacia Lettre, 2016, 8 (19):234-236 (http://scholarsresearchlibrary.com/archive.html) ISSN 0975-5071 <Location>USA CODEN</Location>: DPLEB 234 Scholar Research Library Chemical Constituents of <Synonym>Duranta erecta</Synonym> L. <PlantPart>Flowers</PlantPart> Julius Leonard A. Vivar, Mariquit M. De Los Reyes, Chien-Chang Shen, and Consolacion Y. Ragasa <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, * 1Chemistry Department, De La Salle University, 2401 <Location>Taft Avenue</Location>, <Location>Manila</Location> 1004, <Location>Philippines</Location> 2Biology Department, De La Salle University, 2401 <Location>Taft Avenue</Location>, <Location>Manila</Location> 1004, <Location>Philippines</Location> 3National Research Institute of Chinese Medicine, Ministry of Health and Welfare, 155-1, <Location>LiNong St.</Location>, <Location>Sec</Location>. , <Location>Taipei</Location> 112, <Location>Taiwan</Location> 4Chemistry Department, De La Salle University Science & Technology Complex Leandro V. Locsin Campus, <Location>Binan City</Location>, <Location>Laguna</Location> 4024, <Location>Philippines</Location>.

. Chemical investigation of the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of the <PlantPart>flowers</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Duranta erecta</Synonym> L. has led to the isolation of <Compound>oleanolic acid</Compound> , a mixture of <Compound>alpha-amyrin</Compound> and <Compound>beta-amyrin</Compound> in a 3:1 ratio, <Compound>phytyl fatty acid esters</Compound> , and <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound> , The structures of 1-4b were identified by comparison of their NMR data with literature data.

Keywords: <Synonym>Duranta erecta</Synonym>, <Family>Verbenaceae</Family>, <Compound>oleanolic acid</Compound>, <Compound>phytyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, <Compound>alpha-amyrin</Compound>, <Compound>beta-amyrin</Compound>, <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>.

. <Synonym>Duranta erecta</Synonym> L. (syn <Synonym>Duranta repens</Synonym> L.) of the family <Family>Verbenaceae</Family> is an ornamental plant which originated fom <Location>South America</Location>.

In Chinese medicine, the <PlantPart>fruits</PlantPart> were used for treatment of malaria and the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> are employed for the treatment of abscesses.

The <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Duranta erecta</Synonym> yielded iridoid <Compound>glucosides</Compound>, <Compound>duranterectosides A</Compound>, <Compound>duranterectosides B</Compound>, <Compound>duranterectosides C</Compound>, and <Compound>duranterectosides D</Compound>, <Compound>durantosides I</Compound> and <Compound>durantosides II</Compound>, <Compound>lamiide</Compound>, <Compound>lamiidoside</Compound> and <Compound>verbascoside</Compound>.

<Compound>Duranterectoside A</Compound><Compound>durantosides I</Compound>, <Compound>durantosides II</Compound>, and <Compound>durantosides III</Compound>, and <Compound>lamiidoside</Compound> were also isolated from the <PlantPart>stems</PlantPart>.

The <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Duranta repens</Synonym> yielded <Compound>durantoside IV</Compound>, <Compound>durantoside V</Compound>, <Compound>oleanolic acid</Compound>, <Compound>ursolic acid</Compound>, (<Compound>E)-cinnamic acid</Compound>, <Compound>beta-sitosteryl-3-O-beta-D-glucopyranoside</Compound>, (<Compound>E)-p-methoxycinnamic acid</Compound>, <Compound>kusaginin</Compound>, glucose, <Compound>durantoside I</Compound>nd <Compound>durantoside II</Compound>

The chloroform <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of <PlantPart>stem</PlantPart> and ethanol <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of <PlantPart>fruits</PlantPart> exhibited potent antishigellosis activity and moderate activity against some pathogenic bacteria and fungi.

A mixture of <Compound>beta-amyrin</Compound> and <Compound>12-oleanene</Compound> 3beta, <Compound>21beta-diol</Compound> from these extracts showed mild to moderate <BioAct>antimicrobial</BioAct> ativity.

Phenylethanoid <Compound>glycoside acteoside</Compound>, the iridoid <Compound>lamiide</Compound> and the <Compound>saponin pseudo-ginsenoside</Compound>-RT1 were isolated from the <Compound>methanol</Compound> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of <Synonym>Duranta repens</Synonym>.

<Compound>Acteoside</Compound> showed an IC50 of <Compound>phytyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, 05 +/0.09 g/mL in the DPPH assay, while <Compound>lamiide</Compound> and pseudoginsenoside-RT1 were inactive.

The <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Duranta repens</Synonym> yielded <Compound>durantanin IV</Compound> and <Compound>durantanin V</Compound>, a bidesmosidic <Compound>saponin</Compound>, <Compound>oleanolic acid</Compound>, three phenylethanoids and five <ChemicalClass>flavonoids</ChemicalClass>.

Another study reported the isolation of the <ChemicalClass>flavonoids</ChemicalClass> <Compound>3,7,4'-trihydroxy-3'-(4-hydroxy-3-methylbutyl)-5,6-dimethoxyflavone</Compound>,,7-dihydroxy-3'(4-hydroxy-3-methylbuty l)-5,6,4'-trimetho <Compound>xyflavone</Compound> and <ChemicalClass>diterpenes</ChemicalClass> 6beta-hydrox<CellLine>y-1</CellLine>,-<Compound>epoxy-5beta,8beta,9beta,10alphacleroda-3,13(16),14-trien-18-oic acid</Compound> and 2beta-hydrox<CellLine>y-1</CellLine>,-<Compound>epoxy-5beta,8beta,9beta,10alpha-cleroda-3,13,14-trien-18-oic acid</Compound> from <Synonym>Duranta repens</Synonym>.

Furthermore, <Compound>24-ethylcholest-5-en-3-alpha-ol</Compound>, <Compound>naringenin</Compound>, <Compound>3,4-dihydroxy-beta-phenethyl</Compound>-O-alpha Consolacion Y. Ragasa et al Der Pharmacia Lettre, 2016, 8 (19):234-236.

235 Scholar Research Library <Compound>rhamnopyranosyl-4-O-caffeoyl-alpha-D-glucopyranosid</Compound>, <Compound>lamiide</Compound>, <Compound>alpha-glucopyranosyl</Compound>-alpha-fructopyrano side, and <Compound>alphagalactopyranosyl-alpha-glucopyranosyl-fructopyranoside</Compound> were isolated from the ethanol <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of <Synonym>Duranta repens</Synonym>.

The petroleum ether <Preparation>extract</Preparation> afforded a mixture of hydrocarbons ranging from C15 C27, fatty <Compound>acids methyl esters</Compound> and <Compound>fatty acids</Compound> with <Compound>palmitic acid</Compound> as the main component (46%).

Moreover, <Compound>trans-cinnamic acid</Compound> was isolated from the <Compound>methanol</Compound> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of the <PlantPart>fruits</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Duranta repens</Synonym>.

In this study, we report the isolation of <Compound>oleanolic acid</Compound> , a mixture of <Compound>alpha-amyrin</Compound> and <Compound>beta-amyrin</Compound> , <Compound>phytyl fatty acid esters</Compound> , and <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound> from the <PlantPart>flowers</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Duranta erecta</Synonym>.

The structures of 1-4 are presented in Fig..

Fig..

Chemical structures of <Compound>oleanolic acid</Compound> , <Compound>alpha-amyrin</Compound> and <Compound>beta-amyrin</Compound> , <Compound>phytyl fatty acid esters</Compound> , and <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound> from the <PlantPart>flowers</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Duranta erecta</Synonym> MATERIALS AND METHODS General Experimental Procedure NMR spectra were recorded on a Varian VNMRS spectrometer in CDCl at 600 MHz for 1H NMR and 150 MHz for 13C NMR spectra.

Column chromatography was performed with silica gel 60 (70-230 mesh).

Thin layer chromatography was performed with plastic backed plates coated with silica gel F254 and the plates were visualized by spraying with <Compound>vanillin</Compound>/H2SO4 solution followed by warming.

Sample Collection Samples of the <PlantPart>flowers</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Duranta erecta</Synonym> were collected from <Location>Sta Rosa</Location>, <Location>Laguna</Location>, <Location>Plippines</Location> in January 2015.

The samples were authenticated at the Botany Division, Philippine National Museum.

General Isolation Procedure A glass column 12 inches in height and 0.5 inch internal diameter was used for the chromatography.

The crude extracts were fractionated by silica gel chromatography using increasing proportions of <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 at 10% increment by volume as eluents.

Five milliliter fractions were collected.

All fractions were monitored by thin layer chromatography.

Fractions with spots of the same Rf values were combined and rechromatographed in appropriate Consolacion Y. Ragasa et al Der Pharmacia Lettre, 2016, 8 (19):234-236.

236 Scholar Research Library solvent systems until TLC pure isolates were obtained.

Final purifications were conducted using Pasteur pipettes as columns.

One milliliter fractions were collected.

Isolation of the chemical constituents from the <PlantPart>Flowers</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Duranta erecta</Synonym> The air-dried <Synonym>Duranta erecta</Synonym> <PlantPart>flowers</PlantPart> (70 g) were <Preparation>ground</Preparation> in a blender, soaked in CH2Cl2 for <Compound>phytyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, days and then <Preparation>filtered</Preparation>.

The solvent was evaporated under vacuum to afford a crude <Preparation>extract</Preparation> <Compound>oleanolic acid</Compound>, 86 g) which was chromatographed using increasing proportions of <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 in 10% increments by volume.

The 20% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed using 7.5% EtOAc in petroleum ether.

The less polar fractions were combined and rechromatographed using 7.5% EtOAc in petroleum ether to afford <Compound>phytyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, mg).

The more polar fractions were combined and rechromatographed using 7.5% EtOAc in petroleum ether to afford <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, (5 mg).

The 30% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed (2 ) using 15% EtOAc in petroleum ether to afford a mixture of <Compound>alphaamyrin</Compound>, and <Compound>beta-amyrin</Compound>, (6 mg) after washing with petroleum ether.

The 90% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed (2 ) using CH3CN:Et2O:CH2Cl2 (0.5:0.5:9, v/v) to afford <Compound>oleanolic acid</Compound>, <Compound>phytyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, mg) after washing with petroleum ether..

Silica gel chromatography of the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of the <PlantPart>leaves</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Duranta erecta</Synonym> yielded 1-4b.

The NMR spectra of <Compound>oleanolic acid</Compound>, are in accordance with data reported in the literature for <Compound>olenolic acid</Compound> ; <Compound>alphaamyrin</Compound>, for <Compound>alpha-amyrin</Compound> ; and <Compound>beta-amyrin</Compound>, for <Compound>betaamyrin</Compound> ; <Compound>phytyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, for <Compound>phytyl fatty acid esters</Compound> ; and <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, for <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>.

The 3:1 ratio of the mixture of <Compound>alphaamyrin</Compound> and <Compound>beta-amyrin</Compound> was deduced from the integrations and intensities of the 1H NMR resonances for the olefinic protons of <Compound>alphaamyrin</Compound>, at 5.24 (t, J = <Compound>phytyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, Hz, H-12) and <Compound>beta-amyrin</Compound>, at 5.27 (t, J = <Compound>phytyl fatty acid esters</Compound>, Hz, H-12).

. A research grant from the Science Foundation through the University Research Coordination Office of De La Salle University is gratefully acknowledged.