www.ijpcr.comAvailable online at International Journal of Pharmaceutical and Clinical Research 2017; 9: 218-220 ISSN 1556 Research Article *Author for Correspondence: consolacion.ragasa@dlsu.edu.ph <class>Triterpene</class> and <class>Sterols</class> from <plant>Premna nauseosa</plant> Blanco Phelan G <compound>Apostol</compound>,, Mark Anthony G Fran,4, Chien-Chang Shen, Consolacion Y Ragasa,6 1Chemistry Department, De La Salle University, 2401 <loc>Taft Avenue</loc>, <loc>Manila</loc> 1004, <loc>Philippines</loc> 2Food and Drug Administration, <loc>Civic Drive</loc>, Filinvest Corporate City, <loc>Alabang</loc>, <loc>Muntinlupa City</loc> 1781, <loc>Philippines</loc> 3The Graduate School, Thomas Aquinas Research Complex TARC Bldg., University of Santo Tomas, Espana Blvd., <loc>Sampaloc</loc>, <loc>Manila</loc> City 1008, <loc>Philippines</loc> 4College of Science, Pamantasan ng Lungsod ng Maynila Gen.

 Luna cor.

 Muralla St., Intramuros <loc>Manila</loc> 1002, <loc>Philippines</loc>.

 5National Research Institute of Chinese Medicine, Ministry of Health and Welfare, 155-1, Li Nong St., <loc>Sec</loc>. , <loc>Taipei</loc> 112, <loc>Taiwan</loc> 6Chemistry Department, De La Salle University Science and Technology Complex Leandro V. Locsin Campus, <loc>Binan City</loc>, <loc>Laguna</loc> 4024, <loc>Philippines</loc> Available Online: 25th March, 2017.

Chemical investigation of the <compound>dichloromethane</compound> <prep>extract</prep> of <plant>Premna nauseosa</plant> Blanco afforded <compound>squalene</compound> and a mixture of <compound>beta-sitosterol</compound> and <compound>stigmasterol</compound> in about 6:1 ratio.

 The structures of 1-3 were identified by comparison of their NMR data with literature data.

 Keywords: <plant>Premna nauseosa</plant> Blanco, <family>Verbenaceae</family>, <compound>squalene</compound>, <compound>beta-sitosterol</compound>, <compound>stigmasterol</compound>..

<plant>Premna nauseosa</plant> of the family <family>Verbenaceae</family>, commonly known as <aka>alagau-gubat</aka> is an endemic Philippine plant found in low altitude places in <loc>Luzon</loc>, <loc>Philippines</loc>.

 The <plantpart>leaves</plantpart> of <plant>Premna nauseosa</plant> are said to be a cure for <bodypart>stomach</bodypart> problems.

 There are no reported studies on the chemical constituents of <plant>Premna nauseosa</plant>.

 In an earlier study, the <plantpart>leaf</plantpart> crude ethanolic <prep>extract</prep> of <plant>Premna nauseosa</plant> exhibited an IC50 value of 12.06 g/mL when tested in vitro on colorectal carcinoma (<cell>HCT-116</cell>) using the MTT assay.

 Furthermore, the ethanolic <prep>extract</prep> possessed 78% free radical scavenging activity based on DPPH assay.

 In this study, the <compound>dichloromethane</compound> <prep>extract</prep> of <plant>Premna nauseosa</plant> <plantpart>leaves</plantpart> yielded <compound>squalene</compound> and a mixture of <compound>beta-sitosterol</compound> and <compound>stigmasterol</compound> . The structures of 1-3 are presented in Fig..

This is the first report on the isolation of these compounds from <plant>Premna nauseosa</plant>. MATERIALS AND METHODS General Experimental Procedure NMR spectra were recorded on a Varian VNMRS spectrometer in CDCl at 600 MHz for 1H NMR and 150 MHz for 13C NMR spectra.

 Column chromatography was performed with silica gel 60 (70-230 mesh).

 Thin layer chromatography was performed with plastic backed plates coated with silica gel F254 and the plates were visualized by spraying with <compound>vanillin</compound>/H2SO4 solution followed by warming.

 Sample Collection The <plantpart>leaves</plantpart> of <plant>Premna nauseosa</plant> Blanco were collected from <loc>Brgy</loc>.

 Tulay, <loc>Odiongan</loc>, <loc>Romblon</loc>, <loc>Philippines</loc> in January 2016. The samples were authenticated at the Botany Division, Philippine National Museum.

 General Isolation Procedure A glass column 12 inches in height and 0.5 inch internal diameter was used for the chromatography.

 The crude extracts were fractionated by silica gel chromatography using increasing proportions of <compound>acetone</compound> in CH2Cl2 at 10% increment by volume as eluents.

 Five milliliter fractions were collected.

 All fractions were monitored by thin layer chromatography.

 Fractions with spots of the same Rf values were combined and rechromatographed in appropriate solvent systems until TLC pure isolates were obtained.

 Final purifications were conducted using Pasteur pipettes as columns.

 One milliliter fractions were collected.

 Isolation of the Chemical Constituents from the <plantpart>Leaves</plantpart> of <plant>Premna nauseosa</plant>.

 The air-dried <plant>Premna nauseosa</plant> <plantpart>leaves</plantpart> (298.6 g) were <prep>ground</prep> in a blender, soaked in CH2Cl2 for <compound>stigmasterol</compound> days and then <prep>filtered</prep>.

 The solvent was evaporated under vacuum to afford a crude <prep>extract</prep> <compound>stigmasterol</compound> 8 g) which was chromatographed using increasing proportions of <compound>acetone</compound> in CH2Cl2 at 10% increment by volume.

 The CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed using petroleum ether to afford <compound>squalene</compound> (4 mg).

 The 30% <compound>acetone</compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed using 10% EtOAc in petroleum ether.

 Fractions collected from this column were combined and rechromatographed using 15% EtOAc in petroleum ether Phelan et al. / <class>Triterpene</class> and <class>Sterols</class> IJPCR, Volume 9, Issue 3: March 2017 Page 219 Figure 1: Chemical structures of <compound>squalene</compound> , <compound>betasitosterol</compound> and <compound>stigmasterol</compound> from <plant>Premna nauseosa</plant>. to yield a mixture of <compound>beta-sitosterol</compound> and <compound>stigmasterol</compound> (5 mg) after washing with petroleum ether..

Silica gel chromatography of the dichlorometnahe <prep>extract</prep> of the <plantpart>leaves</plantpart> of <plant>Premna nauseosa</plant> afforded <compound>squalene</compound> , <compound>betasitosterol</compound> and <compound>stigmasterol</compound> . The NMR spectra of <compound>squalene</compound> are in accordance with data reported in the literature for <compound>squalene</compound>; <compound>beta-sitosterol</compound> for <compound>beta-sitosterol</compound>; and <compound>stigmasterol</compound> for <compound>stigmasterol</compound>.

 The 6:1 ratio of the mixture of <compound>beta-sitosterol</compound> and <compound>stigmasterol</compound> was deduced from the integrations of the 1H NMR resonances for the olefinic protons of <compound>beta-sitosterol</compound> at 5.33 (dd, J = <compound>squalene</compound> 8, 4. Hz, H-6)4 and <compound>stigmasterol</compound> at 5.33 (dd, J = <compound>squalene</compound> 8, 4. Hz, H-6), 5.13 (dd, J = 9.0, 15. Hz, H-22) and 5.00 (dd, J = 9.0, 15. Hz, H-23)4. Although no biological tests were conducted on the isolated compounds, a literature search of 1-3 revealed that these have diverse bioactivities.

 <compound>Squalene</compound> was reported to significantly suppress colonic ACF formation and crypt multiplicity which strengthened the hypothesis that it possesses chemopreventive activity against colon carcinogenesis.

 It showed cardioprotective effect which is related to inhibition of lipid accumulation by its hypolipidemic properties and/or its <bioact>antioxidant</bioact> properties.

 A recent study reported that <compound>tocotrienols</compound>, carotenoids, <compound>squalene</compound> and coenzyme Q10 have antiproliferative effects on <bodypart>breast</bodypart> cancer cells.

 The preventive and therapeutic potential of <compound>squalene</compound> containing compounds on tumor promotion and regression have been reported.

 A recent review on the bioactivities of <compound>squalene</compound> has been provided. <compound>beta-Sitosterol</compound> was observed to have growth inhibitory effects on human <bodypart>breast</bodypart> <cell>MCF-7</cell> and <cell>MDA-MB-231</cell> adenocarcinoma cells.

 It was shown to be effective for the treatment of benign prostatic hyperplasia.

 It was also reported to attenuate <compound>beta-catenin</compound> and PCNA expression, as well as quench radical in vitro, making it a potential <bioact>anticancer</bioact> drug for colon carcinogenesis.

 It can inhibit the expression of NPC1L1 in the enterocytes to reduce intestinal cholesterol uptake.

 It was reported to induce apoptosis mediated by the activation of ERK and the downregulation of Akt in MCA-102 <compound>murine</compound> fibrosarcoma cells.

 <compound>Stigmasterol</compound> shows therapeutic efficacy against <cell>Ehrlich</cell> ascites carcinoma bearing mice while conferring protection against cancer induced altered physiological conditions.

 It lowers plasma cholesterol levels, inhibits intestinal cholesterol and plant <class>sterol</class> absorption, and suppresses hepatic cholesterol and classic <compound>bile acid</compound> synthesis in Winstar as well as WKY rats.

 Other studies reported that <compound>stigmasterol</compound> showed cytostatic activity against Hep-2 and McCoy cells, markedly inhibited tumour promotion in two stage carcinogenesis experiments, exhibited antimutagenic, topical antiinflammatory, antiosteoarthritic and <bioact>antioxidant</bioact> activities..

In an earlier study, the ethanolic <prep>extract</prep> of <plant>Premna nauseosa</plant> exhibited high <bioact>cytotoxic</bioact> activity against colorectal carcinoma (<cell>HCT-116</cell>) and free radical scavenging activity based on DPPH assay.

 The <compound>dichloromethane</compound> <prep>extract</prep> of <plant>Premna nauseosa</plant> yielded <compound>squalene</compound> , <compound>beta-sitosterol</compound> and <compound>stigmasterol</compound> . Compounds 15 and 212 were reported to possess chemopreventive activity against colon carcinogenesis, while <compound>beta-sitosterol</compound> was also shown to quench radical in vitro.

 Thus, <compound>squalene</compound> and <compound>beta-sitosterol</compound> could contribute to the <bioact>cytotoxic</bioact> activity of <plant>Premna nauseosa</plant> against <cell>HCT-116</cell>. Furthermore, <compound>beta-sitosterol</compound> could be partly responsible for the free radical scavenging activity of <plant>Premna nauseosa</plant>..

A research grant from the De La Salle University Science Foundation through the University Research Coordination Office is gratefully acknowledged. nauseosa on January 15, 2016. <compound>beta-sitosterol</compound> Fran MAG. (2015). <bioact>Cytotoxic</bioact> and <bioact>Antioxidant</bioact> Screening of Selected Plants of <loc>Romblon</loc>: An Input for Phelan et al. / <class>Triterpene</class> and <class>Sterols</class> IJPCR, Volume 9, Issue 3: March 2017 Page 220 Information Material.

 Unpublished masters thesis, Pamantasan ng Lungsod ng Maynila, Intramuros, <loc>Manila</loc>, <loc>Philippines</loc>.

 <compound>stigmasterol</compound> Ng VAS, Agoo EM, Shen C-C, Ragasa CY.

 Chemical constituents of Cycas sancti-lasallei. J Appl Pharm Sci 2015a; 5(Suppl <compound>squalene</compound> :12-17. 4. Ragasa CY, Lorena GS, Mandia EH, Raga DD, Shen C-C. Chemical constituents of <plant>Abrus precatorius</plant>.

 Amer J Essent Oils Nat Prod 2013; 1:7-10. 5. Rao CV, Mark HLN, Reddy RS.

 Chemopreventive effect of <compound>squalene</compound> on colon cancer.

 Carcinogenesis 1998; 19:287-290. 6. Farvin KHS, Anandan R, Hari S, Kumar S, Shing KS, Mathew S, Sankar TV, Nair PGV.

 Cardioprotective effect of <compound>squalene</compound> on lipid profile in isoprenalineinduced myocardial infarction in rats. J Med Food 2006; 9:531-536. 7. Loganathan R, Selvaduray KR, Nesaretnam K, Radhakrisnan A. Differential and antagonistic effects of palm <compound>tocotrienols</compound> and other phytonutrients (carotenoids, <compound>squalene</compound> and coenzyme Q10) on <bodypart>breast</bodypart> cancer cells in vitro. J Oil Palm Res 2013; 25:208-215. 8. Desai KN, Wei H, Lamartiniere CA.

 The preventive and therapeutic potential of the squalene-containing compound, <loc>Roidex</loc>, on tumor promotion and regression.

 Cancer Lett 1996; 101:93-96. 9. Ronco AL, De Stfani E. <compound>Squalene</compound>: a multi-task link in the crossroads of cancer and aging.

 Functional Foods in Health and Disease 2013; 3:462-476. 10. Awad AB, Chinnman M, Fink CS, Bradford PG <compound>BetaSitosterol</compound> activates Fas signaling in human <bodypart>breast</bodypart> cancer cells.

 Phytomed 2007; 14:747-754. 11. Jayaprakasha GK, Mandadi KK, Poulose SM, Jadegoud Y, Gowda GA, Patil BS.

 Inhibition of colon cancer growth and <bioact>antioxidant</bioact> activity of bioactive compounds from <plant>Poncirus trifoliate</plant> (L.) Raf.

 Bioorg Med Chem 2007; 15:4923-4932. 12. Baskar AA, Ignacimuthu S, Paulraj G, Numair K. Chemopreventive potential of <compound>beta-sitosterol</compound> in experimental colon cancer model-an in vitro and in vivo study. <loc>BMC</loc> Comp Alt Med 2010; 10:24. 13. Jesch ED, Seo JM, Carr TP, Lee JY.

 <class>Sitosterol</class> reduces messenger RNA and protein expression levels of Niemann-Pick C1-like <compound>squalene</compound> in FHs 74 Int cells.

 Nutr Res 2009; 29(12):859-66. 14. Moon DO, Kyeong Jun L, Yung HC, Gi-Young K. Int <compound>Immunopharmacol</compound> 2007; 7:1044-1053. 15. Ghosh T, Maity TK, Singh J. Evaluation of antitumor activity of <compound>stigmasterol</compound>, a constituent isolated from <plant>Bacopa monnieri</plant> Linn <plantpart>aerial parts</plantpart> against ehrlich ascites carcinoma in mice.

 Orient Pharm Exp Med 2011; 11:41-49. 16. Batta AK, Xu G, Honda A, Miyazaki T, Salen G. <compound>Stigmasterol</compound> reduces plasma cholesterol levels and inhibits hepatic synthesis and intestinal absorption in the rat.

 Metabolism 2006; 55:292-299. 17. Gmez MA, Garca MD, Senz MT.

 Cytostatic activity of <plant>Achillea ageratum</plant> L. Phytother Res 2001; 15:633-634. 18. Kasahara Y, Kumaki K, Katagiri S, Yasukawa K, Yamanouchi S, Takido M. Carthami flos <prep>extract</prep> and its component, <compound>stigmasterol</compound>, inhibit tumour promotion in mouse skin two-stage carcinogenesis.

 Phytother Res 1994; 8:327-331. 19. Lim J-C, Park JH, Budesinsky M, Kasal A, Han Y-H, Koo B-S, Lee S-I, Lee D-U. Antimutagenic constituents from the thorns of <plant>Gleditsia sinensis</plant>.

 Chem Pharm Bull 2005; 53:561-564. 20. Garca MD, Senz MT, Gmez MA, Fernndez MA.

 Topical <bioact>anti-inflammatory</bioact> activity of <class>phytosterols</class> isolated from <plant>Eryngium foetidum</plant> on chronic and acute inflammation models.

 Phytother Res 1999; 13:78- 80. 21. Gabay O, Sanchez C, Salvat C, Chevy F, Breton M, Nourissat G. <compound>Stigmasterol</compound>: a <class>phytosterol</class> with potential anti-osteoarthritic properties.

 Osteoarthritis Cartilage 2010; 18:106-116. 22. Panda S, Jafri M, Kar A, Meheta BK.

 <bodypart>Thyroid</bodypart> inhibitory, antiperoxidative and hypoglycemic effects of <compound>stigmasterol</compound>, isolated from <plant>Butea monosperma</plant>.

 Fitoter 2009; 80:123-126.