Available online on www.ijcpr.com International Journal of Current Pharmaceutical Review and Research; 7; 334-336 ISSN: 0976 822X Research Article *Author for Correspondence: consolacion.ragasa@dlsu.edu.ph <ChemicalClass>Sterol</ChemicalClass> and Lipid from <Synonym>Pleurotus eryngii</Synonym> (DC.) Qul and <Synonym>Flammulina velutipes</Synonym> Cuttis Singer Consolacion Y Ragasa <Compound>trilinolein</Compound>, , Maria Carmen S Tan1, Robert Brkljaa, Sylvia Urban 1Chemistry Department, De La Salle University, <Location>Taft Avenue</Location>, <Location>Manila</Location>, <Location>Philippines</Location>.

Chemistry Department, De La Salle University Science & Technology Complex Leandro V. Locsin Campus, <Location>Binan City</Location>, <Location>Laguna</Location>, <Location>Philippines</Location>.

School of Science (Discipline of Applied Chemistry and Environmental Science), RMIT University (City Campus), <Location>Melbourne</Location> 3001, <Location>Victoria</Location>, <Location>Australia</Location>.

Available Online: 25th December, 2016.

Chemical investigation of the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> extracts of the <PlantPart>fruiting bodies</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Pleurotus eryngii</Synonym> and <Synonym>Flammulina velutipes</Synonym> led to the isolation of <Compound>ergosterol</Compound> .

<Synonym>Pleurotus eryngii</Synonym> also afforded <Compound>trilinolein</Compound> , while <Synonym>Flammulina velutipes</Synonym> also yielded <Compound>triacylglycerol</Compound> .

The structures of <Compound>ergosterol</Compound>, <Compound>trilinolein</Compound>, <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, were identified by comparison of their NMR data with literature data.

Keywords: <Synonym>Pleurotus eryngii</Synonym>, <Family>Pleurotaceae</Family>, <Synonym>Flammulina velutipes</Synonym>, <Family>Physalacriaceae</Family>, <Compound>ergosterol</Compound>, <Compound>trilinolein</Compound>, <Compound>triacylglycerol</Compound>..

<Synonym>Pleurotus eryngii</Synonym>, commonly known as <MedicinalPlant>king oyster mushroom</MedicinalPlant> is sold in supermarkets throughout the <Location>Philippines</Location>.

A number of studies have been conducted on the chemical constituents and biological activities of <Synonym>Pleurotus eryngii</Synonym>.

The ethanol <Preparation>extract</Preparation> of <Synonym>Pleurotus eryngii</Synonym> afforded <Compound>ergosterol peroxide</Compound> which is an inhibitor of osteoclast differentiation.

This <ChemicalClass>sterol</ChemicalClass> exhibited an inhibitory effect in a dose-dependent manner with an inhibition rate of up to 62% with low cytotoxicity.

Activity-guided fractionations led to the isolation of antitumor compound, <Compound>ergosterol peroxide</Compound> from the <PlantPart>fruiting body</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Pleurotus eryngii</Synonym>.

The IC50 of <Compound>ergosterol peroxide</Compound> against human lung cancer cell line (A549) and human ovarian cell line (SK-OV3) were 7 M and 14 M, respectively.

This <ChemicalClass>sterol</ChemicalClass> showed chromosomal DNA fragmentation and arrests G1 phase of the cell division cycle.

Another study reported the isolation of <Compound>5alpha,9alpha-epidioxy-8alpha,14alpha-epoxy-(22E)-ergosta-6,22-dienbeta-ol</Compound>, <Compound>3beta,5alpha-dihydroxyergost-7-en-6-one</Compound>, <Compound>6beta-acetoxy(22E)-ergosta-7,22-diene-3beta,5alpha-diol</Compound>, <Compound>3beta,5alpha-dihydroxy(22E)-ergosta-7,22-dien-6-one</Compound>, <Compound>ergosterol peroxide</Compound>, <Compound>2alpha,5alpha,9alpha-epidioxy-(22E)-ergosta-7,22-diene-3beta,6beta-diol</Compound>, <Compound>5alpha,9alpha-epidioxy-3beta-hydroxy-(22E)-ergosta-7,22-dien-6one</Compound> and <Compound>3beta,5alpha,9alpha-trihydroxy-(22E)-ergosta-7,22-dien-6one</Compound> from <Synonym>Pleurotus eryngii</Synonym> (DC.: FR.

<Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>,

In an additional study the isolation of <Compound>pleurone</Compound>, <Compound>ergosterol</Compound>, (<Compound>24E)-3betahydroxycucurbita-5,24-diene-26-oic acid</Compound> and <Compound>nicotinic acid</Compound> were reported from <Synonym>Pleurotus eryngii</Synonym> var ferulae.

<Synonym>Flammulina velutipes</Synonym>, also known as <MedicinalPlant>Enoki mushroom</MedicinalPlant> are sold in supermarkets throughout the <Location>Philippines</Location>.

Several studies were conducted on the chemical constituents of this mushroom.

An earlier study reported that <Compound>D-arabinitol</Compound>, 9(Z) <Compound>oleic acid</Compound>, 9(Z),12(Z) <Compound>linoleic acid</Compound>, <Compound>ergosta-5,7,22trien-3beta-ol</Compound>, <Compound>5alpha,8alpha-epidioxy-ergosta-6,22-dien-3beta-ol</Compound>, <Compound>3beta,5alpha,9alpha-trihydroxy-ergosta-7,22-dien-6-one</Compound>, <Compound>5hydroxymethyl-2-(1-methyl-ethenyl)-1-cyclohexanol</Compound>, <Compound>1,3-dilinolein</Compound> and <Compound>hemisceramide</Compound> were isolated from <Synonym>Flammulina velutipes</Synonym>.

Furthermore, <Compound>5alpha,8alpha-epidioxy-(22E,24R)ergost-6,22-dien-3beta-ol</Compound>, <Compound>ergosta-4,6,8(14),22-tetraen-3one</Compound>, <Compound>sterpuric acid</Compound>, <Compound>mannitol</Compound> and <Compound>ribitol</Compound> were obtained from this mushroom.

In another study, <Synonym>Flammulina velutipes</Synonym> <ChemicalClass>sterols</ChemicalClass> (FVS) which mainly consisted of <Compound>ergosterol</Compound> (54.78%), <Compound>22,23-dihydroergosterol</Compound> (27.94%) and <Compound>ergost-8(14)-ene3beta-ol</Compound> were reported to exhibit cytotoxicity against U251 cells (IC50=23.42 g/mL)7, This study is part of our research on the chemical constituents of Philippine edible mushrooms.

We earlier reported the isolation of <Compound>ergosterol</Compound>, <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound> and <Compound>fatty acid methyl esters</Compound> from <Synonym>Pleurotus djamor</Synonym> We also reported the isolation of <Compound>ergosterol</Compound>, <Compound>ergosterol peroxide</Compound>, <Compound>cerevisterol</Compound>, <Compound>palmitic acid</Compound>, <Compound>stearic acid</Compound>, <Compound>linoleic acid</Compound>, and <Compound>oleic acid</Compound>, and <Compound>dilinoleoyloleoylglycerol</Compound> from P. florida.

Furthermore, we recently reported the isolation of <Compound>ergosterol</Compound> and <Compound>trilinolein</Compound> from Lentinus edodes.

We report herein the isolation of <Compound>ergosterol</Compound> and <Compound>trilinolein</Compound> from the <PlantPart>fruiting bodies</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Pleurotus eryngii</Synonym>, while the <PlantPart>fruiting bodies</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Flammulina velutipes</Synonym> yielded <Compound>ergosterol</Compound>, and <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound> .

The structures of <Compound>ergosterol</Compound>, <Compound>trilinolein</Compound>, <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, are presented in Fig..

MATERIALS AND METHODS General Experimental Procedure 1H (500 MHz) and 13C (125 MHz) NMR spectra were acquired in CDCl on a 500 MHz Agilent DD2 NMR spectrometer with referencing to solvent signals ( 7.26 and 77.0 ppm).

Column chromatography was performed with silica gel 60 (70-230 mesh).

Thin layer chromatography was performed with plastic backed plates coated with silica gel F254 and the plates were visualized Consolacion et al. / <ChemicalClass>Sterol</ChemicalClass> and Lipid IJCPR, Volume 7, Issue 5, NovemberDecember 2016 Page 335 by spraying with <Compound>vanillin</Compound>/H2SO4 solution followed by warming.

Sample Collection The samples werepurchased from a supermarket in Metro <Location>Manila</Location>, <Location>Philippines</Location> in January 2016.

They were authenticated as <Synonym>Pleurotus eryngii</Synonym> (DC.) Qul and <Synonym>Flammulina velutipes</Synonym> Curtis Singer at the Botany Division, Philippine National Museum.

General Isolation Procedure A glass column 18 inches in height and <Compound>ergosterol</Compound>, 0 inch internal diameter was packed with silica gel.

The crude extracts were fractionated by silica gel chromatography using increasing proportions of <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 (10%increment) as eluents.

Fifty milliliter fractions were collected.

All fractions were monitored by thin layer chromatography.

Fractions with spots of the same Rf values were combined and rechromatographed in appropriate solvent systems until TLC pure isolates were obtained.

A glass column 12 inches in height and 0.5 inch internal diameter was used for the rechromatography.

Two milliliter fractions were collected.

Final purifications were conducted using Pasteur pipettes as columns.

One milliliter fractions were collected.

Isolation of the chemical constituents of the <PlantPart>fruiting bodies</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Pleurotus eryngii</Synonym> The freeze-dried <PlantPart>fruiting bodies</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Pleurotus eryngii</Synonym> (580 g) were <Preparation>ground</Preparation> in a blender, soaked in CH2Cl2 for <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, days and then <Preparation>filtered</Preparation>.

The solvent was evaporated under vacuum to afford a crude <Preparation>extract</Preparation> <Compound>ergosterol</Compound>, 36 g) which was chromatographed using increasing proportions of <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 at 10% increment.

The CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed <Compound>trilinolein</Compound>, ) using 5% EtOAc in petroleum ether to afford <Compound>trilinolein</Compound>, (6 mg).

The 30% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed <Compound>trilinolein</Compound>, ) using 15% EtOAc in petroleum ether to yield <Compound>ergosterol</Compound>, (9 mg) after washing with petroleum ether.

Isolation of the chemical constituents of the <PlantPart>fruiting bodies</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Flammulina velutipes</Synonym> The freeze-dried <PlantPart>fruiting bodies</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Flammulina velutipes</Synonym> (300 g) were <Preparation>ground</Preparation> in a blender, soaked in CH2Cl2 for <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, days and then <Preparation>filtered</Preparation>.

The solvent was evaporated under vacuum to afford a crude <Preparation>extract</Preparation> <Compound>trilinolein</Compound>, 03 g) which was chromatographed using increasing proportions of <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 at 10% increment.

The CH2Cl2 to 20% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> fractions were combined and rechromatographed <Compound>trilinolein</Compound>, ) using 5% EtOAc in petroleum ether to afford <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, (7 mg).

The 30% <Compound>acetone</Compound> in CH2Cl2 fraction was rechromatographed <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, ) using 15% EtOAc in petroleum ether to yield <Compound>ergosterol</Compound>, (5 mg) after washing with petroleum ether..

Silica gel chromatography of the <Compound>dichloromethane</Compound> extracts of the <PlantPart>fruiting bodies</PlantPart> of <Synonym>Pleurotus eryngii</Synonym> and <Synonym>Flammulina velutipes</Synonym> led to the isolation of <Compound>ergosterol</Compound>, <Compound>trilinolein</Compound>, <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, . The NMR spectra of <Compound>ergosterol</Compound>, are in accordance with data reported in the literature for <Compound>ergosterol</Compound>; <Compound>trilinolein</Compound>, for <Compound>trilinolein</Compound>; and <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, for <Compound>triacylglycerol</Compound>.

<Compound>The fatty acids</Compound> attached to the <Compound>glycerol</Compound> in <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, of <Synonym>Flammulina velutipes</Synonym> were identified as <Compound>linolenic acid</Compound>, <Compound>linoleic acid</Compound> and <Compound>oleic acid</Compound> based on resonance intensities for the methyl triplet at 0.96 (t, J = 7. Hz), the double allylic methylenes at <Compound>trilinolein</Compound>, 78 and the olefinic protons at 5.34 (m) for the <Compound>linolenic acid</Compound>; methyl triplet at 0.86 (t, J = 6. Hz), the double allylic <Compound>methylene</Compound> at <Compound>trilinolein</Compound>, 80 and the olefinic protons at 5.34 (m) for the <Compound>linoleic acid</Compound>; and the methyl triplet at 0.86 (t, J = 6. Hz) and the olefinic protons at 5.34 (m) for the <Compound>oleic acid</Compound>.

Literature search revealed that <Compound>ergosterol</Compound>, <Compound>trilinolein</Compound>, <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound>, exhibited diverse biological activities.

A study reported that <Compound>ergosterol</Compound> provides significant protection against the promotion of <BodyPart>bladder</BodyPart> tumor induced by many types of promoters in the environment.

Moreover, the <Compound>ergosterol</Compound> content of brown and white button mushrooms correlated with their <BioAct>antioxidant</BioAct> activities.

In another study, <Compound>ergosterol</Compound>, was reported to have the capability to inhibit lipid peroxidation.

<Compound>Trilinolein</Compound> exhibits protective effects against cardiovascular disorders.

<Compound>Trilinolein</Compound> also inhibits ischemia-induced ventricular arrhythmias and <Compound>Trilinolein</Compound> exhibits anti-oxidant effect.

<Compound>Trilinolein</Compound> was also reported to inhibit the growth of human non-small cell lung carcinoma A549 and induce apoptosis in a doseand timedependent manne.

Another study reported that <Compound>triglycerides</Compound> showed a direct relationship between toxicity and increasing unsaturation, which in turn correlated with increasing susceptibility to oxidation.

<Compound>Linoleic acid</Compound> belongs to the <Compound>omega-6 fatty acids</Compound>.

<Compound>Linoleic acid</Compound> was reported be a strong anticarcinogen in a number of animal models.

<Compound>Linoleic acid</Compound> reduces risk of colon and <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> cancer and lowers cardiovascular disease risk and inflammations.

<Compound>Triacylglycerols</Compound> exhibited <BioAct>antimicrobial</BioAct> activity against <Synonym>S. aureus</Synonym>, <Synonym>Pleurotus aeruginosa</Synonym>, <Synonym>B. subtilis</Synonym>, <Synonym>C. albicans</Synonym>, and <Synonym>T. mentagrophytes</Synonym>.

Another study reported that <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound> showed a direct Figure 1: Chemical structures of <Compound>ergosterol</Compound> and <Compound>trilinolein</Compound> from <Synonym>Pleurotus eryngii</Synonym> and <Compound>triacylglycerols</Compound> from <Synonym>Flammulina velutipes</Synonym>.

Consolacion et al. / <ChemicalClass>Sterol</ChemicalClass> and Lipid IJCPR, Volume 7, Issue 5, NovemberDecember 2016 Page 336 relationship between toxicity and increasing unsaturation, which in turn correlated with increasing susceptibility to oxidation.

<Compound>Linoleic acid</Compound> belongs to the <Compound>omega-6 fatty acids</Compound>.

<Compound>Linoleic acid</Compound> was reported to be a strong anticarcinogen in a number of animal models.

<Compound>Linoleic acid</Compound> reduces the risk of colon and <BodyPart>breast</BodyPart> cancer and lowers cardiovascular disease risk and inflammations.

Linolenic and linoleic acids inhibited parasites growth by 70% and 64% respectively, against <Synonym>Pleurotus berghei</Synonym> using the 4-day suppressive test.

The two compounds, when used in combination, inhibited the parasites by 96% on day 4 of treatment..

A research grant from the De La Salle University Science Foundation through the University Research Coordination Office is gratefully acknowledged.